<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Gospel-separation separated from its abuses; or The saints guide in Gospel-fellowship. Whereby they may be directed not onely to preserve the purity, but withall the unity of Gospel-worship: by a well-wisher to Sions purity and unity, R.L. Imprimatur. Joseph Caryl.</title>
            <author>Lawrence, Richard, d. 1684.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1657</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 254 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 89 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A88816</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L676</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1613_5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R202679</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862882</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862882</idno>
            <idno type="VID">115061</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A88816)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115061)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 204:E1613[5])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Gospel-separation separated from its abuses; or The saints guide in Gospel-fellowship. Whereby they may be directed not onely to preserve the purity, but withall the unity of Gospel-worship: by a well-wisher to Sions purity and unity, R.L. Imprimatur. Joseph Caryl.</title>
                  <author>Lawrence, Richard, d. 1684.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[32], 141 [i.e. 140], [4] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Giles Calvert at the Black Spread Eagle at the west end of Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1657.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Rich. Lawrence.</note>
                  <note>With two final advertisement leaves.</note>
                  <note>P. 140 misnumbered 141.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "8ber: [i.e. October] 20".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian union --  Anglican Communion --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:115061:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>GOSPEL-SEPARATION <hi>Separated from its Abuſes;</hi> OR THE Saints Guide IN <hi>GOSPEL-FELLOWSHIP.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>WHEREBY They may be directed not onely to preſerve the Purity, but withall the Unity of GOSPEL-WORSHIP:</p>
            <p>By a well-wiſher to <hi>Sions</hi> Purity and Unity, <hi>R. L.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Mercy and Truth have met together, Righteouſneſs and Peace have kiſſed each other,
<bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal. 85.10.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Therefore love the Truth and Peace,
<bibl>
                  <hi>Zach. 8.19.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="lat">
                  <body>
                     <div type="imprimatur">
                        <p>Imprimatur.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>JOSEPH CARYL.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Giles Calvert</hi> at the Black Spread Eagle at the Weſt end of <hi>Pauls,</hi> 1657.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:115061:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:115061:2"/>
            <head>TO HIS EXCELLENCY <hi>Charls Fleetwood</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr> Lord Deputy of IRELAND.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hough the Truth aſſerted by this little Treatiſe have but few Friends (amongſt whom you deſerve to be numbered in the firſt rank) yet is it able to plead its own cauſe; for where-ever its abſence is, there wants no Arguments to prove the worth of its pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence;
<pb facs="tcp:115061:3"/>
for as the Puritie of the Goſpel may be eſteemed in the myſtical Body of Chriſt as its life blood; ſo its Unity may be next eſteemed as its health; and ſtrength; and life without health, is but a lingring death; but I am perſwaded I need not ſpend time to beget in you a love to this Truth; you have evidenced the ſincerity of your love thereto, and therein I hope have taſted of <hi>that fruit of righteouſneſs which is ſown in peace of them that make peace,</hi> Jam. 3.18.</p>
            <p>The reaſon why Contention and divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion have been more natural to Gods people then union in all ages, is, becauſe it is more naturally ſuitable to their unregenerate part; therefore thoſe duties and graces that moſt croſſe the luſts of the fleſh, muſt neceſſarily be attended with moſt difficulty and oppoſition; but to bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance that, they are alſo attended with pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable inward comfort and peace; and therefore (my Lord) though impoſing, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing principles and ſpirits do cry out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you, as the injurious <hi>Iſraelites</hi> did againſt <hi>Moſes, Exod.</hi> 2.14. yet ceaſe not to plead with them, <hi>Ye are Brethren, why do
<pb facs="tcp:115061:3"/>
ye wrong one another;</hi> though it may coſt you dear at the preſent, yet conſider the Lord that made it up to him, is able to do ſo to you.</p>
            <p>Among the reſt of thoſe excellent prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples the Lord hath born an approving teſtimony unto in the day of his glorious power, none have been attended with more ſignal evidences of his preſence with, and delight in then this pleaded for. Moſt diſowned inſtruments that have tendred their ſervice to the Lord in the Work of this Generation, have profeſt and declared a love to Gods ways and people; but therein have confined their care &amp; affection to a part if not the leaſt ſpiritual part of them, which the Lord took ſo unkindly at their hands, that he viſibly removed the Tabernacle of his preſence from among them, and choſe the ſame people deſpiſed and ſlighted by them, to be the inſtruments of his praiſe and glory, in the great work he hath done for his people in theſe Nations; And eaſie it is to demonſtrate (if it were not too large a diſcourſe for an Epiſtle) that as thoſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſo ſingularly owned by the Lord, have
<pb facs="tcp:115061:4"/>
declined &amp; abated in this principle, ſo hath the Lord withdrawn from them, and left them to that deſtraction and miſerable confuſion they are at this day involved in; as if the Lord ſhould ſay, if you with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw your equal reſpect and affection from any of my people, I will withdraw mine from you.</p>
            <p>And do but well weigh and conſider the viſible principles, and frame of ſpirit of ſuch perſons, who are vehemently driving on the intereſt of ſome part of Gods people (under ſome peculiar notion they have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived of the truth or work of the Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) in oppoſition to the reſt; (that are not like-minded. And ye may obſerve a viſible inconſiſtency in their principles and practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, to the obtaining or ſecuring the very things they pretend for.</p>
            <p>That my Lord, it is not onely your praiſe, but your mercy, that your heart is kept in an even frame towards all the Lords people in this day in which ſo many emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Profeſſors are through temptation and ſtumbling blocks laid in their way by the weakneſs and frailties of ſome of the Lords
<pb facs="tcp:115061:4"/>
people, growing weary and faint in their minds, as to the ſtedfaſt practice of, and impartial reſpect to Saints as ſuch; and to be good in bad times, is the beſt teſtimony of goodneſs from a good principle. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as your diſcouragements and oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on encreaſe, labor to encreaſe in your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence and diligence; though you may have War without, you may have Peace within.</p>
            <p>And of all dangers be moſt watchful a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt heart-riſings, and alienation of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection towards ſuch who are contrary-minded to you herein; that is the ſtone many at this day are ſtumbling on. They meaſure out their reſpect and affection to Saints proportionably to that reſpect and affection they or their principles receive from them, whereas the cheif excellency of this principle above others lieth in this dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, that it can extend reſpect to others upon the account of duty to Chriſt, though diſreſpect on the account of different opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on be returned to them again; for uniting principles muſt be attended with the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of uniting Graces, if they intend to be ſucceſsful in uniting work.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:115061:5"/>That the Lord may guide you in all your ſtreights, ſupport you under all your burthens, and render into your boſom plentiful returns of all that kindneſs you have ſhewn unto, and weakneſſes you have over-looked in his people, for his Image ſake upon them, is the earneſt prayer of the moſt unworthy of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Excellencies ſincere Servants in</hi> Ireland, RICH. LAWRENCE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:115061:5"/>
            <head>The Author to the Churches of Chriſt in the Dominions of <hi>England, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>To them that are ſanctified in Chriſt Jeſus called to be Saints,</hi> 1 Cor. 1.1. And to all the faithful in Chriſt Jeſus; with all that in every place call upon the name of Jeſus Chriſt our Lord, Grace and Peace be multiplied.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Beloved in the Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ere is a Treatiſe preſented to your view, which ſtands in much need of your favour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able conſideration, as to the weakneſs, and imperfection in the writing thereof; but if you can over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>look them, the Truth endeavored to be held out thereby is worth your ſtudying, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring after; It is a Truth that hath many Hangers-on, but few faithful Servants; many Goſpel Merchants have been trading for this goodly Pearl, but few have been
<pb facs="tcp:115061:6"/>
willing to go to the price of it; they have had Peace in their mouthes, but War in their hearts, like thoſe <hi>Micah</hi> ſpeaks of <hi>chap 3.5. They bite with their teeth, and cry peace;</hi> but if thou wouldeſt obtain the precious u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of Saints, thou muſt not onely <hi>ſeek peace but purſue it, Pſal. 34.14.</hi> not ſtand ſtill, and call it to thee; but <hi>follow after the things that make for peace, Rom. 14.19.</hi> If the peace of God once rule in thy heart, it will <hi>guide thy feet into this way of peace;</hi> this work of peace will ſurely attend thy ſoul with the comforts and joy of peace; nay, <hi>the Lord himſelf ſhall give you peace always by all means,</hi> as in <hi>2 Theſſ. 3.16.</hi> If thou wouldeſt have thy ſoul proſper, <hi>Pray for the peace of Jeruſalem, they ſhall proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per that</hi> (ſo) <hi>love her;</hi> nay, if thou wouldeſt have <hi>Sion</hi> proſper, <hi>ſay Peace be within thy wals, and</hi> (then) <hi>proſperitie ſhall be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in her Pallaces</hi> (and therefore) <hi>for thy brethren and companions ſake ſay, Peace be within thee;</hi> (and) <hi>becauſe of the houſe of the Lord our God, I will ſeek thy good,</hi> as in <hi>Pſal. 122.6, 7, 8, 9.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If after you have peruſed this Diſcourſe
<pb facs="tcp:115061:6"/>
you ſhall obſerve there are many conſiderable Objections againſt the thing preſt unſpoken to; that I admit; I do not expect theſe few weak Lines ſhould anſwer all Objections in a controverſie of this weight, neither do I judge my ſelf able to anſwer them, but am aſſured there are well wiſhers to this Truth, that are able to proceed. Therefore if theſe Lines may but tend to awaken and ſtir up the people of God to enquire after this <hi>Truth;</hi> and to allow that the laboring after <hi>Saints Union,</hi> is not only a <hi>Dutie,</hi> but a <hi>great</hi> and <hi>weighty Duty,</hi> and to be numbered in the firſt Rank of Chriſtian Duties, I have my aim; for that would prepare the hearts of Saints for Unity, and make the work of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moving obstructions, and reſolving parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular caſes, much more eaſie.</p>
            <p>For many of Gods people do already, and more will be daily diſcerning the inconſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency of the principles they walk by to Goſpel-proſperity; unity doth as naturally fore-run Glory to Chriſts Church, as health doth ſtrength, or light heat.</p>
            <p>Therefore the main deſign of Satan at this day is to prevent Goſpel-Glory, by obſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:115061:7"/>
Goſpel-Unity; but the more the ſpirit of ſtrife and diviſion ſtruggles againſt this work, let it provoke you the more to ſet to all your ſtrength to promote it; the Lord doth not onely require that his people ſhould be faithful unto, but valiant for the Truth up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on earth.</p>
            <p>Shall Quakers and ſuch like rigid cenſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious dividing principled people compaſs ſea and land, and conſume their estates to make common purſes in order to the promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and carrying on their ridiculous princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of diviſion and confuſion? and ſhall thoſe who pretend the Eſpouſing the univerſal in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of Saints as ſuch, be <hi>Ephraim</hi>-like, <hi>a ſilly Dove without heart?</hi> as their dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence and painfulneſs do now upbraid us, ſo I fear it will in the great day riſe up in judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt us.</p>
            <p>It was good Mr. <hi>Burroughs</hi> complaint in his time, when the ſpirit of diviſion was but in its infancy, That there were many would cry Loe the Thief, but who ſtopt him? So ſaints are many at this day will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moan ſuch diviſions, and make ſad com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints of it one to another when they
<pb facs="tcp:115061:7"/>
meet; but how few have ſet themſelves to ſtudy and propagate uniting principles; which I truſt the Lord will ſet upon the hearts of ſome who he hath ſo eminently principled and qualified for the work; that the friends of this precious Truth may not have cauſe above all the reſt of Truths Favorites to complain with the Prophet in its behalf; <hi>There is none to guide her among all the Sons whom ſhe hath brought forth, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is there any that taketh her by the hand, of all the ſons which ſhe hath brought up,</hi> Iſa. <hi>51.18.</hi> Nay, is there not rather cauſe for this Truth to take up the Lords complaint, Iſa. <hi>1.2. I have nouriſhed and brought up children, and they have rebelled againſt me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Principle hath been dealt withal by ſome of its Favourites, as <hi>Saul</hi> dealt with <hi>David,</hi> who honoured and imbraced him in his camp, and hated and baniſhed him his Court; yet bleſſed be the Lord there are ſome <hi>Jonathaas</hi> to ſtand up and ſay, <hi>What evil hath he done?</hi> whoſe ſouls are knit to this principle, as the ſoul of <hi>Jonathan</hi> was to <hi>David,</hi> who will not be afraid to anſwer
<pb facs="tcp:115061:8"/>
impoſing and dividing principles as <hi>Moſes</hi> anſwered <hi>Pharoah,</hi> Exod. <hi>10.9. We will go with our young and with our old, with our Sons and with our Daughters, with our Flocks and with our Herds will we go, for we muſt hold a Feaſt unto the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pharoah</hi> would have put off <hi>Moſes</hi> with the liberty and freedom of ſome part of Gods people, <hi>Go you that are men to ſerve the Lord</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ver. 11.</hi> No ſaith <hi>Moſes,</hi> Church deliverances from bondage &amp; opreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion muſt be univerſal deliverances; other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe how ſhould we hold a feaſt to the Lord? can part of us rejoyce in our Liberties as long as other part is under bondage and oppreſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? No, we must either all go together, or all ſtay together; all rejoyce together, or all mourn together; therefore <hi>we will not leave a hoof behind us, ver. 26.</hi> Now this ſpirit in <hi>Moſes,</hi> is the true nature of this Goſpel-principle; it will not own any deliverance from oppreſsion and impoſition of conſcience contrived and propoſed by men, to anſwer the deſign of Gods deliverance to his people, untill it include the common Goſpel Liberty due to all Saints, and that in all their neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb facs="tcp:115061:8"/>
concernments, though it may out of tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs with <hi>David, 1 Sam. 30.10.</hi> leave ſome of the weak and feeble behind in the work of War and danger, yet all must have an equal ſhare of the ſpoil, whether the Sons of <hi>Belial</hi> will or no, as in <hi>ver. 24.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It's the faithfulleſt and impartialleſt Stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard to truſt with the Saints common ſtock that can be found on earth: there ſhall be no cauſe of complaint ſo far as its power reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth; every one of <hi>Sions</hi> children ſhall have an equal ſhare of thoſe common mercies and priviledges their Heavenly Father appoints for them: And therefore whatſoever opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or way thou art of, conſiſting with ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briety and holineſs, this principle, if thou doſt promote it, will take equal care, and make equal proviſion for thy Chriſtian liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and encouragement, that if thou beeſt a favourer of Saints proſperity, labor to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with this common friend of theirs, it will teach thee how to obſerve and own the ſhining beauty of grace in Saints through the darkeſt cloud of thoſe common errors and miſtakes that the oppoſite principle ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders them ſo unlovely and deformed one to another by.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:115061:9"/>And let not the homely and mean attire this Truth ſalutes thee in, make it leſs accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table; if the Author had had better, it ſhould not have worn ſo bad; but Beauty is Beauty though clothed in rags. The enſuing Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe is rather intended to tell thee there is ſuch a Principle accommodated with ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Qualifications, and to provoke thee to enquire after it, and endeavor acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance with it, then to give the an exact de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of it; But I ſhall ſubmit what fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows to thy favorable cenſure, and cloſe with the words of <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Philippians,</hi> c. <hi>2.</hi> v. <hi>1, to 6. If there be therefore any conſolation in Chriſt, if any comfort of love, if any fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip of the Spirit, if any bowels and mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cies: Fulfil ye my joy, that ye be like minded having the ſame love, being of one accord, of one mind: Let nothing be done through ſtrife or vain-glory, but in lowlineſs of mind let each eſteem other better then them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. Look not every man on his own things, but every man alſo on the things of others. Let this mind be in you, which was alſo in Chrſt Jeſus.</hi> In whom I rest</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Friend and Brother in the Unity and Purity of the Goſpel. R. LAWRENCE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:115061:9"/>
            <head>THE CONTENTS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>TRuth ſeldom found in extreams. p. <hi>1.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Searchers after truth muſt ſuſpect danger of erring on each hand. p. <hi>1. 2.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>As the door of the Church may be opened too wide, ſo it may be ſhut too cloſe. p. <hi>2.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That ſince God hath had a Church on earth, its ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration from the World, and unity in its ſelf, have been required by him as an equal duty. p. <hi>3.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>All the Reformed Churches juſtifie ſeparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. p. <hi>4.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The General notion of a competent knowledge and ſuitable converſation are to intricate and uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain rules to be the viſible bounds of Gods viſible Church. p. <hi>5 6:</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Lord hath alwayes preſerved to his
<pb facs="tcp:115061:10"/>
Church a viſible undiſputable bound betwixt them and the World p. <hi>6. 7, 8.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Circumciſion and Abrahams ſeed in the Type and Antitype was foreordained &amp; eſtabliſhed to be the infallible and everlaſting bounds of Gods viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Church on earth. p. <hi>8, 9.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>It continued ſo unqueſtionable untill Chriſt came; who only changed the Type for the Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>type. p. <hi>9, 10.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Believers ought to make the ſame uſe of the Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>type under the Goſpel the Type ſerved for under the Law. p. <hi>10, 11.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Antitype of Circumciſion and Abrahams ſeed is viſible Grace and Holineſs. p. <hi>11.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Which <hi>Paul</hi> affirms to be the viſible bound of Gods Church, and mark of Gods children, to <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Galatia</hi> &amp;c. p. <hi>11, 12.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Antichriſt ſet up his Kingdom by laying waſte theſe Goſpel Bounds, and Chriſtians open the door to all diviſion and confuſion by not repairing them. p. <hi>13. 14.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Gods Church muſt not only be a City of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but a City with Walls. p. <hi>15.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>All Churches of Saints ought to own one another as true Churches of Chriſt and fellow members of his body. p. <hi>16.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Seven General Heads, from whence the arguments to prove the duty of Saints union, as ſuch, are drawn. p. <hi>17, 18.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:115061:10"/>
                  <hi>1.</hi> From the choyce and approbation of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. p. <hi>19.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Prooving that ſuch as the Father hath manifeſted his viſible Choyce and approbation of, to be his Children, beleevers ought to admit and chuſe to be their Brethren. p: <hi>9</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chriſt and all Saints have but one Father, for which cauſe he was not aſhamed of their infirmities. <hi>p. 20. 21.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2.</hi> General head, is from the choyce and approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of God the Son. p. <hi>22.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chriſt a perfect Emblem of union in his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. p. <hi>22.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chriſt had no helper in his work, nor no partner in his relations to his Church, that Gods deſigne of union in him might be viſible. p. <hi>22.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chriſts chiefe deſigne in aſſuming our nature was a work of union. p. <hi>23.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chriſt walked by uniting Principles, preſt uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting dutyes and commended uniting Graces moſt to his People. p. <hi>23, 24.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chriſt owned all viſible gracious perſons to be mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of his body; therefore ought all Saints to own them ſo. p. <hi>25.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The <hi>3</hi> ſort of Arguments is drawn from the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible choice and approbation of the holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. p. <hi>26.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The moſt infallible rule to chuſe Church-members by, is to follow the track of the Spirits
<pb facs="tcp:115061:11"/>
choyce. p. <hi>27.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The ſanctifying effects of the ſpirit in Saints ought to be admitted as ſufficient teſtimony of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits choyce. p. <hi>27.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>No beleevers without ſome viſible mark of the Spirits choyce. p. <hi>28.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Prooved that this choyce of the ſpirit inſtates a Beleever in all Goſpel relations and Priviledges both in the Kingdom of grace and glory. p. <hi>29.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The <hi>4</hi> general head from whence arguments are drawn, is from the viſible choyce and approbation of the infallible ſervants of God in all ages. p. <hi>30.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>They made the choyce of the Father Son and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit their choyce. p. <hi>30.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>They laid more weight upon the duty and mercy of the Churches union, then upon most others dutyes and mercyes. p. <hi>31.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Paul laid more to heart, and endeavored more to preſerve the Churches union, then all other errors to reform. p. <hi>32, 33, 34.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Argument for Saints union from the whole. p. <hi>35.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The <hi>5</hi> generall Head from whence Arguments are taken, is from the ſeveral Metaphors and Simi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litudes the Church is compared unto in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. p. <hi>35.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>1.</hi> From that of Beleevers being Gods Children, and thereby of his Family, the houſholder of faith. p. <hi>36, 37.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:115061:11"/>
                  <hi>2.</hi> From that of the memberſhip of the ſame body, which relation is inconſiſtent without uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. p. <hi>38, 39.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The <hi>6</hi> general Head is from the ſad conſequences and effects of our preſent diviſions. p <hi>40.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Diviſion is uſually the forerunner of deſtruction, the former preparing the way for the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. p. <hi>40.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Directions to be obſerved in heart ſearchings for the cauſe and cure of Saints diviſions. p. <hi>41, 42, 43.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The ſpirit of diviſion ſometime imployes our graces as well as our Corruptions to divide by. p: <hi>42.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Knowledge and Zeal much imployod at this day by the ſpirit of diviſion in dividing work. p <hi>42. 43.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The ſad effects and conſequences of our diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. p. <hi>44.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>1.</hi> They have obſtructed and hindred reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. p. <hi>44.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2</hi> They have opened the door and let in upon us that overflowing flood of Errors, hereſies and blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies which many Profeſſors among us are car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried away with. p. <hi>45.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>And the continuation of them will make that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe uncurable. p. <hi>46.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>They have been the cauſe of that great decay in the life and power of Religion amongſt us p. <hi>46.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>They have rendered the power and life of godlyneſs contemptible in the eyes of Formaliſts and the carnal multitude. p. <hi>47.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:115061:12"/>
                  <hi>5.</hi> They have rendered the power and purity of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and the profeſſors of it unacceptable in the eyes of authority, and ſeveral perſons in eminent place. p. <hi>48, 49.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>6.</hi> They have brought ſcorn and contempt upon the glorious cauſe of God in theſe Nations, and have ſtained the glorious preſence of God with his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that had once ſtained the pride of all the Glory of the World. p. <hi>50, 51.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>They have been the cauſe of the removal of many eminent worthy Instruments from their Publick Stations, &amp; therby made way for others, no wayes ſpirited nor principled for the places they ſtand in. p. <hi>52.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>8.</hi> They furniſh wicked Magiſtrates and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters with plauſible excuſes, in the exerciſe of their oppreſſing perſecuting principles, <hi>p. 53.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>9.</hi> It is from this ſpirit of diviſion, ſo many emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent gracious perſons in Authority are diſabled from doing that good in their places, they have otherwaies an opportunity for. <hi>p. 53, 54.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The argument for union from the whole. <hi>p. 55.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The <hi>7</hi> General head from whence arguments for Saints union is drawn, is from the evident and great good it would be attended with to Gods Church. <hi>p. 55. 56.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>1.</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity would renew its ſtrength, and make it terrible to its enemies. <hi>p. 56. 57.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2.</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity would renew its purity. <hi>p. 57.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:115061:12"/>
                  <hi>3.</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity would repaire its reputation and eſteem. <hi>p. 57, 58.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4.</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity would renew its growth and increaſe. <hi>p. 59. 60.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>5.</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity would abundantly renew its joy and comfort. <hi>p. 61.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Argument from the whole. <hi>p. 62.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>From whom objections may be expected. <hi>p. 63.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How the objections are ſtated to the Reader. <hi>p. 64.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>1. Object.</hi> Againſt the admiſſion of erroneous per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, anſwered: <hi>p. 65.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>And wherein is proved that perſons holding greater errors then Generally Saints now ſeparate upon, were admitted communion with the Primitive Churches. <hi>p. 65. 66.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Much more reaſon for Gods Miniſters, and Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches to permit Erroneous perſons into commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, now then then. <hi>p. 67.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2. Object.</hi> That this Principle admits all Errors and hereſies in Gods Church, anſwered <hi>p. 67.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>In which anſwer is ſhewn what ſort of errors or erroneous perſons Gods Churches and people ought to withdraw from. <hi>p 68.</hi> to <hi>77.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3. Object.</hi> Raiſed from the <hi>2 Theſſ 3.6.</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning diſorderly walking and diſobedience, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered from <hi>p. 77.</hi> to <hi>83.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:115061:13"/>
                  <hi>4. Object.</hi> Whether the power of Religion can conſiſt without the true form, anſwered. <hi>p, 83. 84</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>5. Object.</hi> From the inconſiſtency of unity, with Principles directly oppoſite one to another, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered. <hi>p. 85.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>6. Object.</hi> Againſt the too generall ſtateing the caſe, and not coming to thoſe particular points, wherein the difference lies, anſwered. <hi>p. 86.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>7. Object.</hi> From the unpoſſibility of Goſpell union untill the fulfilling of the glorious promiſes, relating to the later times, anſwered. <hi>p. 87.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Wherein is proved, that there is as much reaſon to deferr our indeavors after the increaſe of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and purity as after unity. <hi>p. 87. 88.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity muſt precede Glory to Chriſts Church. <hi>p. 88.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Diviſion lies as much in the way of Chriſts glory now, as unbelief did formerly in the way of his grace. <hi>p. 89.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The promiſes of the Churches glory, hold forth an univerſality of peace, purity and glory to all Saints. <hi>p. 89.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The union we are capable of attaining, is not to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from the agreement of our underſtandings, wherein we differ; but in the exerciſe of Grace one towards another, while thus differing. <hi>p. 90.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:115061:13"/>The Lord hath ſupplyed his Church with ſpeciall uniting graces, as the meanes; to aſſiſt them in this ſpeciall uniting duty as the end <hi>p. 91.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>They that begin the work of Saints union by diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puting and reaſoning them into the ſame under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, begin at the wrong end. <hi>p. 92, 93.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Saints too apt to be p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aring upon each others infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities. <hi>p. 94.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> From the prejudice that is in Chriſtians, againſt each others opinions and principles, anſwered. <hi>p. 95.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Directions to ſuch as ſhall ſet upon the work, of Saints union. <hi>p. 96.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>1.</hi> Direction, to labour to informe themſelves of the worth of the mercy and weight of the duty. <hi>p. 95.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2.</hi> Direction to arme themſelves againſt all diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragements and dificulties they muſt expect to meet with therein. <hi>p. 96.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3.</hi> To take heed of exerciſing any of the Spirit of diviſions weapons in the Spirit of unions cauſe. <hi>p. 96. 97.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4.</hi> Labour to obtain a Compaſſionate tender frame of Spirit. <hi>p. 97.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>5;</hi> Set thy affections on thoſe things in Saints, wherein the Image of Chriſt is most viſible. <hi>p. 99.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>6.</hi> Labor to abound in uniting graces. <hi>p. 99. 100.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>7.</hi> Labour to preſerve a proportionable growth of of grace in thy ſoule. <hi>p. 100.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:115061:14"/>
                  <hi>8.</hi> Be moſt exerciſed in thoſe duties, thy place and abilities moſt cal thee unto and fit thee for. <hi>p. 102. 103.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Further directions to Goſpel Miniſters in order to Saints union. <hi>p. 103. 104</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>1.</hi> To be ſenſible of the ſad effects of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions amongſt themſelves. <hi>104. 105. 106.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2.</hi> Then to ſtudy all holy waies of furthering the worke of union. <hi>p. 107.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3.</hi> To change their ſharp cenſurings and blamings into intreatings and beſeechings. <hi>p. 108.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4.</hi> To commend what is good, as well as condemn what is evill in thoſe differing from them. <hi>p 109.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>5.</hi> To lay no more ſtreſs upon the errors reproved, then the Scripture doth. <hi>p. 110.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>6.</hi> To take heed of ſo intailing errors one to another as to charge upon perſons holding ſome leſſer error, with others they deteſt the thoughts of. <hi>p. 111.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>7.</hi> To beware in ſo oppoſing errors controverſall in ſome, they do not thereby commend errors funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall in others. <hi>p. 112.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chriſtians of all hands are too apt to manifeſt more indignation against ſome holy perſons for controverſall errors, differing from them, then againſt viſible ungodlineſs and open prophan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in them that in opinion cloſe with them. <hi>p. 113. 114.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Little helpe to be expected in the work of Saints
<pb facs="tcp:115061:14"/>
union, from ſuch as have much engaged them<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelves in the evil of Saints deviſions. <hi>p. 115.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Therefore thoſe that have the evill of Saints di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions upon their hearts, ought the more to labor for unity. <hi>p. 116.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>1.</hi> By being much in prayer together, and apart for Saints union. <hi>p. 116.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2.</hi> To ſtudy to propagate the principles of this truth, <hi>p. 117.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3.</hi> To ſet up ſome beginnings in Goſpel fellowſhip, upon this Goſpell principle. <hi>p. 117. 118.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> From the averſneſs of particular Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and from thence the danger of further diviſions, upon the promoting this principle, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered. <hi>p. 118, 119, 120.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> From the inconſiſtency of perſons not agreeing in judgment, to walke together in fellowſhip, without obſtructing the mutuall edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of the whole anſwered. <hi>p. 121, 122.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> From the diſadvantage that ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverted deſpiſed truths might receive thereby, anſwered. <hi>p: 123. 124.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> From the oppoſition that may ariſe from ſuch of the godly, as are against all ſeparation, anſwered. <hi>p. 126 127.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:115061:15"/>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> From the difficulty of walking towards ſuch whoſe Converſion though hopeful, may be very doubtfull anſwered. <hi>p. 128. 129.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A cenſorious Spirit, and provoking carriage to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards any profeſſing Chriſtianity, though not viſibly gracious, is blameable and hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. <hi>p. 130.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>What caſes may give a diſpenſation from the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent promoting this or any other pretious truth among ſome people. <hi>p. 131.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>What the droſs and rubiſh of Chriſtians principles and ſpirits are that hinder them from uniting, which Gods Miniſters ſhould be labouring to remove in order to unity, when they can do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe towards it. <hi>p. 132, 133.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chriſtians uſually more curious about the diſh the Lord preſents the bread of life to them in, then the purity and ſpirituallneſs of the bread it ſelfe. <hi>p. 134.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>npoſſible for Saints ever to come to an union wherein they differ, untill they come to a commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion in what they are agreed. <hi>p. 135.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Spirit of diviſion never ſpeakes good of diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Chriſtians one to another. <hi>p. 136</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Spirit of diviſion confines the hearts of Saints, in prayer and praiſes, to a few of Gods people, and ofttimes ſets them in oppoſition one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther at the throne of grace. <hi>p. 137, 138.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>This evil principle leades to a wreſting &amp; miſapply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:115061:15"/>
the pretious promiſes and precepts of Chriſt, and to miſguide us in our obedience to God, and duty towards our Bretheren. <hi>p. 139.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>What the Author drives at in all he hath ſpoke to Goſpell Miniſters. <hi>p. 140</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:115061:16"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:115061:16"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 7, l. 1. r <hi>Iohn</hi> 17.3. p. 17. l. 8. r. <hi>which,</hi> p. 26. l. 24. for <hi>the,</hi> r. <hi>that.</hi> p. 44. l. 12. for <hi>care,</hi> r. <hi>Core.</hi> p. 60. l. 19. r. <hi>unſeaſonable.</hi> p. 66. l. 21. r. <hi>quoted</hi> p. 32. 33. 34. p. 72. laſt line, for <hi>peace,</hi> r. <hi>place.</hi> p. 85. l. 16. r. p. 68. p. 98. l. 8. r. <hi>aflictions.</hi> p. 101. l. 10. for <hi>time</hi> r. <hi>kinde.</hi> p. 104. l. 11. r. <hi>as it is.</hi> p. 116. l. 11. r. p. 30. 31. 32. 33. 34. 35 p. 119. l. 1. for <hi>which</hi> r. <hi>ſuch.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:115061:17"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:115061:17"/>
            <head>
               <hi>GOSPEL-SEPARATION</hi> SEPARATED From its Abuſes: Wherein is aſſerted the Duty of Gods Churches, ſeparating from the World.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S it is a Principle in Moral Philoſophy, that vertue is uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aly found in <hi>mediums</hi> and Vice in <hi>extreams;</hi> ſo may it be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in a great meaſure that Divine truth is found in <hi>medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ums,</hi> &amp; Errous in <hi>extreams;</hi> For <hi>the Lord was not in the Wind, nor in the Earthquake, nor in the Fire, but in the ſtill ſmall voyce.</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 19.11, 12. And therefore the way of truth in Scripture is held forth to be the ſtrait-way: <hi>Pſal</hi> 5.8. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 40.3, 4. and 42.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Matth.</hi> 3.3. in oppoſition to the crooked ways of Errour, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 125.5. <hi>Prov.</hi> 2.15. Therefore they that would walk in the ſtrait-path of truth and peace, muſt take heed they avoid the Errours of the right hand as well as the left: <hi>Deut.</hi> 5.32. <hi>Joſh.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.7.
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:115061:18"/>
2 <hi>Kings</hi> 22.2. <hi>Prov.</hi> 4 27. <hi>Jſai.</hi> 30.21. all which Scriptures evidence to us that there is danger of running into Errour of both hands, which many Chriſtians not duely conſidering have runne into ſad extreams, like thoſe people <hi>Amos</hi> mentions, <hi>that fled from a Lyon, and a Bear hath met them, Amos</hi> 5.19.</p>
            <p>And as this ſad evill of <hi>extreamity</hi> hath had its influence over moſt controverſal points at this day amongſt the rigid ſticklers for them; ſo in eſpeciall manner hath it produced ſad effects in the point of ſeparation; wherein as on the one hand ſeveral profeſſing Chriſt, not duely weighing the bounds the Lord hath ſet in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhing the Precious from the Vile, have opened the door of the Church too wide; ſo many others under pretence of ſeparating the ſheep from the Goats, do ſhut the door too cloſe, and reject thoſe that God hath choſen, and keep ſuch ſheep out of Chriſts fold as have his own mark upon them: <hi>And he that juſtifieth the wicked, and he that condemneth the juſt, even they both are an abomination unto the Lord, Pro.</hi> 17 15.</p>
            <p>And therefore that the truth may be found out in this weighty caſe, I ſhall make an enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry after the rule of Chriſt in Church-ſeparation from the world; &amp; ſhal therein occaſionally diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſe the ſeveral principles and practices which thoſe that erre in the <hi>extreams</hi> of either hand are ſtumbling in: that betwixt both, the ſtraite
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:115061:18"/>
and narrow (yet ſweet and pleaſant) path of puritie and unitie may be found out and walked in.</p>
            <p>And for the more diſtinct handling of this matter, that the truth I plead for may be as well diſcerned, as the Errour pleaded againſt, I ſhall ſtate theſe two general Poſitions.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That it hath been in all ages wherein God hath had a viſible Church on earth, a duty required by the Lord from ſuch his Church and People, to ſeparate themſelves in matters of his worſhip from all the reſt of the Nations and People of the world. For proof, read <hi>Exod.</hi> 19.6. compared with 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 8.53. ſo <hi>Ezra</hi> 10.11: and 6.21. <hi>Exod.</hi> 23.16. <hi>Lev.</hi> 20.23, 24, 25, 26. ſo <hi>Neh.</hi> 9 2. and 13.3. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.1. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.1.</p>
            <p>Secondly, That it hath been alſo required by the Lord as an equal duty from his Church and People ſo ſeparated to walk together in the practice of all thoſe dutyes of worſhip and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice required at their hands; without dividing or ſeparating from one another. <hi>Deut.</hi> 5.1.3. and 18.6. and 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 8.55.62. 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 13.5, 6, 7, 8. and 28.21. and 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 30.1. and 35.3. <hi>Ezra</hi> 10.5. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 31.23, 24. In which Scriptures conſider the word ALL <hi>Iſrael</hi> and ALL Saints; and ſo <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. to the 14. <hi>Cant.</hi> 6.9. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 133. <hi>Hoſea</hi> 10 1, 2. <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.17. and 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.10. and 3.3. and 11.18.</p>
            <p>But theſe two Poſitions thus generally ſtated,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:115061:19"/>
I judge will be agreed unto by moſt, if not all ſober Chriſtians, and therefore I ſhall ſpend no time in the demonſtration of them in this place, but referr the Reader to the Scriptures quoted, and to what ſhall be ſpoken in the enſuing diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to the ſeveral particulars relating to them.</p>
            <p>And firſt I deſire you to note, if the firſt Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition be true, then the difference amongſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians about ſeparation is rather about the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner or extent then the thing; for that the church of God in the world ſhould be a ſeparated People from the the World in matters of Gods worſhip, would be ridiculous to deny.</p>
            <p>Therefore the difficulty lieth in a right di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhing betwixt the World and the Church, wherein ſome would have that part of the World called the Chriſtian World, to be the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall Catholique Church; and only the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Jews, Turks, Pagans &amp;c. to be the World; but I hope the moſt vehement a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſeparation among the reformed Churches will not admit this extent (if they ſhould, it would be a difficult thing for them to clear themſelves from thoſe brands of Separatiſts and Schiſmaticks caſt upon them by the Papiſts) which if they do not, they then aſſent that a ſeparation may be lawfull from a People make<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an outward profeſſion of the Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:115061:19"/>But ſay others when there is not only an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward profeſſion of the Chriſtian Religion, but alſo a competent knowledge of the Doctrine of the Goſpel and a ſuteable life and converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereto, there are the bounds of the true Church; but the terms of this Qualification will admit of ſo much difficulty in their expla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation that the generality of Chriſtians will be as far to ſeek for their ſatisfaction in this point as before.</p>
            <p>For firſt, ſome will interpret that term of a competent knowledge of the doctrine of the Goſpel to be a bare ability through education to anſwer to queſtions given them in a Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſm, which a child of ſix or Seaven years of age is uſually more capable of and expert in then perſons of grown yeares; which if that be admitted, <hi>then repentance from dead works, and faith towards God, Heb.</hi> 6.1. with all other Goſpel qualifications attending the work of converſion and regeneration may be ſpared as to Church fellowſhip on earth: But as vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous as men opinions are in the ſeveral points of Religion at this day in controverſy, ſo various are their explanations of a competent know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the principles of Religion, each make<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thoſe points wherein they differ from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in, and <hi>ſeparate</hi> upon part of thoſe points of Doctrine, which the knowledge of is neceſſary to a Church-member, the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſing
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:115061:20"/>
of all which would take a Treatiſe by it ſelf.</p>
            <p>Then for the other term of a ſuitable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, that will admit of as much contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſy as the former; for ſay ſome, They that are not of a ſcandalous converſation are of a ſuitable converſation; and if ſo, then many Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, nay Jews, Turks and Pagans are of a ſuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble converſation; for abundance of all them are free from ſcandal in their lives, and do walk very unblameably; <hi>Paul</hi> before his converſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>was according to the Law blameleſſe:</hi> the Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſes <hi>made cleane the outſide of the Cup and Plat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter;</hi> and therefore ſure a Suitable converſation to the Goſpel muſt be more then a meer mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral converſation: but if all perſons of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral perſwaſions walking by theſe Rules that admit of ſo much variousneſs and uncertainty, were put to give their ſeveral meanings in theſe qualifications, they would leave the enquirer after truth at a greater uncertainty then they found him.</p>
            <p>But ſurely the Lord hath not left his People in this great and weighty Caſe at ſo evident an uncertainty; and therefore to ſpend no more time in this labyrinth of different Opinions in this Caſe,</p>
            <p>Let us conſider what light the infallible word of the Lord wil afford us therein; For as <hi>the Lord knows who are his, Jo.</hi> 10.14. and <hi>is known of his,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:115061:20"/>
Col.</hi> 1.10. <hi>ſo hath he left to</hi> his Church and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple a rule of knowing one another from all the people of the world: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4.3. <hi>But know that the Lord hath ſet apart him that is godly for himſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſince the day that the Lord put an enmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty betwixt the two ſeeds, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. there have been viſible marks and rules of diſtinction to know them by: After <hi>Abels</hi> death we read no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of a viſible Church, or Gods viſible wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip upon earth until the dayes of <hi>Seth,</hi> who was given in ſtead of <hi>Abel,</hi> whom <hi>Cain</hi> ſlew; and after his poſterity began to increaſe in the earth; that is, after <hi>Enoch</hi> was born; <hi>then began men to call upon the name of the Lord, Gen.</hi> 24.25, 26. in whoſe ſeed the Church of God continued un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til the Flood, at which time the Church and people of God polluted themſelves, and corrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the holy ſeed by mixing themſelves in mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages with the ſeed of the world: For <hi>the Sons of God ſaw the daughters of men that they were fair, and took them wives of all which they choſe;</hi> at which the Lord was greatly provoked, and ſaid, <hi>My Spirit ſhall not always ſtrive with fleſh, Gen.</hi> 6.2.3. and after the Flood the holy ſeed was again revived in <hi>Shem, Gen.</hi> 9.26, 27. in whoſe line the viſible Church continued until <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi>'s time, with whom the Lord again renewed his Covenant, and made another ſeparation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the two ſeeds, <hi>Gen.</hi> 12.2, 3. who again re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:115061:21"/>
and revived the viſible worſhip of God, <hi>Gen.</hi> 12.7.8. <hi>Gen.</hi> 13.4. After which God did at ſeveral times not onely renew his Covenant of Promiſe, but in the ſeventeenth of <hi>Geneſis</hi> did declare more fully then before, the Condition of his Covenant; for as before he uſually ſaid, my Covenant will I keep with thee; he here ſaith, my Covenant thou ſhalt keep with me, verſes 9, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14. <hi>And God ſaid unto Abraham, Thou ſhalt keep my Covenant therefore, thou, and thy ſeed after thee, in their generations: This is my Covenant which ye ſhall keep between me and you, and thy ſeed after thee: Every man-child among you ſhall be circumciſed. And ye ſhall circumciſe the fleſh of your foreskins, and it ſhall be a token of the Covenant between me and you. And he that is eight dayes old, ſhall be circumciſed among you, every man child in your generations; he that is born in the houſe, or bought with money of any ſtranger, which is not of thy ſeed. He that is born in thy houſe, and he that is bought with thy money, muſt needs be circumciſed: and my Covenant ſhall be in your fleſh for an everlaſting Covenant. And the uncircumciſed man-child, whoſe fleſh of his foreskin is not circumciſed, that ſoul ſhall be cut off from his people; he hath broken my Govenant.</hi> In which words the Lord doth ordain and eſtabliſh a new <hi>pale</hi> or <hi>bound</hi> to his Church, which was never again to be altered; for <hi>Abrahams ſeed</hi> and <hi>circumciſion</hi> in the type,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:115061:21"/>
or in the Antitype, in the fleſh or ſpirit, ſhall ever continue to be the true <hi>bound</hi> of Gods Church militant: which Covenant we finde was renewed again to <hi>Iſaac, Gen.</hi> 26.1, 2, 3, 4. <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.7. <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.28. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 11.1. And after that to <hi>Jacob, Gen.</hi> 28.13, 14, 15. from whoſe time this Covenant of diſtinction was uſually repeated to be the Covenant made with <hi>Abraham, Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob, Exod.</hi> 2.24. <hi>Lev.</hi> 26.42. and that for an everlaſting Covenant, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 16.16, 17. compared with the thirty fourth verſe.</p>
            <p>Which <hi>Rule of Church-memberſhip,</hi> or <hi>viſible bound</hi> of Gods Church, continued in the type unqueſtionable until the coming of the promiſed Meſſiah, <hi>Luke</hi> 1.59. &amp; 2.21. And therefore the Phariſees in the 8th of <hi>John,</hi> thought they made a good plea to Chriſt, verſe 33. <hi>We are Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams ſeed;</hi> and verſe 39. <hi>Abraham is our Father;</hi> which our Saviour admits to be true, verſe 37. <hi>I know that ye are Abraham's ſeed;</hi> And this priviledge <hi>Paul</hi> pleaded, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.1. <hi>Hath God caſt away his people? God forbid; for I alſo am an Iſraelite, of the ſeed of Abraham:</hi> And ſo againſt thoſe falſe teachers in the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. <hi>Are they Hebrews? ſo am I: are they Iſraelites? ſo am I: are they the ſeed of Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham? ſo am I:</hi> By all which, and much more of that nature that might be added, it is a truth out of controverſie, that the Condition of the Covenant made with <hi>Abraham,</hi> &amp;c. was the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:115061:22"/>
ſtanding unalterable <hi>bounds</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of God until Chriſt came, who did not at all diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>annul this Covenant, as it was a <hi>diſtinguiſhing</hi> Covenant, nor alter the leaſt Condition of it, but fulfilled it; that what our Lord ſaith of the Law in general, may be truly applyed to this particular: <hi>Think not that I am come to deſtroy the Law and the Prophets; I am not come to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy, but to fulfill; for verily I ſay unto you, till heaven and earth paſs, one jot or one title ſhall in no wiſe paſs from the Law, till all be fulfilled, Mat.</hi> 5.17, 18. And ſo <hi>Paul argues, Rom.</hi> 3.31. <hi>Do we then make void the Law through Faith? God forbid; we eſtabliſh the Law:</hi> So that we muſt not ſeek for another Rule to know Gods Church and people by under the Goſpel, then what was under the Law: But to enquire after that Legal Rule Goſpelized; that what the ſeed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and <hi>Circumciſion</hi> under the Law, were Types of; under the Goſpel, that muſt we enquire for, and make the ſame uſe of the Antitype now which the type then ſerved for.</p>
            <p>Now the <hi>ſeed of Abraham</hi> in the Fleſh, typed out to us the <hi>ſeed of Abraham</hi> in the Spirit; the Carnal ſeed under the Law, was the type of the Spiritual <hi>ſeed</hi> under the Goſpel, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.11. to the end, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.10. firſt verſes; ſo <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.14. to to the end, concluding with theſe words, <hi>if ye be Chriſts, then are ye Abrahams ſeed, and heirs
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:115061:22"/>
according to promiſe;</hi> and in the 7th verſe, <hi>Know you therefore that they which are of Faith, the ſame are the children of</hi> Abraham.</p>
            <p>And for the Antitype of <hi>Circumciſion,</hi> it is evident to be the inward work of grace in the heart: <hi>In whom alſo ye are circumciſed with the Circumciſion made without hands, in putting off the body of the ſins of the Fleſh, by the Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion of Chriſt:</hi> and ſo <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.28, 29. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.9, 10, 11, 12. and divers other places.</p>
            <p>Now that which I deſire you to obſerve, in order to the finding out the everlaſting infallible <hi>bounds</hi> of Gods true Church, and <hi>Character</hi> of his true children on earth, is, that theſe Anti-types of <hi>Abraham</hi>'s fleſhly <hi>Seed</hi> and <hi>Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi> are made uſe of in the Goſpel, and pleaded for the ſame end.</p>
            <p>That the Types themſelves were under the Law, as you may read at large in the Epiſtles to the <hi>Romans</hi> and <hi>Galatians,</hi> the chief drift and ſcope of thoſe Epiſtles being to convince the Jews, that what they formerly enjoyed by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of <hi>Abraham</hi>'s <hi>Covenant,</hi> were now made out to believers by Faith in Chriſt, pleading with them, that now all partition walls betwixt Jew &amp; Gentile were broken down, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.13, 14. And ſhewing that in <hi>Jeſus Chriſt neither circumciſion availeth any thing, nor uncircumciſion, but faith which worketh by Love.</hi> Ga. 5.6. And ſo Peter, <hi>Act.</hi> 10.34. ſaid, <hi>Of a truth I perceive that God is no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecter
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:115061:23"/>
of Perſons: but in every Nation, he that feareth him, and worketh Righteouſneſs, is accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of him;</hi> and if you do but conſider the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles Arguments in the aforeſaid Epiſtles, to prove the Gentiles to be fellow-Heirs <hi>with the Jews, and of the ſame body, partakers of his promiſe in Chriſt by the Goſpel,</hi> as in <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.6. you ſhall find he proves it by proving that they are <hi>Abrahams ſeed: Rom.</hi> 4.15, 16, 17. &amp; <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.7, 8. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.16, 29. <hi>And therefore heirs according to promiſe: Rom.</hi> 8.17. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.29. <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.6. And that they were not of the <hi>uncircumciſed,</hi> but were the true <hi>circumciſion; Rom.</hi> 2.25, 26, 27, 28, 29. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.9, 10. &amp; 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.19. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.3. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.11. From all which Scriptures, and abundance more that might be added of like tendency, it is evident that the <hi>diſtinguiſhing Character</hi> of Gods People and Church in <hi>Abrahams</hi> Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant continues the ſame; and ought to be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by Gods Miniſters and People, to the end of the world, to be the true unalterable and infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>bound</hi> of Gods Church, and <hi>mark</hi> of Gods Children: The ſwerving from which hath led into all thoſe confuſions and diviſions which are at this day in Gods Church, moſt particular opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions and perſwaſions, laying waſte thoſe old Church <hi>bounds,</hi> and clipping off Gods antient <hi>Sheep mark,</hi> would confine the place of his flock to their own <hi>Folds,</hi> and owne none to be his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture ſheep, but ſuch as will receive their by
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:115061:23"/>
               <hi>marks,</hi> againſt whom the <hi>Sons</hi> of the Church of Chriſt may juſtly take up that complaint <hi>Labans</hi> ſons made againſt <hi>Jacob, Gen.</hi> 31.1. <hi>He hath tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en away all that was our Fathers; And of that which was our fathers hath he gotten all this glory.</hi> Some on the one hand wholy breaking down this hedge about Gods Vineyard: they will not ſo-much as admit of an inward work of grace and regeneration of heart, of being born again (which is the undoubted type of <hi>Circumciſion</hi> and <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams ſeed,</hi> as before) to be the viſible <hi>bound</hi> of Gods viſible Church, and <hi>mark</hi> of viſible Saints, but content themſelves with a bare profeſſion of the Chriſtian Religion; and ſome others there are as we minded before, will add ſome further uncertain diſputable qualifications of knowledge and ſuitable converſation; But doubtleſs, this unſound Principle hath Antichriſt ſet himſelf upon his thron by, and laid Waſte the mountain of God by, and trodden under his Feet the holy City by: This hath let in the Boare out of the wood, and the wild Beaſts out of the Field to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voure, that it is time for the Church to cry out againſt this Principle, with the Prophet <hi>Iſay</hi> 64.10. <hi>Sion is a wilderneſs, Jeruſalem a deſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> and to plead with the Lord in the words of the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Why haſt thou broken down her hedges, ſo that all they which paſſe by the way do pluck her? the Boar of the forreſt doth waſte it, and the wild beaſt of the Field doth devoure it: Pſal.</hi> 80.12.13.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:115061:24"/>For it is evident that Antichriſt, if you do but obſerve the Hiſtory of the Churches declining ſtate, made his way into Gods Church, and uſhered all his train of falſe Prophets, and falſe Doctrines, by laying waſte the Churches true <hi>fence</hi> and <hi>bounds;</hi> and by laying the garden encloſed, <hi>Cant.</hi> 4.12. into an open field, in which every unclean beaſt may make his den, and paſs through, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 80.12, 13. And as theſe ancient <hi>bounds</hi> of Gods Church are again diſcovered and made up, that our ſpiritual watchmen may keep their guards upon the towers of theſe holy <hi>walls,</hi> ſo ſhall the Churches purity and unity be recovered.</p>
            <p>But now there are ſome other Chriſtians that admit viſible grace and holineſs to be a diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; nay, the chief and main <hi>diſtinction</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt Gods Church and the world, beleevers and unbeleevers; but they will not admit it to be the onely <hi>diſtinction,</hi> but will add ſome other private <hi>mark,</hi> according, to their particular opinions and perſwaſions; ſome doctrine or practice that they have attained to ſome diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent underſtanding in from the reſt of Gods people, muſt be as a <hi>poſt</hi> of their own ſet up by Gods <hi>poſt,</hi> as in <hi>Ezek.</hi> 43.8. in the <hi>bounds</hi> of his Church. Now though this be not ſo dangerous as the former, in regard it preſerves holineſs, and viſible grace as the main <hi>rule</hi> or bound; yet the effect of this error is very ſad; for this was
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:115061:24"/>
the apparent inlet of all thoſe diviſions and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal contentions that happened in the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> and the reſt of the Churches in the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive times, and that continues and increaſeth the ſame at this day, even to the hazard of the total ruine and deſtruction of the Church of Chriſt, as we ſhall more at large prove when we come to ſpeak of the particular evil conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences of it: For <hi>Jeruſalem muſt not onely be as a City of righteouſneſs, an holy City, Iſa.</hi> 52.1. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.26. <hi>but as a City compact, Pſal.</hi> 122.3. <hi>A City with walls, Pſal.</hi> 51.18. <hi>Lam.</hi> 2.8, 18. <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.7.</p>
            <p>Now the way to avoid both theſe <hi>extreams,</hi> is to obſerve the <hi>bounds</hi> and <hi>marks</hi> that God hath ſet about his Church, <hi>to walk about</hi> Sion, <hi>and go round about her, and tell the towers thereof; mark ye well her Bulwarks, and conſider her Palaces, that ye may tell it the generations fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing;</hi> the right obſervation and preſerving of which would make the Church <hi>to be comly as</hi> Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, <hi>Cant.</hi> 6.4. <hi>God would then be known in her Palaces for a refuge, Pſal.</hi> 48.3. we ſhould then <hi>behold how good and pleaſant a thing it is for brethren to dwell together in unity,</hi> Pſal. 133.1.</p>
            <p>But for the firſt and worſt of theſe two ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treams, which diſownes viſible grace and holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to be required in perſons, in order to <hi>viſible memberſhip,</hi> or <hi>Church-ſtate,</hi> I ſhall ſay
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:115061:25"/>
no more to that point, it being already ſo large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpoken unto, and fully cleared by ſeveral of the congregational way; and eſpecially that late eminent diſcoverer of the ancient and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible <hi>bounds</hi> of Gods true Church, Mr <hi>Jo. Cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> in that little Treatiſe of his, (beſides ſeveral others) intituled <hi>The holineſs of Church mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers:</hi> for I am far from preſſing an unity of Church-ſtate with any that make not viſible Grace and holineſs the main <hi>mark</hi> of viſible Faith and Church-memberſhip; but what uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is to be deſired, and endeavoured with the godly of that judgement, I ſhall give my opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in its place; and ſhall now chiefly inſiſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſecond general Poſition, That all true be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers congregated together, and ſeparated from the world and mixt worſhip, to ſerve the Lord in the beauty of holineſs, ought to own and eſteem one another as <hi>true Churches,</hi> and Saints, giving the right hand of fellowſhip to one another, and walking together as children of the ſame Father, <hi>Jo.</hi> 11.52. Members of the ſame body, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.4, 5. ſheep of the ſame fold, <hi>Jo.</hi> 10.16. in obſervance of all thoſe joynt duties required by the Lord at their hands, without dividing, rending or ſeparating from one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>The Terms of your Poſition ſo general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtated, may admit of ſeveral conſtructions, and thereby give little light to the caſes in contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:115061:25"/>
though you ſhould prove it; if not more particularly explained.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I ſhall have occaſion to explain the terms, in anſwer to ſeveral objections that will ariſe in the enſuing diſcourſe; and therefore for brevitie ſake ſhall paſs them by here, and ſhall next proceed to the ſeveral ſorts of Arguments to prove the Poſition with Arguments I ſhall chiefly draw from theſe ſeven general heads following.</p>
            <p>Firſt, From the viſible choice and approbati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of God the Father, proving, that ſuch as the Father hath viſibly manifeſted his choice and approbation of, to be his children, beleevers ought to chuſe and approve of to be their brethren.</p>
            <p>Secondly, From the viſible choice and approbation of God the Son, proving, that ſuch as the Lord Jeſus Chriſt hath mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted his choice and approbation of to be <hi>members</hi> of his viſible body and Church on earth, all his ought to make choice and approve of to be <hi>fellow members</hi> with him of the ſame body.</p>
            <p>Third, From the evident choice and appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation of God the holy Ghoſt, proving, that ſuch as the ſpirit hath manifeſted its <hi>viſible choice</hi> of, by the holy inſpiration of its <hi>quicken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> and <hi>ſanctifying</hi> Grace, beleevers ought to make <hi>choice,</hi> and approve of as ſuch who have
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:115061:26"/>
an <hi>equal right</hi> with them to a mutual participa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the <hi>priviledges, gifts</hi> and <hi>comforts</hi> of the ſame ſpirit.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, From the choice and approbation of the infallible ſervants of God, his holy Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and Apoſtles, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in all ages, proving, that ſuch as the infallible ſervants of God in all ages of his Church have made choice of, and appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to be their <hi>brethren</hi> in the Lord, and <hi>fellow-members</hi> with themſelves in Gods viſible Church, ought to be ſo <hi>approved of</hi> and cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen by all his ſervants to the end of the world.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, From the ſeveral Similes and Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phors the Church of God is compared unto in the Scriptures, whereby their mutual intereſt in an union with one another is held forth from thence; proving, that what <hi>unity</hi> is required, and <hi>intereſt</hi> is given to members of the ſame bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, branches of the ſame root, ſheep of the ſame fold, and under the ſame Shepherd, chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the ſame Father, and fellow-heirs of the ſame inheritance, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that the ſame <hi>intereſt</hi> is given unto, and <hi>union</hi> required in the ſeveral members of Gods Church, which is ſo fitly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared thereto, and lively ſet out thereby.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, From the evident ſad conſequences that attend the Church and people of God, though their <hi>dividings</hi> and <hi>ſeparatings</hi> from one another, and uniting together upon other
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:115061:26"/>
principles then this of <hi>viſible grace;</hi> arguing from thence, that ſuch principles and practices as open <hi>the door,</hi> and <hi>let in</hi> upon the Church of God ſuch deſtructive, uncomfortable conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences, ſhould be of all evils laboured againſt, and avoided.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, From the evident, and unſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able good, both to the outward and inward man, the union of Gods Church upon ſuch Goſpel laſting principles, would be attended with; ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guing from thence, that ſince the unity of Gods Church, upon ſuch a binding and abiding prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple as this of <hi>viſible grace,</hi> would ſo exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly tend to the unvaluable good thereof, it ought to be ſought after, and prayed for above all things, by every true member thereof, next to an intereſt in Chriſt, and viſible grace it ſelf.</p>
            <p>Now from the firſt head <hi>(viz)</hi> the viſible choice and approbation of God the Father, I argue.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Thoſe whom the Father hath manifeſted his viſible choice and approbation of, to be his children. 2. Beleevers ought to manifeſt their choice and approbation of, to be their <hi>bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the Father hath manifeſted his choice and approbation of all viſible beleevers, and grations holy perſons to be his <hi>children.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore ought Beleevers to chooſe and approve of ſuch to be their <hi>Brethren.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:115061:27"/>1. The Major, or firſt Propoſition, is evident from the very light of nature and reaſon; yet ſince prejudice againſt truth doth ofttimes put out all light, I ſhall add the light of ſome Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures to the clearing up this truth: And firſt that of our Saviour in <hi>Matth.</hi> 23. verſe 8. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with the 9th. Saith the word in verſe 8. <hi>All ye are Brethren,</hi> which he proves in verſe 9. <hi>For one is your Father which is in Heaven;</hi> and ſo <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.11. <hi>For both he that ſanctifieth, and they who are ſanctified are all of one; for which cauſe he is not aſhamed to call them Brethen:</hi> from which Scripture, I gather, that the Lord Jeſus Chriſt was not aſhamed to own all <hi>Saints</hi> for <hi>Brethren,</hi> though they were attended with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of imperfection and uncomlineſs, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſutatable to his moſt holy nature and courſe of life; becauſe himſelf as head, and they as mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, were all of one <hi>Father;</hi> that ſince his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was not aſhamed to own them all as <hi>Sons,</hi> verſe 10. therefore he was not aſhamed to own then all as <hi>Brethren,</hi> verſe 11.</p>
            <p>Now it is a ſad thing, that fellow-<hi>Brethren,</hi> who are <hi>all ſubject to like infirmities, Jam.</hi> 5.17. who do all ſee but in part, and know but in part, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.9, 10, 11. ſhould be more high-minded in this caſe, and ſooner aſhamed of their <hi>Brethren,</hi> upon the account of their infirmities and weakneſs, then their elder <hi>Brother,</hi> who was free from all imperfections, and ſtood in no
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:115061:27"/>
need of their bearing with him; he bore all their ſins, not onely in the puniſhment, but in the ſhame of them, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.2. thereby ſetting them a pattern to bear the ſhame of each others infirmities: for ſo argues Paul, <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.1, 2, 3. <hi>We then that are ſtrong ought to bear the infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the weak, and not to pleaſe our ſelves; for even Chriſt pleaſed not himſelf: but as it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, The reproaches of them that reproached thee fell upon me:</hi> and that this is not onely a duty, but a ſpecial duty to all Saints, See further, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.6. 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.3, and 2, 13. <hi>Mal.</hi> 2.10. <hi>John</hi> 4.21, 23. <hi>John</hi> 6.45.</p>
            <p n="2">2. For the Minor, or ſecond Propoſition, none can deny, that doth not deny the Scripture; conſider the firſt Epiſtle of <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.1, 2. compared with verſe 10. <hi>Galat.</hi> 3.26, 27. <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 62.12. <hi>Deut.</hi> 28.9 <hi>Iſa.</hi> 13.3. <hi>Act.</hi> 20.32. with a multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of other places; it is hard to read a Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that affords no evidence to this truth.</p>
            <p>So that I conclude, this Argument in every part of it fully cleared.</p>
            <p>I might draw from this head many more Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments of equal ſtrength, as from the Fathers viſible Covenant, <hi>with</hi> ſpecial promiſes <hi>unto</hi> the Saints, poſitive precepts for this union of Saints, upon the principle of <hi>viſible grace,</hi> &amp;c. But I ſhall leave them to the Readers meditation to enlarge, and come to the ſecond head.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The viſible choice and approbation, with
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:115061:28"/>
the perſonal qualification of God the Son, who as he hath ſet himſelf a patern of all grace to his people; ſo in an eſpecial manner of this glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious ſtate of Goſpel <hi>union,</hi> he became a perfect pattern of holy <hi>union,</hi> by uniting the humane and divine nature in his own perſon; God and Chriſt, and Saints, muſt all be made <hi>one</hi> in in the myſtical <hi>union, Jo.</hi> 17.21, 22. which though it cannot be perfected until the ſtate of glory, yet it is to be begun, imitated, and preſt after, in the ſtate of Grace: And therefore God the Father would have but <hi>one</hi> Son to be his dearly beloved Son, <hi>Mark</hi> 1.11. <hi>Luke</hi> 7.37. he muſt have <hi>no equal, Col.</hi> 1.18. nor no partner, nor help in his work, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 63.3.5. <hi>He muſt tread the wine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs alone; of the people there muſt be none with him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo Saints muſt have but <hi>one</hi> Saviour, <hi>Acts</hi> 4.12. <hi>one</hi> Redeemer, <hi>Revel.</hi> 5.9. <hi>one</hi> Mediator, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.5. <hi>one</hi> Head, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.22. <hi>one</hi> Husband, 1 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 11.2. <hi>one</hi> Chief Shepherd, <hi>John</hi> 10.16. <hi>one</hi> Captain of their Salvation, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.10. all which lively holds forth to us the <hi>unity</hi> of Saints, and in him alone; Chriſt muſt not be divided, 1. <hi>Corinth.</hi> 1.13. neither in his headſhip, nor in his members; but they muſt <hi>grow up into him in all things, which is the Head, even Chriſt, from whom the whole Body fitly joyned together, and compacted by that which every joynt ſupplyeth, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the effectual working in meaſure of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:115061:28"/>
every part, maketh increaſe of the body, to the edify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it ſelf in love, Epheſ.</hi> 4.15, 16. From whence we may obſerve, what a perfect pattern of <hi>uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> the Lord Jeſus Chriſt is, both Head and Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; as if not onely the Glory, but the very Eſſence of heavenly things depended on unity.</p>
            <p>And ſo the main deſign of Chriſt, in his aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming our nature, and doing and ſuffering all for us, was chiefly a work of <hi>union</hi> and reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.20. to reconcile God and man, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.20. to break down partition walls be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt Jew and Gentile, bond and free, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.14, 16. <hi>that in the diſpenſation of the fulneſs of time, he might gather together in</hi> one, <hi>all things in Chriſt, both which are in heaven, and which are on earth; even in him,</hi> Epheſ. 1.10.</p>
            <p>And ſo we finde him in the whole courſe of his miniſtry, walking by principles of <hi>union,</hi> commanding thoſe duties, and commending thoſe Graces moſt which were the <hi>uniting</hi> Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Graces. The firſt Goſpel that was prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched on earth, was in theſe words; <hi>Glory to God in the higheſt, and on earth</hi> Peace <hi>and good will towards men, Luke</hi> 2.14. himſelf is called the Prince of <hi>Peace, Iſa.</hi> 9.6, 7. <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.2. His Goſpel is called the Goſpel of <hi>Peace, Rom.</hi> 10.15. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.16. his people are called the Sons of <hi>Peace, Luke</hi> 10.6. his wayes are called the wayes of <hi>Peace, Luke</hi> 1.79.</p>
            <p>And as Peace, ſo <hi>Love</hi> is held forth in the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:115061:29"/>
Goſpel of Chriſt as a Cardinal Grace; <hi>A new commandment give I unto you, that ye</hi> Love <hi>one another, as I have loved you, John</hi> 13.34. And ſo we might proceed to the Graces of Humility, Meekneſs, Patience, Mercifulneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which are all <hi>uniting</hi> Graces; and by our Lord commend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto us above all Graces; they are conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal Graces, unto which promiſes are annexed; above all things, ſaith the Apoſtle, put on <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity:</hi> in the diſcription of which Grace all theſe are contained, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. from all which, and indeed from the whole ſcope, and tendency of the Scripture, I argue;</p>
            <p>That the duty which is moſt lively held out unto us by our Paterne, and required of us by our Lawgiver the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, ſhould be moſt upon our hearts to imitate and obey him in.</p>
            <p>But the Duty of <hi>uniting</hi> the Saints to one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, next to that of <hi>uniting</hi> them to himſelf, was the greateſt duty held forth by our Lord and Maſter to us; and required by him of us; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>for the <hi>unity</hi> of Saints with one another ought to be moſt upon our hearts next unto <hi>their union</hi> with Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>But ſay ſome, we do admit, all Chriſts Members ought to be united together in his worſhip, but the doubt lies who we ſhould own as his mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Thoſe whom the Lord Jeſus Chriſt
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:115061:29"/>
owns as Members of his viſible body here on earth, ought all to own one another, as <hi>members</hi> of the ſame body.</p>
            <p>But the Lord Jeſus Chriſt owns all true Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers or viſible gracious perſons to be members of his viſible body on earth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ergo,</hi> All ſuch ought ſo to own one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Anſw.</hi> Thoſe for whom Chriſt prayed to the Father that they all might be <hi>One,</hi> as he and the Father were <hi>One, John.</hi> 17.11. ought to walk in <hi>union</hi> one with another.</p>
            <p>But it was for all the Father had then viſibly given him, verſes 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12. And that ſhould afterward be converted by their doctrine verſes 20, 21. for whom he prayed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ergo</hi> all ſuch ought to walk together in <hi>uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We might draw arguments of <hi>union</hi> from all the Metaphorical relations the Scripture holds forth Chriſt to ſtand in to his People, as an head, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.18. an husband, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 54.5. A King, <hi>Revel.</hi> 15.3. a Shepheard, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 23.1. a Root, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.17, 18. the very eſſence of which relations con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts in <hi>union;</hi> and the main end of them in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is to hold forth the neceſſarineſs of <hi>union</hi> in the Church and People of God: hut I ſhall ſpeak to them under another head.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 3. From the viſible choice and appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation of God the holy Ghoſt. The Spirit of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:115061:30"/>
God though it fill all things, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.10. yet is but one Spirit, verſes 3, 4. the ſame ſpirit that fills Chriſt the head with all fulneſs. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.19. and 2.9. fills all his members out of the ſame fulneſs, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.23. <hi>They all receive out of his fulneſs grace for grace, John</hi> 1.16.</p>
            <p>And as the Spirit of God that fills whole Chriſt, head and members, is but one ſpirit: ſo the chief buſineſs of this own ſpirit, and tendency of its operation is unity, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.3. And next to that betwixt head and members, Chriſt and Saints, it drives on the deſigne of the Saints union with one another in all truth, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.13.</p>
            <p>It can neither be divided, nor deceived, but muſt ſpeak the ſame thing at all times to all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.8. Men may have different appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions, and underſtandings, and from the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety in them may put a various interpretation upon the Spirits teaching, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.3. but yet the ſpirit remains the ſame ſpirit of truth, it leadeth into all truth; <hi>Jo.</hi> 16.13. And though this variety be in the ſpirits operation, in the work of illumination, and directing the judgement from the variety which is in the capacities and appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions of men; yet in the more certain pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties of the ſpirits work upon the hearts of Beleevers, as in the works of mortification and ſanctification &amp;c. there is no ſuch variety; for though there may be difference of degree, yet the leaſt meaſure of the ſpirits work in thoſe
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:115061:30"/>
things bears a divine ſtamp: that fruit of the Spirit, which is in all goodneſs, righteouſneſs and truth, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.9. is of the ſame nature and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion in all Saints; from whence I argue,</p>
            <p>That the moſt infallible Rule Saints can walk by in their choice of goſpel <hi>brethren</hi> or <hi>Church-members,</hi> is, to follow the tract of the Spirits <hi>choyce,</hi> to <hi>chooſe</hi> where it hath <hi>choſen</hi> before them.</p>
            <p>But the viſible tract, or evidence of the Spirits <hi>choyce</hi> is its manifeſting its indwelling through its operation in carrying the Soul out to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of Grace.</p>
            <p>Therefore the viſible operation of the Spirit of Grace in perſons, is the moſt infallible Rule for Beleevers to make their <hi>choyce</hi> by.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>But may ſome ſay, how ſhall we know the Spirits operations, and thereby its choyce in ſuch a day of deluſion as this is: when the ſpirit of Errour that new reigneth, hath transformed it ſelf to ſo neere a likeneſſe to the Spirit of Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Whatſoever is held forth to be the viſible fruits and effects of the Spirit of grace in the hearts and converſation of Beleevers by the word of truth, ought to be admitted by them as ſufficient Teſtimony of the Spirits choice, <hi>Acts</hi> 11.17.</p>
            <p>But the effects and fruits of the Spirit are clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly teſtified to be <hi>Love, Joy, Peace, Long-ſuffering, Gentleneſs, Goodneſs, Faith, Meekneſs and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance, Gal.</hi> 5.22.23. Therefore ſuch perſons
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:115061:31"/>
whom the Spirit of the Lotd hath ſo <hi>qualified,</hi> ought to be admitted, and owned by Beleevers as ſuch of whom the Spirit hath manifeſted its <hi>choyce.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For what may be further objected againſt this Argument from the various underſtandings, and different minds of ſeveral viſible gracious perſons; and from the groſſe Errours held by ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral perſons ſeemingly gracious and ſpirituall; I ſhall have occaſion to ſpeak to, when I come to anſwer to ſuch general Objections, as will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude many of thoſe particular Objections that might be made againſt every Argument.</p>
            <p>I might add many Arguments more drawn from the <hi>fruits</hi> of the Spirits <hi>choyce:</hi> But let all that long for the <hi>union</hi> of Saints, firſt reſolve to make the Spirits choice theirs: and then they ſhall hardly read a Scripture, but will afford them ſome Characters of the Spirits <hi>choyce;</hi> for our heavenly Father hath not a <hi>Child,</hi> nor our chief Shepheard a <hi>Sheep</hi> (that are viſibly ſuch) but his holy Spirit hath ſet his ſeal on them; either leſſe or more viſible, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.22. <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.13. &amp; 4.30. Therefore I ſhall conclude this head with one Argument more, and leave the remain to the Readers meditation.</p>
            <p>That qualification or State which gives us free acceſs to and <hi>acceptance</hi> with the Father, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.18. &amp; 1.6. by which we are made his <hi>adopted Sons, Rom.</hi> 8.15. unto which he hath an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:115061:31"/>
the <hi>performances</hi> of his preitious promiſes, 2 <hi>Peter.</hi> 1.4. wherein he ſeeks and deſires us to worſhip him, <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.23. by which we are joyned unto the ſame body of which Jeſus Chriſt is the head, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.13. and whereby we are made <hi>partakers</hi> of the ſame grace, 1 <hi>Col.</hi> 12. <hi>heirs</hi> with him of the ſame <hi>Kingdom, James</hi> 2.5. or inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.11, 14. and <hi>partakers</hi> with him of the ſame <hi>glory</hi> in heaven, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.27. &amp; 3.4. nay wherein the perfection of, ſhall be their <hi>State in glory, John</hi> 17.23, 24, <hi>Eph</hi> 4.13. when all other qualifications and additional rules of diſtinction ſhall ceaſe, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.8, 10. is doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe the moſt infallible <hi>rule,</hi> and qualification for Gods Church and People to owne and joyn with one another in the worſhip and ſervice of God by. But the qualification that gives us right unto &amp; intereſt in all the former particulars is a <hi>parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipation of a ſpiritual work of grace upon the heart,</hi> as the Srciptures annexed with abundance more that might be added, do ſufficiently evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</p>
            <p>Therefore it is the moſt infallible <hi>rule</hi> for Gods Churches and People to make choice of <hi>Church-members</hi> and Goſpel <hi>Brethren</hi> by.</p>
            <p>The fourth General head from which we ſhall argue, is, the choice and approbation of the <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible ſervants</hi> of God in all ages, whoſe fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip and communion with perſons as Gods Church, and People, is recorded for our Example
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:115061:32"/>
in Scriptures; who in their ſeveral generations, and ages of the Church they lived in, made this duty of preſerving the Churches <hi>union</hi> and peace within it ſelf, the great and weighty duty; unto which moſt other dutyes when they come in competition muſt give place unto. And they did always make the declared <hi>viſible choice</hi> of <hi>God</hi> their choice.</p>
            <p>For thoſe whom God had <hi>choſen</hi> to be his <hi>peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi> by his viſible Covenant with an eſpecial grace unto —they owned to be their <hi>brethren</hi> and fellow members in his Church— ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding none of them—nor admiting no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; which point I ſuppoſe hath been ſufficiently proved in my diſcourſe of the true Church-bounds,</p>
            <p>That until I meet with one inſtance at leaſt out of Gods word of a perſon or perſons viſible which in thoſe <hi>Church-bounds</hi> before mentioned (viz. <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſeed &amp; Circumciſion in the type &amp; Antitype) was kept out or not eſteemed one of Gods Church, not ſcandalous or unexcommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated, I ſhall for bear further ſpeaking to that.</p>
            <p>And ſhall chiefly from this head inſiſt to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the weight that the holy ſervants of God in all ages have laid upon the Churches peace and <hi>unity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When the Church conſiſted of <hi>Jacobs</hi> family, how carefull was <hi>Joſeph</hi> to preſerve <hi>union</hi> among his <hi>Brethren,</hi> though they had little deſerved it
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:115061:32"/>
at his hands! yet the great and chief charge he layeth upon them, is, <hi>ſee that you fall not out by the way, Gen.</hi> 4.5.24. So <hi>Moſes</hi> reproves his Brethren the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> for <hi>ſtriving</hi> one with another <hi>Exod.</hi> 2.13. in in theſe words as <hi>Stephen</hi> quotes it, <hi>Acts</hi> 7.26. <hi>Sirs, ye are Brethren, why do ye wrong one another?</hi> So for the <hi>Diviſions</hi> of <hi>Reuben</hi> there were great ſearchings of heart, <hi>Judges</hi> 5.15, 16. So <hi>David, Behold, how good and how pleaſant a thing it is for Brethren to dwell together in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity,</hi> &amp;c. The whole Pſalm is a compendium of the bleſſings and excellencies of the Churches <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So obſerve <hi>Solomons</hi> diſcription of a ſower of diſcord among <hi>Brethren, Prov.</hi> 6.12, 13, 14, 15, 16. verſes, compared with the 19th verſe, and you will judge he loved <hi>unity</hi> well. And ſo <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> again in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 122.6. <hi>Pray for the</hi> Peace <hi>of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, they ſhall proſper that love her,</hi> verſe 7. <hi>Peace be within thy walls;</hi> and verſe 8. <hi>For my</hi> Brethren <hi>and companions ſake, I will now ſay, peace be within thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Many Examples might be added, but I ſhall end with <hi>Paul,</hi> who was an eminent exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, both to Miniſters and Chriſtians in the Church-<hi>uniting</hi> work: If we ſhould conſider him no further then the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> he approved himſelf amongſt them a skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Phyſitian, furniſhed with <hi>healing medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines,</hi> which he tenderly adminiſtred to that
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:115061:33"/>
ſad divided erroneous Church; from whom he had received ſo much hard meaſure, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratefull uſage; and yet it is evident, the peace and <hi>union</hi> of that Church was more upon his heart to preſerve, then all its other errours and miſcarriage was to reform, though they were very great ones, and were minded by him in their due place too.</p>
            <p>But the whole being under the profeſſion of <hi>viſible Saints,</hi> he writes unto them as fuch, without diſtinction, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto the Church of God which is at Corinth, to them that are ſanctified in Chriſt Jeſus, Called to be Saints, &amp;c.</hi> as in the firſt chapter and ſecond verſe.</p>
            <p>And after he had finiſhed his Preface, in the 9th verſe, begins with that which was moſt upon his heart, verſe 10. <hi>Now I beſeech you Brethren by the name of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that ye all ſpeak the ſame thing, and that there be no Diviſions among you, but that ye be perfectly joyned together in the ſame minde, and in the ſame judgment: for it hath been declared unto me of you, my brethren, of them which of are the houſe of</hi> Cloe, <hi>that there are contentions among you,</hi> ver. 11. <hi>Now this I ſay, that every one of you ſaith, I am of</hi> Paul, <hi>I of</hi> Apollo, <hi>and I of</hi> Cephas, <hi>and I of Chriſt,</hi> ver. 12. <hi>is Chriſt Divided? was Paul crucified for you, &amp;c. or were you baptized into the name of</hi> Paul? ver. 13. But if you pleaſe to obſerve the main ſcope and drift of this holy Apoſtle in the 1, 2, 3, 10, 12, 13,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:115061:33"/>
and 14. Chapter of this firſt <hi>Epiſtle;</hi> they all drive at <hi>union,</hi> teaching <hi>uniting principles</hi> and preſſing <hi>uniting practices;</hi> affirming to them, that whatſoever pretences or arguments they might have to juſtifie their <hi>Diviſions,</hi> &amp;c. yet they muſt neceſſarily ariſe from carnal principles, Chap. 3. verſe 3. And in the 12th Chapter, he commends to their conſideration unanſwerable <hi>uniting</hi> Arguments; in the 13th Chapter, he preſſeth them to <hi>uniting</hi> graces: in the 14th Chapter, directs to <hi>uniting</hi> Duties; <hi>videlicet,</hi> orderly improving their gifts to the Churches <hi>Edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So to the Church of <hi>Rome; Mark them which cauſe Diviſions,</hi> &amp;c. Rom. 16, 17. So to the Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latians the 5. and 6. Chapters, <hi>But if ye bite and devour one another, ye ſhall be conſumed one of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> Chap. 5.15. So to the Epheſians the 2, 3, and 4. Chapters, eſpecially Chap. 4. verſe 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6. <hi>I therefore the Priſoner of the Lord beſeech you, that you walk worthy of the vocation wherewith ye are called, with all lowlineſs and meckneſs, with long-ſuffering, forbearing one another in Love; endeavouring to keep the</hi> Unity <hi>of the Spirit in the bond of Peace: there is</hi> one <hi>Body, and</hi> one <hi>Spirit, even as ye are called in</hi> one <hi>Hope of your calling:</hi> One <hi>Lord,</hi> One <hi>Faith,</hi> One <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> One <hi>God and Father of all, who is above all, and through all, and in you all:</hi> So to the <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. 1, 2, 3, 4, 5. eſpecially the firſt verſe. <hi>If there be any conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:115061:34"/>
in Chriſt, if any comfort of Love, if any fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip of the Spirit, if any bowels and mercies; Fulfil ye my joy, that ye be like minded, having the ſame love, being of</hi> one <hi>accord, of one minde. Let nothing be done through ſtrife, or vain-glory, but in lowlineſs of minde, let each eſteem other better then themſelves. Look not every man on his own things, but every man alſo on the things of others. Let this minde be in you, which was alſo in Chriſt Jeſus:</hi> So to the <hi>Coloſſians,</hi> Chap. 3.12, 13, 14, 15, verſes: <hi>Put on therefore (as the elect of God, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and beloved) bowels of mercy, kindeneſs, hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſs of minde, meekneſs, long-ſuffering, for-bearing one another, and forgiving one another, if any man hath a quarrel againſt any; even as Chriſt forgave you, ſo alſo do ye. And above all theſe things put on Charity, which is the bond of perfectneſs. And let the peace of God rule in your hearts, to the which alſo ye are called in</hi> one <hi>body, and be ye thankfull:</hi> And thus we might track him through all his Epiſtles; he hath ſometimes more or leſs of this doctrine, as the ſtate of the people to whom he writ required.</p>
            <p>By which exhortations, and earneſt perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, you may obſerve how much the <hi>unity</hi> of Gods Churches and Saints were upon the heart of this bleſſed Apoſtle, having doubtleſs that Maxime of our Saviour much upon his heart; that a Church no more then a Kingdom, or houſe divided againſt it ſelf could not ſtand,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:115061:34"/>
               <hi>Matthew</hi> 12.25. From all which I Argue;</p>
            <p>That if the union of Gods Church, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting diviſions and ſeparations amongſt his people, were upon the hearts of the moſt holy and faithfull ſervants of God in all ages and ſttates of the Church, as a principal and ſpecial mercy to labour the attaining of; it then ought to be of the ſame eſteem and weight with all his now.</p>
            <p>But that is evident by what hath been ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; <hi>Ergo,</hi> the <hi>union</hi> of Gods Church, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ought to be principally upon the hearts of the ſervants of God now.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The fifth general Head from whence we ſhall argue, is, from the ſeveral <hi>Similitudes</hi> and <hi>Metaphors</hi> the Church of God is compared unto in Scripture; whereby their mutual intereſt in, &amp; <hi>union</hi> with one another is ſo lively held forth, of which I ſhall onely mention ſome few, by which the Reader may make uſe of the reſt to the ſame end.</p>
            <p>Firſt, From the Similitude of Beleevers, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Gods Children, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.26. and thereby of his <hi>houſhsld, Gal.</hi> 6.10. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.1. from whence I Argue;</p>
            <p>That all perſons who ſtand in an equal rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to God as children, and are thereby all equally of Gods <hi>family</hi> of the <hi>houſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ld of faith, Gal.</hi> 6.10. have all an equal <hi>right</hi> unto and <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt</hi> in the <hi>priviledges</hi> and <hi>proviſions</hi> of <hi>Gods
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:115061:35"/>
houſe</hi> proportionable to their place therein; nay though prodigal children if they will return, may encourage themſelves ſo to do from the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of that intereſt they have in the plenty of bread in their <hi>Fathers houſe, Luke</hi> 15.17. but all viſible gracious perſons, or true beleevers do ſtand in an <hi>equal relation</hi> to God as <hi>Children,</hi> and thereby of his <hi>houſhould: Ergo,</hi> they ought all to be <hi>equally admitted by one another</hi> to the free par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipation in the priviledges and proviſions of their <hi>Fathers houſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond Argument; If it be a ſin in men who are truſted by earthly parents, with the care and guardianſhip of their Children until they come to Age, to with-hold from them that part of their portion appointed for their main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance in their nonage, to the hazard of the ſtarving or ruine of the Orphants; then it muſt be a greater ſin in Gods miniſters, and Churches whom God hath intruſted with that part of his <hi>Childrens portion</hi> which the Father hath appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them for their ſpiritual maintenance in their <hi>nonage</hi> of this life, to withhold or detain it from them: But is a grievious crying ſin in the former Caſe; <hi>Ergo</hi> in the latter.</p>
            <p>Third Argument. If it would not conſiſt with true natural affection, and the <hi>fatherly</hi> Care and wiſdom of an earthly father only to make <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion</hi> for his moſt healthfull ſtrong and lovely Children, and leave the ſickly, weak and deform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:115061:35"/>
in a ſtarving Condition, much leſs can it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt, with the affection wiſdom and care of the moſt merciful and heavenly Father, (<hi>who knows how to pitty his children,</hi> Pſal. 103.13. <hi>who much more knows how to give good things to them that ask him:</hi> Mat. 7.11. <hi>who when his childen ask bread, will not give a ſtone,</hi> verſ. 9. <hi>who though a mother may forget her ſucking child,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>yet he cannot forget his,</hi> Iſa. 49.15.)</p>
            <p>To make proviſion for the ſtrong, and health<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and lovely, and to leave the diſeaſed, weak, and unlovely in a periſhing ſtate: But it would not conſiſt with the former;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ergo</hi> not with the latter.</p>
            <p>Nay, the Scripture holds forth a more ſpecial extraordinary care in the Lord of ſick &amp; weak ſouls, then of ſtrong and healthy: <hi>The whole needs no Phyſitian, but they that are</hi> Sick, Luke 5.31. <hi>He ſhall feed his flock like a Shepherd: he ſhall gather the</hi> Lambs <hi>in his Arms, and carry them in his boſom; and ſhall gently lead thoſe that are with young,</hi> Iſa. 40.11.</p>
            <p>And the contrary unmercifull diſpoſition in his people he ſeverely reproves, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 34.4. <hi>The diſeaſed have ye not ſtrengthened, neither have ye healed that which was ſick, neither have bound up that which was broken, neither have ye brought again that which was driven away, neither have ye ſought that which was</hi> loſt; <hi>but with force and with cruelty have ye ruled them;</hi> compare this with
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:115061:36"/>
the tenth verſe, from which Scriptures it is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, That our heavenly Father is a mercifull tender Father to all, but eſpecially to the <hi>weak;</hi> they ſtand in more need of Church guidance and feeding then the ſtrong doth; And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore for any one to deny the benefit of Church-priviledges and proviſions to ſuch as are viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble beleevers, and ſincere in the main, and walk cloſe with God according to the light received by them, upon the conſideration of leſſer errors and weakneſſes, then what by a viſible Rule <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaints</hi> them, or brings them within Church cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, as they have no Authority, ſo have they no example from the Lord for it: The weak and diſeaſed of Gods children are not onely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided for by him, but moſt eſpecially upon his heart to be taken care of, and therefore not to be denied the <hi>priviledges</hi> and <hi>proviſions of his houſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond Metaphor whereby the neceſſity of the Saints union is lively held forth, is their <hi>memberſhip</hi> of the ſame <hi>body:</hi> now of all relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, this is leaſt conſiſtent without <hi>unity;</hi> if they be living <hi>members,</hi> though ſome may be <hi>lame,</hi> and others <hi>weak;</hi> yet the other <hi>members</hi> will not deſpiſe, nor cut them off whiles there is any hope of cure; but rather take more care for the preſervation and recovery of them; and therefore ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>If one member ſuffer, all ſuffer with it,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.26. in which Chapter
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:115061:36"/>
he doth fully ſpeak to the duty of <hi>unity</hi> amongſt <hi>members</hi> of the ſame <hi>body,</hi> proving that the <hi>eye</hi> cannot ſay to the <hi>hand,</hi> nor the head to the <hi>feet,</hi> I have no need of thee; but that the Lord had ſo ordered the State of the body, that the moſt feeble, and uncomely <hi>members</hi> ſhould have their office in and care from the body, the comly and uſeful have, verſe 21, 22, 23, 24, That there might be no Schiſm in the body; but that the <hi>members</hi> ſhould have the ſame care one for ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, verſe 25. From whence I argue;</p>
            <p>That if all the members of Chriſts body have a right unto the priviledges, and benefits of their <hi>memberſhip,</hi> and have upon them a mutual duty of care, and ſervice to one another,</p>
            <p>Then ought no <hi>members</hi> to exclude each other from their right of <hi>memberſhip</hi> in the body.</p>
            <p>But all Chriſts true <hi>members</hi> of his viſible <hi>body,</hi> have an equal right to the priveledges and duties of their place in the body, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ergo,</hi> None ought to exclude each other from their right of <hi>memberſhip.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which might be added that of branches, of the ſame Root, Sheep of the ſame Fold, under the ſame Shepheard, Plants in the ſame Garden, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides their holy fellowſhip, 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.3. in the fellowſhip of the Gopel, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. Fellowſhip of Chriſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.9. Fellowſhip of the ſpirit, 2 <hi>Phil.</hi> 1. ſo fellow-Citizens, <hi>Eph.</hi> 9.19 Fellow Heirs, <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.6. Fellow-ſervants, <hi>Matt.</hi> 18.28,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:115061:37"/>
29. and chap. 24.49. Fellow-Soldiers, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. 25. All which relations implie <hi>mutnall intereſt</hi> in the publique Stock of their fellowſhip, and would afford plenty of Arguments to prove this duty of the <hi>unity</hi> of Saints in all their joynt pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges and duties as ſuch. But I ſhall leave them to the Readers own meditation; and ſhall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to the ſixth general head.</p>
            <p>The ſixth ſort of Argument, ſhall be drawn from the evident ſad conſequences that attend the Church and People of God, through their ſeparating and dividing from one another; and their uniting together upon other principles then that of viſible grace.</p>
            <p>The many and great evills that enter in at this door (if former ages had left us without preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents) the age in which we live will afford us ſad experience, that the old Machivilian principle, <hi>divide</hi> if ye will <hi>deſtroy</hi>—hath much truth in it; and therefore when <hi>Jacob</hi> would pronounce a curſe againſt <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Levi</hi> for their iniquity he ſaith; I will divide them in <hi>Jacob,</hi> and ſcatter them in <hi>Iſrael. Gen</hi> 49.7. And ſo the Church complaines, <hi>Lam.</hi> 4, 16. The an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of the Lotd hath divided them, he will no more regard them.</p>
            <p>Diviſion is an evident forerunner of deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the former being uſualy inflicted upon a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple as a forerunning Judgment to make way for the latter; and from thence was the force of our
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:115061:37"/>
Saviours Argument, <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.25. <hi>Every King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom divided againſt it ſelf is brought to deſolation, and every City or houſe divided againſt it ſelf can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſtand;</hi> implying that diviſion prepares a king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom for deſolation, and removes the ſtrength by which the united City or Houſe ſtands; And therefore <hi>for the diviſions of</hi> Reuben, <hi>Jud</hi> 5.16. <hi>there were great ſearchings of heart;</hi> partly to find out and remove the cauſe, and partly to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare and arme themſelves againſt the neceſſary and ſad conſequences that might attend them: which Duty the diviſion of our days among Gods people loudly calls for: which to ſpeak a word unto, I ſhall make a little digreſſion; which is to entreat all who deſire in ſincerity to ſet upon this work of heart-ſearching in order to find out the cauſe and avoid the coſequences of the ſad Diviſions amongſt us, to conſider the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing directions.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Search thine own heart and way throughly; for this curſed ſpirit of Diviſion may have hidde it ſelf under ſuch plauſible pretences of good; that whilſt thou ſeekeſt for it among thy tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and corruptions, it may be cloſe hid in ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral of thy beſt duties, and religious qualificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <p>And therefore if thou find him not amongſt thy temptations of pride of minde, ſelf con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, affecting Singularity, a deſire to ſeem ſome body amongſt thoſe with whom thou
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:115061:38"/>
walkeſt—a loving preheminence, over thy Brethren, or in a froward, raſh uncharita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſpirit &amp;c.</p>
            <p>If thou ſearcheſt thy heart throughly, and find him not dwelling there under the Covert of theſe or the like temptations, or corruptions; then proceed to a further heart ſearching; as to the tryall of thy graces, and religious dutyes: for this ſpirit of darkneſs knows how to transform it ſelf into an angel of light. If thou beeſt one that hath attained to an eminent knowledge, and hath found out the mind of God, in ſome ſpecial truths that many other of Gods people are dark in: then ſearch whether thy knowledge hath not pufft thee up, as in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.18.19. 4 <hi>chap.</hi> verſe 8. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.8. and begotten in thee <hi>an high eſteeme of thine own things, Phil.</hi> 2.4 <hi>and a low eſteem of the things of others, Phil.</hi> 2.3. Whether thy gifts, graces, and religious endowments have not been more employed by thee in promoting and propagating of diſputable points, and doubtfull queſtions, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.1. <hi>tending rather to ſtrife a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout words,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.4. <hi>and</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.23. <hi>and vaine janglins.</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.7. <hi>then to godly edifying,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.26. Whether by thy knowledge thou haſt not laid a ſtumbling block in thy weak brothers way, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.13. by preſſing upon him more remote dutys, while the immediate du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of his preſent ſtate in grace have been neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected, contrary to that of our Saviour who had
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:115061:38"/>
many things to ſay, but could not ſay them then, becauſe the Diſciples could not bear them, <hi>John</hi> 16.12. And to that of <hi>Paul,</hi> who could not ſpeak to the Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> as ſpirituall <hi>but unto carnal, even unto babes in Chriſt,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 1. And therefore fed them with milke; and not with ſtrong meat, verſe 2. I ſay ſearch and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine whether thy knowledge hath not been employed by this Spirit of Diviſion in ſome ſuch or the like failings which hath ſo viſibly tended to the promoting the diſſentions and diviſions among <hi>Gods People.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſecondly, Art thou one that hath attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to an extraordinary zeal for God, his wayes and truths, that thou thinkeſt thou couldeſt ſay with the Pſalmiſt, <hi>The zeal of thy Houſe hath eaten me up,</hi> Pſal. 69.9. then ſearch and try thy zeal, for fear this ſpirit of diviſion hath not hid it ſelf there: the Jews miſguided zeal, mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Acts</hi> 21.20. provoked them to cry out againſt <hi>Paul;</hi> verſe 28. <hi>Men of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>help! this is the man that teacheth all men everywhere againſt the people, and the Law, and this place,</hi> &amp;c. It was <hi>Paul</hi>'s miſguided zeal before converſion, for the tradition of his fathers, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.14. that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked him <hi>beyond meaſure to perſecute the Church of God, and waſte it,</hi> verſe 13. and ſo <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.6. And therefore when thou art zealous, be ſure it be in a good thing, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4, 18. It is dangerous be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing exceedingly zealous for points of Doctrine,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:115061:39"/>
or practice in matters diſputable, and much controverted betwixt both godly and able Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians; leaſt whileſt like thoſe Phariſees, <hi>Luke</hi> 11.42. thou be zealous <hi>in Tything Mint, and Rue, and paſs over Judgement, and the Love of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For as holy zeal rightly managed, is the moſt excellent grace among Chriſtians; ſo miſguided is the moſt dangerous; and thus in thy ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of heart, for the diviſions among Saints, go on by the ſame rule to ſearch and try every grace and gift in thee, leſt thou miſſeſt of thy care in ſearching the wound.</p>
            <p>Now for the ſad effects and evil conſequences flowing from <hi>Diviſions</hi> among Chriſtians, I may ſay they are unmentionable; for it is very hard to name an evil, that at this day the people of God, and this Commonwealth groans under, that our Diviſions hath not had an hand in, if not the main cauſe of.</p>
            <p>Is there cauſe to complain; the much prayed for, and expected reformation hath been ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed and retarded?</p>
            <p>Why, conſider whether Diviſion hindred it not; if the generality of the godly could but agreed on good things, to have propoſed them, or joyntly deſired them, we have not wanted an Authority to have granted and confirmed them: but the ſeveral opinions and perſwaſions in Religion have had every one a Reformation to promote; wherein an equal proviſion of
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:115061:39"/>
liberty, and encouragement for all that are truly godly, have been declined, and the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treams of each of their different perſwaſions inſiſted on, like the cruel harlot <hi>Solomon</hi> gave judgement againſt, they have rather choſen half a dead child, then their oppoſites ſhould enjoy a living one.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Is there cauſe to complain of the ſpread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Errors, Hereſies, and Blaſphemies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Why, Diviſion opens the door for them; for every one making their particular opinions a particular different Religion; and ſeparating thereupon, hath given a kinde of reputation to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>aration, though it be from the moſt pure Churches, and holy people; ſo that if any make ſhipwrack of Faith and a good conſcience, and ſuck in principles inconſiſtent with grace and godlineſs: And obſerve, they will not be born among the people with whom they then walked; why, it is but ſeparating, and ſetting up for themſelves, and they have field-room enough to ſowe their tares in.</p>
            <p>Whereas were the people of God, who are ſound in the Subſtantials of Religion, <hi>united</hi> together within the bounds before mentioned, and exerciſing that diſcipline God hath ſet in his Church, it would bear an Authority, that as the Apoſtle ſaith, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.14. <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.8. <hi>The offending perſon would be aſhamed,</hi> which now it doth not; for now the perſonmarked, <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.17. or with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawn
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:115061:40"/>
from, with all others obſerving him not of the ſame way or fellowſhip with them that paſt the cenſure, do but look at it, as a cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure paſt by a few Chriſtians upon the account of opinion, and from thence heed it not: That I may ſay the ſolemn Ordinances of Chriſt, for the healing and recovery of the diſeaſed and infected of his people, are become contemptible, which nothing but the union of his Church (that the cenſure of one congregation may be the cenſure of the whole) will remedy.</p>
            <p>And then if the walls of our Goſpel <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> were again repaired, the gates might be kept ſhut againſt all that is <hi>Infectious,</hi> as well as t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nclean,</hi> which whiles the one lies waſte, the other will ſtand open.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Is there cauſe to complain, that Religion is ſadly decayed, the Profeſſors of it are gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally abated in their zeal for it, life or livelineſs in it, and love unto it?</p>
            <p>Why, it is evident Diviſions are the main cauſe of that too; for the great noiſe that hath been made amongſt the Profeſſors of Religion in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral about their different judgements (nay in moſt particular Societies of the ſame way, there hath not wanted ſo much difference of minde amongſt them, as to occaſion much debates, diſputings and vain janglings) hath con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>verted the time and pains of ſuch who ſhould have laboured in the teaching and hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:115061:40"/>
forth heart-ſearching, quickning words to the people, into controverſies and unprofitable Subjects not tending to ſpiritual edification, and from the ſame cauſe the generality of Profeſſors have had their heads filled with notional Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and their hearts with diſcouraging im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent ſcruples and doubts; thus ſtriving about the ſhadow until they have loſt the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, contending about the true form until they have loſt the true power.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Is Religion in the power of it become con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible with formal Profeſſors and the carnal multitude, and moſt faithfull Preachers in many places little followed nor eſteemed, whereby the work of converſion hath little ſucceſs, <hi>&amp;c?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Why, in theſe evils, Diviſions hath had the greateſt hand; for what will formall Profeſſors and carnal people ſay to you, if you ask them, why they take up in the <hi>form,</hi> and reject the <hi>power</hi> of Religion, and ſcorn and oppoſe the Profeſſors of it? why, they will anſwer; we know not which of your new Religions to chooſe; when you can agree among your ſelves which is the right way, and what Religion you will be of, then you ſhall know more of our mindes; from whoſe anſwer you may plainly perceive, that they judge all the difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt them and others that profeſſe the power of Religion, is the difference in opinions; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as were opinions leſs heeded, and Religion more
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:115061:41"/>
placed in the power and life of godlineſs; if Chriſtians would uſe the ſame Arguments a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>againſt ſuch as David did (<hi>Pſalm</hi> 4.2.3. <hi>Oh ye ſons of men, how long will ye turn my glory into ſhame; how long will ye love vanity; and ſeek after leaſing. Selah. But know that the Lord hath ſet apart him, that is Godly for himſelf</hi>) they would not bleſs themſelves in the evil before mentioned, as they do.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Doth Religion, as to the power and ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ality of it, begin to grow daily leſs and leſs in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt with many perſons in Authority? That whereas formerly Religion and gracious qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations in perſons were moſt enquired after, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> firſt approved of, its now with them little ſet by, unleſs the perſon to be admitted be of the ſame opinion with the Admittor; or at leaſt of that opinion which ſhal add ſomething to his reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and intereſt to be a favourer of: but to ſhew reſpect and countenance to a religions man as he is a religious man, which was the principle owned by the inſtruments God chiefly choſe to carry on his work by in its low eſtate, this much decayes.</p>
            <p>Why, Diviſions about opinions in Religion, hath been the cauſe hereof too. For at that time when Religion was ſo much in requeſt with moſt perſons in Authority, it was before Religion was ſo much diſſolved into diſputes and opinions, as it is now; and it is evident
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:115061:41"/>
that reputation which a gratious humble pious diſpoſition and converſation gave religious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons generally once in the eyes of Authority, and ſeveral perſons of eminency in place, the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry frame of ſpirit and converſation, that have ſince overſpread ſo many profeſſing perſons about different opinions hath loſt it ſo far as it is diminiſhed: and I muſt ſay of all perſons, the hot contenders about opinions, of all hands, have the leaſt ground to be offended at this; for I know few of them, if they had power in their hands, would reform it. But it is evident that ſo far as there may be ground for this complaint, the contentions, ſtrifes, and vain janglings about opinions in Religion hath cauſed it, by being ſtumbling blocks, and cauſe of offence to ſeveral in Authority, not able to bear it, nor to diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh betwixt the weakneſſes and offences of ſome violent promoters of an opinion they diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent from; and the innocency or truth of the opinion it ſelf, or the generality of people pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing it, which with the diſcouragements put upon many truly gratious, for their judgement ſake, by ſome rigid froward perſons in Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity in ſeveral places, I deſire the Lord may make thoſe in chief Authority in time ſenſible of, whoſe hearts I hope are yet preſerved ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere to God in this matter, if they had but a right underſtanding of caſes, which for want of, they may too ſlightly paſs over.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:115061:42"/>6. Is that glorious cauſe of God in theſe Nations ſo wonderfully owned, and proſpered by him in the hands of his people, for ſo many years paſt, wherein he hath ſo eminetly manifeſted his ſubduing overturning power againſt his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and with all his aſſiſting and ſtrengthen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing power with his people to whom that graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous promiſe, <hi>Levit.</hi> 26.7. hath been fulfilled, <hi>And ye ſhall chaſe your enemies, and they ſhall fall before you by the ſword. And five of you ſhall chaſe an hundred, and an hundred of you ſhall put ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand to flight,</hi> &amp;c. From whence all the Nations round about have been put to ſilence, and made to confeſs with the Heathen, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 126.2.3. <hi>The Lord hath done great things for us:</hi> is this glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious day of Gods preſence overſhadowed with clouds of ſcorn and contempt from enemies both at home and abroad, that there is cauſe to fear our Sun will ſet at noon? why conſider what a great hand our Diviſions in Religion hath had in this; for this carnal ſpirit of Diviſions in the things of God hath been the mother of all our Diviſions and Factions in civil things; for ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral particular opinions in Religion have diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved into particular Factions and intereſts of State, wherein the mutual common good of all good men hath been declined, each party la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring to ſet up it ſelf above the reſt, and hath onely prevailed in this, to keep thoſe things down, wherein the mutual good and benefit of
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:115061:42"/>
the whole conſiſted, and to weaken the hands of ſuch whoſe hearts were ſincere and uprightly diſpoſed to the common good, that they have been conſtrained to throw much of the richeſt loading of the ſhip of this new Commonwealth overboard in this ſtorm, in order to ſave the whole from ſinking: from whence hath alſo proceeded thoſe obſtructing oppoſitions that have been betwixt good men, with thoſe uncha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable reflections and aſperſions they have one endeavoured to caſt upon another, to the laying open and publiſhing to the view of their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Adverſaries all, (nay, more then all) their frailties and weakneſſes; from whence they have taken encouragement from time to time to ſtrengthen themſelves in their evil principles; concluding that a people thus divided and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>united could not long preſerve themſelves, much leſs protect them, if they ſhould have inclined to a peaceable acquieſcence in their preſent conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on under them; and from thence they have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken encouragement to attempt what they have done, and even to make uſe of ſome of our ſelves to carry on their treacherous, and wicked diſigns by: and to an eye of reaſon, unleſs the Lord do ſpeedily unite all or moſt good men joyntly to agree, and ſtand by one another in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moting of, and preſerving the common good of the whole, it will not be poſſible long to bear up againſt ſuch an united and potent adverſary
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:115061:43"/>
with ſuch a miſerable divided, diſtracted people, as our diviſions render us to be; that if the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God, and the good of his people ſhould be of no weight with us, yet if we were not ſtupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with this ſpirit of Diviſion, ſelf-preſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on might be ſufficient to ſtir up all ſober-minded to labour for union among all good men, leſt whiles we ſtrive for that we cannot obtain, we loſe what we do poſſeſs. I might proceed to mention the loſs of all thoſe eminently worthy inſtruments, both military and civil, that our diviſions hath laid aſide, even of ſeveral judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and prevented their generation in a great meaſure of the benefit of their abilities and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; beſides a great number of mean-ſpirited and uncertain-principled perſons, who are thereby crept into places of power, wherein they carry themſelves much to the diſcourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and grievance of ſeveral precious to the Lord, &amp; the encreaſe of whom even threatens the return of all thoſe hard meaſures to Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple they have been by a mighty hand of his for ſeveral years delivered from, there wanting no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but a ſupream Magiſtrate to countenance or permit ſuch to oppreſs and perſecute; and if any perſon branded with a nick-name of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſhould diſcover or ſpeak his ſenſe of this thing, or of any perſon ſo qualified, it would be anſwered, he is not of your opinion, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you eſteem him not.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:115061:43"/>That let any perſon in power have never ſo much manifeſt prejudice in his heart againſt godlineſs and a pious life: why, he hath by our diviſions an opportunity to exerciſe it under the vizzard of oppoſing errors and hereſies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> without being diſcovered as an enemy to godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; and the ſame opportunity hath any car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal principled or froward ſpirited preacher to ſtigmatize and wound holy perſons and princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and incenſe Authority and the rude multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude againſt them, and to cruſh the power of Religion in their pariſhes, by exalting ſome pleaſing form of it to the people; and by the advantage of the diviſions among the Godly can put a plauſible vail over all this; It is onely againſt Schiſmaticks and Hereticks, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> they ſpeak.</p>
            <p>Nay, further, if we take a view of all the hard meaſure that any gracious tender ſpirited perſons in Authority have met with, to the weaking their hands from profeſſors of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it proceeds generally from this cauſe: ſuch of them as have endeavoured to bear an even hand towards all they judge Godly, and to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend an equal encouragement to all that fear God without reſpect to opinion; why preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that ſpirit of jealouſie and emulation, this ſpirit of Diviſion hath begotten, will ſuggeſt apprehenſions of their want of Love to Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Gods people and truths, ſuch are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:115061:44"/>
eſteemed men of looſe uncertain princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, favourers of Hereticks and Schiſmaticks, diſcountenancers of publick worſhip, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructers of Reformation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> on the one hand; and yet at the ſame time eſteemed lukewarm <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>odiceans,</hi> carnal Politicians, and complyers with carnal principles, and intereſts, time-ſervers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> on the other hand, when all the matter is, they do not give a ſpecial or peculiar reſpect to the private opinion of ſuch perſons as finde them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves grieved above other their brethren, equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly godly; by which means the hands of ſome in chief places have been weakened, and their hearts diſcouraged in the work of their genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and ſome others who have for a long time profeſſed an equal reſpect to all the godly, have been offended, and ſtumbled; and from thence have withdrawn their countenance from ſome of the godly, and thereby ſtrengthened the hands of Dividers and inſulting principles and ſpirits; which poor <hi>Ireland</hi> at this day hath ſad experience of.</p>
            <p>I might further minde that general dejection of ſpirit that ſeems to be upon many godly Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates and people in the work of their gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, with that encreaſe on the other hand, of confidence and height of ſpirit in oppoſers and malignant Adverſaries.</p>
            <p>But to conclude, it is hard to name an evil of a publick nature, either in Church or Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:115061:44"/>
that diviſions among the Godly hath not had a great hand in, if not been the chief cauſe thereof.</p>
            <p>From all that hath beene ſaid to this head I ſhall argue;</p>
            <p>That that evill which is the inlet and ſupport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of ſuch a multitude of other evills, muſt needs be a very great evill, and of all other evills to be avoided and laboured againſt.</p>
            <p>But it is evident ſuch is the evill of Saints Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions; Therefore it ought of all evills to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voided and laboured againſt.</p>
            <p n="7">7. The laſt general head from which I ſhall argue, is from the evident and unſpeakable good both to Church and Commonwealth, and Soul and Body, the union of Saints upon ſuch Goſpel ſtable principles would be attended with.</p>
            <p>Whatſoever hath been obſerved before as the evill of Diviſions, union muſt neceſſarily be the remover of, which I ſhall not need again to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peat, but ſhall leave the Reader to obſerve and ſatisfie himſelf in by meditation: For the moſt happy Commonwealth, City, Nation, Family, or Society of men, it is evident to the very light of nature and reaſon, that union in their commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities is the preſervation of their happineſs, nay the perfection of union is part of the Glory and happineſs of heaven; And therefore of the Church of God on earth.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:115061:45"/>Thoſe pretious promiſes in Scripture foretell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the glorious eſtate of Gods Church on earth do declare the Excellency of it ſhall be its union and peace, as <hi>Iſay</hi> 11. <hi>The Wolfe ſhall dwell with the Lamb; and the Leopord ſhall lie down with the Kid, and the Calf and the Young Lyon and the Fatling together, and a little Child ſhall lead them, verſ.</hi> 6: <hi>And the ſucking child ſhall play on the hole of the Aſpe &amp;c. They ſhall not hurt nor deſtroy in all my holy Mountaine &amp;c. verſes</hi> 8, 9.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Envy alſo of Ephraim ſhall depart &amp;c. Ephraim ſhall not envy Judah, nor Judah ſhall not vex Ephraim, verſe</hi> 13. <hi>and ſo Ezek.</hi> 37.22. <hi>And I will make them one Nation in the Land upon the Mountaines of Iſrael, And one King ſhall be King to them all, and they ſhall be no more two Nations, neither ſhall they be divided into two Kingdoms any more, and</hi> David <hi>my Servant ſhall be King over them, and they all ſhal have one Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd, ſo</hi> Zech. 14.9. <hi>And the Lord ſhall be King over all the earth; in that day ſhall there be one Lord, and his name one.</hi> But more particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly,</p>
            <p n="1">1. This glorious <hi>union</hi> of Gods Church would renew its <hi>ſtrength,</hi> that though now in its <hi>divided</hi> ſhattered ſtate it ſhews it ſelf like Iſrael ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered abroad throughout all the Land of <hi>Egypt</hi> to gather ſtubble,<hi>Exod.</hi> 5.12, in which ſtate every Petty task-maſter of <hi>Pharcah</hi> can exerciſe Tyranny over them, <hi>ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ.</hi> 14. but if once <hi>united,</hi>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:115061:45"/>
they would then be in the ſight of their enemies, as <hi>Iſrael</hi> gathered together was in the plains of <hi>Moab, terrible</hi> for their enemies to look upon, <hi>Numb.</hi> 22.3. their beholders then, inſtead of cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, of them would ſay: <hi>How goodly are thy tents, O</hi> Jacob, <hi>and thy Tabernacles, O</hi> Iſrael! <hi>Numbers</hi> 24.5. <hi>He hath as it were the ſtrength of an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nicorn; he ſhall eat up the Nations his enemies, and ſhall break their bones, and pierce them through with his arrows,</hi> verſe. 8. The Church in its <hi>united</hi> State, is like a City with <hi>walls</hi> and <hi>bulwarks, Iſa.</hi> 26.1. <hi>In that day ſhall this ſong be ſung in the Land of</hi> Judah: <hi>We have a ſtrong City, Salvation will God appoint for walls and bulwarks. Beautifull as</hi> Tirzah, <hi>comly as</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>Terrible as an Army with Baxners, Cant.</hi> 6.4, 10.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The renewing of the Churches <hi>unity</hi> would renew its <hi>purity;</hi> when there ſhall be <hi>One Lord,</hi> and his <hi>Name One, Zach.</hi> 14.9. <hi>Every Pot</hi> in <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> ſhall be <hi>holy</hi> unto the Lord, verſe 21. The way of the Lord ſhall then be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the way of <hi>holineſs, Iſay.</hi> 35.8. compared with the 9th. The Gates of the holy City might then be ſhut, that there ſhould no more paſs through the uncircumciſed and unclean.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Churches unity would repair its <hi>repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation</hi> and <hi>eſteem; the precious ſons of Sion more precious then fine gold, how are they</hi> eſteemed <hi>as</hi> earthen Pitchers <hi>in their ſcattered divided State,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:115061:46"/>
Lam.</hi> 4.2. The Church may then truly complain; <hi>how is the gold become dim, the moſt fine gold changed; the ſtones of the Sanctuary are poured out on the top of every ſtreet,</hi> verſe 1. they are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed as the Common pibbles of the Brook; eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry vile abject, every mean, baſe, vile-ſpirited man, can look uppon precious Saints, if but branded with a nicknamed Religion, as a meaner creature then himſelf, of which the Church complains, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 44.11. <hi>Thou haſt given us like ſheep, appointed for meat<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and haſt ſcattered us among the heathen;</hi> and from thence in the 13th verſe complains, <hi>thou makeſt us a reproach to our neighbours, and a ſcorn and deriſion to them that are round about us; thou makeſt us a by-word among the heathen, and a ſhaking of the head among the people.</hi> But when <hi>Sion</hi> comes to be a City with Walls and Towers, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 48.12, 13. then <hi>Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull for ſtituation, the joy of the whole earth is mount</hi> Sion, verſe 2. then the abjects and baſe people ſhall be ſo far from ſcorning her, and ſhaking the head at her; <hi>That loe Kings, when aſſembled, and paſs by together, ſhall ſee her, they ſhall marvel, and be troubled, and haſte away; fear ſhall take hold upon them, and pain as on a woman in travel,</hi> verſes 4, 5, 6.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The renewing the unity of the Church will renew the growth and <hi>increaſe</hi> of the Church; it is a ſad and juſt complaint of many of the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in theſe dayes, that converting work ceaſeth,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:115061:46"/>
we are ſpending all upon the old Stock; Why, what hinders, as a ſecond cauſe, ſo much as our diviſions? I am perſwaded, that never ſince the aſcention of him that aſcended up on high to give gifts unto men, and the ceſſation of extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary gifts, there hath been ſuch a meaſure of ſpiritual gifts given forth as this day affoords; never more painfull Labourers ſent into Gods harveſt; nor more able faithfull Paſtors and Teachers given to his Churches, of all perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, <hi>for the perfecting of the Saints, for the work of the Miniſtry, for the edifying of the body of Chriſt, Epheſ.</hi> 4.11, 12.</p>
            <p>But this overflowing ſpirit of Diviſion, like a ſweeping rain in harveſt, carries all the fruit away; or like the froſts in ſpring, nips all in the bud.</p>
            <p>This ſpirit may well be reckoned as the chief of <hi>thoſe little foxes that ſpoils the vines; for our vines have tender grapes,</hi> as <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.15. for no ſooner is a ſoul brought to a ſenſe of his loſt eſtate by nature, and begins to enquire after Chriſt, to ſay with the Jaylor, What ſhall I do? but forthwith it meets with, from this ſpirit, ſuch a multitude of needleſs, or at leſt unſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable queſtions and doubts in its minde, about ſome of the points in controverſie, that diſſolves all its beginnings of <hi>heart</hi>-work into <hi>head</hi>-work; that moſt of Chriſts new born babes at this day, inſtead of deſiring the ſincere milk of the word
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:115061:47"/>
to grow thereby, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.2. will at firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to drink wine, and feed on ſtrong meat, which they being not able to digeſt, fall into ſpiritual ſurfeits, from whence proceed ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual loathings of heavenly things, ſpiritual ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, and diſeaſes of all ſorts, which ſo many poor Profeſſors at this day lie languiſhing under; whereas if once the Lord ſhould unite his people upon the principles of viſible grace, all would then be joyntly concerned chiefly to propagate thoſe <hi>principles</hi> of grace and <hi>godlineſs,</hi> upon which they were <hi>united;</hi> and though moſt of the points in controverſie might remain of weight upon the hearts of all that ſincerely hold them, to be faithfull to their conſciences in walking up in the practice of them; yet there would be an holy tenderneſs of troubling the heads of young Converts, or weak Chriſtians, with unreaſonable ſcruples; but each ſober mind would take the Apoſtles advice, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.1. <hi>Him that is weak in the faith, receive you, but not to doubtfull diſputations.</hi> And with the Apoſtle <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> would exhort them, <hi>to add to their faith, ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue; and to vertue, knowledge; and to knowledge, temperance; and to temperance, patience; and to patience, godlineſs; and to godlineſs, brotherly kindeneſs; and to brotherly kindneſs, charity;</hi> 2 Pet. 1.5, 6, 7. <hi>and to tell them, if theſe things be in them, and abound, they ſhall neither be barren nor unfruitfull in the knowledge of the Lord Jeſus
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:115061:47"/>
Chriſt,</hi> verſe 8. That the unity of Gods people in principles of viſible grace and godlineſs, would much tend to the <hi>encreaſe and growth</hi> of Gods Church; therefore in the glorious day of the Churches <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion, Iſa.</hi> 60. <hi>when violence ſhall no more be heard in the land, nor waſting, nor deſtruction within thy borders; but thou ſhalt call thy walls Salvation, and thy gates praiſe,</hi> verſe 18. <hi>Then ſhall Kings come to thy light, and Kings to the brightneſs of thy riſing,</hi> verſe 3. <hi>then ſhall the Abundance of the Sea be Converted unto thee,</hi> verſe 5. It ſhall be then ſaid, <hi>who are theſe that flye like a Cloud, and as the Doves to the Windows,</hi> verſe 8. <hi>The Sons alſo of them that afflicted thee ſhall come bending to thee, and All they that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed thee ſhall bow themſelves down at the ſoles of thy feet, and They ſhall call thee the City of the Lord, the</hi> Sion <hi>of the holy one of</hi> Iſrael, verſe 14. That whereas in thy divided <hi>diſunited</hi> State, thou haſt been <hi>forſaken and ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed, ſo that no man went through thee, I will make thee an eternal excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency, a joy of many generations,</hi> verſe 15. the whole Chapter is ſpent in ſeting forth the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty <hi>encreaſe</hi> of Gods Church in the day of its <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. The renewing of the Churches <hi>unity</hi> would abundantly tend to renew its <hi>joy</hi> and <hi>comfort; The ranſomed of the Lord ſhall then return, and come to</hi> Sion <hi>with ſongs and everlaſting joy upon their heads; they ſhall obtain joy and gladneſs; and
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:115061:48"/>
ſorrow and ſighing, ſhall flee away, Iſa.</hi> 35.10. compared with the 8. and 9. verſes, which ſpeaks of the Churches Unity; So <hi>Pſal.</hi> 48.1. <hi>Let mount</hi> Sion <hi>rejoyce; let the Daughter of</hi> Judah <hi>be glad, &amp;c.</hi> compared with the 12. and 13. verſes; which ſpeaks of Unity; if for the divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of <hi>Reuben</hi> there were ſuch great ſearchings of heart, ſurely for the healing of the diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Reuben there muſt flow in great <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort</hi> and <hi>Joy</hi> of heart; and therefore ſaith <hi>David,</hi> who had great experience of the evil of diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons among Gods people, the ſenſe he had thereof, made him cry out, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 133. <hi>How good,</hi> and <hi>how pleaſant</hi> it is for Brethren to live <hi>toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in unity! Its like the precious ointment upon the head, that runs down upon the beard, even</hi> Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons <hi>beard, that went down to the skirts of his gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as the dew of</hi> Hermon, <hi>and as the dew that deſcended upon the mountain of Sion, &amp;c.</hi> He could not think of things excellent enough to compare the <hi>ſweetneſs</hi> and <hi>comfortableneſs</hi> of union unto.</p>
            <p>I might further proceed upon this Head, as to the encreaſe of the Peace and all other outward proſperitie with the encreaſe of all ſpirituall graces, both in the enjoyment and exerciſe of them: but I ſhall leave the reſt to the Readers en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>largement and cloſe up this head with this fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Argument.</p>
            <p>That that mercy which would prepare the
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:115061:48"/>
way for, and bring in with it ſuch a multitude of other precious mercies, muſt needs be it ſelf a glorious mercy, and of all other mercies infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior to it, to be laboured after and prayed for.</p>
            <p>But ſuch is the mercy of the Saints <hi>union</hi> as before; Therefore it ought of all mercies inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or to it to be prayed, and laboured for.</p>
            <p>I ſhall now proceed to the anſwering of ſuch Objections as I can remember to have met with, or have ground to beleeve will be made againſt the ſeveral forementioned heads and arguments drawn from them, which I have deferred for this place rather then to annex them to the head or argument they may moſt properly op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, in regard ſeveral of them are ſo general, that they will include the ſeveral particulars that might be made againſt each part, thereby avoiding prolixity. Now the perſons from whom the enſuing objections may be expected, muſt be either from ſuch as do erre in the extream againſt my firſt propoſition, in not approving of a ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration betwixt Beleevers and Unbeleevers, or viſibly gracious and viſibly ungracious perſons, or otherwiſe from ſuch as do erre in the extream againſt my ſecond generall poſition of the duty of all true Beleevers, and Churches ſeparated from the World <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to walk together in the performances of all Religious worſhip and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices without ſeparating or dividing from one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:115061:49"/>Which two ſorts of perſons will include the contrary-minded to this truth in both <hi>extreams.</hi> And being deſirous to avoid all names of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction that might be offenſive, earneſtly wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that thoſe Nicknames of diviſion among Saints might be like thoſe names of <hi>Baal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m, Hoſ.</hi> 2.17. taken out of our mouths, that the old good names of Beleevers and Unbeleevers, or godly and Ungodly might be again revived:</p>
            <p>I ſhall ſtate the objections in a general way, leaving the reader to chooſe ſuch as are his own, and conſider the Anſwers to them as to himſelf accordingly; for I judge there will be ſeveral ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections that would be joyntly made by perſons of ſeveral perſwaſions, and from ſeveral Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, which to anſwer to diſtinctly would be a meanes to multiply many words to the ſame thing.</p>
            <p>Object. 1. <hi>We do admitt all true Beleevers, and holy gracious perſons to have a right to all Gods Ordinances, and to be admitted as true members of his Church. But they which only ſeem to be ſuch, and are poyſoned with Errours and Deluſions; with which they would infect the flock of Chriſt, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe we only reject and ſpeak againſt as Schiſmaticks and Hereticks</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Such as the Errours, and deluſions may be, your rejection may be juſt; but the generality of Chriſtians ſo rejected, and ſtigmatized with nick-names by you are not of that ſort; but ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:115061:49"/>
holds the foundation points of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and ſubſtance of Religion with you, the difference lying in things very controverſal.</p>
            <p>Now in the pureſt times of the Church, there were believers tainted with divers errors of a dangerous nature, who yet were not rejected, as incommunicable, nor reproached with the odious names of Schiſmaticks, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> by the reſt of their brethren, though ſeveral of them erred in points of great weight; as denying Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by Faith, without the works of the Law; againſt whom <hi>Paul</hi> wrote his Epiſtle to the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> and <hi>Galatians;</hi> the chief ſcope of which Epiſtles being to prove the erroneouſneſs and danger of thoſe Doctrines, with which you may obſerve the <hi>Epheſians, Coloſſians</hi> and <hi>Philippians</hi> were alſo tainted; which error, as it was held by thoſe Chriſtians, I judge was of a more dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous tendency, then the generality of thoſe controverſies, Chriſtians in theſe dayes uſually ſeparate upon: and in the Church of the <hi>Coloſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> there were ſeveral deluded with Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phical errors, and Heatheniſh opinions and cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms, as worſhipping of Angels, <hi>&amp;c. Col.</hi> 2.8. compared with the 16, 17, 18, 19, verſes. And further, what ſad errors and ſchiſms was the Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> infected with? there were contentions, ſtrifes, and vain janglings, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.10. and 3.3, 4. contradiction and contempt of their Miniſters, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.12. even of <hi>Paul</hi>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:115061:50"/>
himſelf, whom God had uſed as the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their converſion, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.12. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.1, 10. given to vexatious, Law ſuits, to the ſhame of the truth among the heathen, chap. 6. verſes 1, 2. and abuſing of their Chriſtian liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to the hazzard of the deſtruction of the Faith of their brethren, chapter 8. Errors in the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration and receiving of the Lords Supper even to the prophaning that holy Ordinance, Chap. 11.</p>
            <p>Yet the Apoſtle in all he wrote againſt theſe great errors and miſcarriages, gives not a word of Command or direction to the more ſober and ſound, to ſeparate from thoſe corrupted, nor caſt them out of the Church, nor to eſteem them as Schiſmaticks, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but labours by ſound Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and holy example, to convince them of their errors; and withall, preſſeth them to unity, and warns them againſt their diviſions, as the worſt of their errors; as it is evident from thoſe Scriptures quoted: From whence I argue;</p>
            <p>That if the Apoſtles and infallible penmen of Scriptures, who were able to judge of matters of controverſie without miſtake, did for the Churches peace ſake, permit perſons holding and maintaining many great and dangerous errors to abide in the Church; and there own them as fellow-Brethren, whileſt they manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed viſible ſanctitie in the main, and retained the ſubſtance of true Faith, and that in the moſt pure
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:115061:50"/>
time of the Church, when the erroneous per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons could not receive thoſe errors by tradition and education from Chriſtian Anceſtors or Teachers:</p>
            <p>Then much more ought the Miniſters of the Goſpel, and with them all Gods people now (being themſelves fallible in judgement, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly diſagreeing among themſelves about the points in controverſie, (even the able and gracious of them) and eſpecially conſidering the time we live in, is but the dawning of the day of Goſpel light, and knowledge out of a long dark night of Antichriſtian error and pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, through which many of themſelves, not long ſince were groping in the dark about ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Goſpel truths, in which the light of Chriſt hath ſince more fully informed them) to walk towards one another with all tenderneſs and charity, putting in practice that rule of <hi>forbear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one another in love,</hi> Epheſ. 4.2. <hi>And thereby en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring to keep the unity of the Spirit, in the bond of Peace,</hi> verſe 3.</p>
            <p>But it is evident, the Apoſtle and holy Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of Scripture, did ſo walk in like caſes, when there was not the like Reaſon.</p>
            <p>Therefore Gods Miniſters and people ought ſo to walk now.</p>
            <p>Object. 2. <hi>Then you are for the permitting of all</hi> Errors <hi>in the Church; for if we muſt not ſeparate from</hi> Errors <hi>of this nature, what ſhall we</hi> ſeparate <hi>from?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:115061:51"/>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> To make a particular diſcrimination by name of all <hi>Errors,</hi> or to determine the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of any particular <hi>Errors</hi> that ſhall render the erroneous perſon incommunicable, is too hard a task for me to undertake; I ſhall onely propoſe ſome general Rules and Caſes which the Scriptures ſeems to countenance, and ſhall ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit them to the judgement of judicious Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That Churches and Beleevers ought to withdraw from, and deny Communion with all ſuch, who though they profeſs the true <hi>form</hi> of godlineſs, yet deny the <hi>power</hi> of it.</p>
            <p>Secondly, From ſuch, who though they make a profeſſion of the <hi>power</hi> as well as the <hi>form</hi> of Religion, by holding regeneration and viſible grace to be neceſſary qualifications for viſible members of Goſpel Churches; yet when they are ſo corrupt in judgement, that their Errors are firſt, contrary to <hi>godlineſs;</hi> or ſecondly, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtent with <hi>true Grace;</hi> or thirdly, deſtroy the <hi>foundation</hi> Doctrine of Salvation, they ought to be withdrawn from.</p>
            <p>For the firſt, By perſons denying the <hi>power of godlineſs;</hi> I mean ſuch, who though profeſſing of, and practiſing the true <hi>external Acts</hi> of Gods worſhip, as they may be generally pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, and practiſed by the generality of ſound Chriſtians; yet in their declared principles and converſation diſown the <hi>inward life</hi> and <hi>power
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:115061:51"/>
of it,</hi> expreſt by the viſible effects of true Grace, (as the work of regeneration, and being born again, <hi>Jo</hi> 3.3. with all other viſible ſignes of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance from dead Works, and Faith towards God, as <hi>Hebr.</hi> 6.1.) to be neceſſary qualificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for Goſpel-fellowſhip, which may be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcerned, either by their palpable <hi>ignorance,</hi> as <hi>Nicodemus, Joh.</hi> 3.4. or otherwiſe by their <hi>ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent</hi> enmity to, or <hi>ſcorn</hi> of gracious qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations in others, by deriding the godly, as holy brethren and ſiſters; or by the ſcorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſpirit in its gifts and graces in the Saints.</p>
            <p>Now ſuch, though they may profeſs the <hi>form,</hi> do viſibly deny the <hi>power</hi> of godlineſs, from whom we have an expreſs rule to withdraw, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.5. <hi>From ſuch turn away;</hi> and from ſuch doubtleſs the Apoſtle preſſeth the <hi>Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians</hi> to ſeparate themſelves, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.14, 15, 16, 17. <hi>Be ye not unequally <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>aked together with unbeleevers; for what fellowſhip hath righteouſneſs with unrighteouſneſs? and what commmunion hath light with darkneſs? And what concerd hath Chriſt with</hi> Belial? <hi>or what part hath he that beleeveth with an Infidel? And what agreement hath the Temple of God with Idols? for ye are the Temple of the living God, as God hath ſaid, I will dwell in them, and walk in them, and I will be their God, and they ſhall be my people. Wherefore come out from among them, and be ye ſeparate, ſaith
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:115061:52"/>
the Lord, and touch not the unclean thing, and I will receive you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Second ſort of perſons, that the Scripture is clear, the Churches and Servants of God are to ſeparate from, is from perſons holding opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, or living in Practiſes <hi>contrary to Godlineſs,</hi> I mean ſuch opinions as tends to a denying of God to be a <hi>patterne of Life,</hi> in his revealed com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municable qualities, manifeſted by his word, and by the Life of Chriſt, who was the expreſs Image of his Father, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.3. and the lives of his holy Prophets and Apoſtles, concerning which <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Timothy</hi> gives an expreſs com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, 1 <hi>Tim,</hi> 6.3. <hi>If any man teach otherwiſe, and conſent not to wholeſom words, even the words of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and to the doctrine which is according to Godlineſs</hi> &amp;c. from ſuch withdraw thy ſelf; and further in the firſt Chapter, and 1 verſe; <hi>But thou oh man of God, flie theſe things, and follow after Righteouſneſs, Godlineſs, &amp;c.</hi> Nay the ſame Apoſtle to <hi>Titus</hi> makes this the diſtinguiſhing Character of the true faith, <hi>Titus</hi> 1.1. <hi>Paul a Servant of God, according to the faith of Gods Elect, and the truth which is accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Godlineſs,</hi> So in <hi>Titus</hi> 2.11, 12, verſes, <hi>for the grace of God which bringeth ſalvation, hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared to all men, teaching us, that denying ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, and worldly luſts, we ſhould live ſoberly. righteouſly, and godly in this preſent World,</hi> and by well conſidering the ſcope of thoſe three ſhort
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:115061:52"/>
Epiſtles, you may plainly obſerve what the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles meaning was by doctrines according to Godlineſs in all perſons, of what State of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition ſoever, as in People towards Magiſtrates, 1 <hi>Tim,</hi> 2.1, 2, 3. <hi>Titus</hi> 3.1. In Miniſters in their places, Chap. 3. Chap. 4.6.12. <hi>verſ.</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.15.24. Chap. 4.2. <hi>Titus</hi> 1.6, 7, 8 9. in private Chriſtians towards their Miniſters, Chap. 5.1. 17, 18, 19. In Servants towards Maſters, Chap. 6.1, 2. <hi>Titus</hi> 2.9.10. In rich toward the poor, Chapter 6.17, 18, 19 <hi>verſes.</hi> In aged men, <hi>Titus</hi> 2, 2. In aged women, <hi>Titus</hi> 2, 3, 4. In young women, <hi>Titus</hi> 2.4, 5. In young men, <hi>verſ.</hi> 6.</p>
            <p>Teaching us by all thoſe Scriptures with all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of like tendency in the Word of God, that then are Opinions to be eſteemed <hi>contrary</hi> to the <hi>truth</hi> which is according to <hi>Godlineſs,</hi> when they tend to break the <hi>Bonds</hi> of <hi>natural</hi> and <hi>Civil</hi> relations, and to ſlight the duties of them, and fill the Heads and minds of Chriſtians with looſe Notions of carnall liberty, which the Apoſtle calls <hi>perverſe diſputings of men of Corrupt minds, deſtitute of the truth,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.5. <hi>and doating a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout queſtions and ſtrife of words whereof cometh envy, Strife, raylings, evill, ſurmizings verſ.</hi> 4. which he again preſſeth them to avoid, as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane, vaine bablings, <hi>verſ.</hi> 20th.</p>
            <p>Now from ſuch the Word of God is clear, though they walk with never ſuch a ſhew of <hi>holineſs</hi> and profeſſion of ſpiritualneſs, they
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:115061:53"/>
ought to be <hi>avoyed and withdraw</hi> from as <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly</hi> perſons</p>
            <p n="3">3. Third ſort of perſons I judge Churches and Saints ought to <hi>ſeparate</hi> and <hi>withdraw</hi> from, are perſons ſo corrupt in Judgement, and tainted with ſuch groſs impious Errours in opinions, as are evidently <hi>inconſiſtent with true grace;</hi> ſuch was <hi>Hymeneus, Alexander</hi> and <hi>Philetus</hi> menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.2. compared with 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.17. who had made Shipwrack of <hi>faith,</hi> and a good <hi>conſcience;</hi> ſuch doth the Apoſtle mean by an <hi>Heretick, Titus</hi> 3.10. Such opinions the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle cals the Error of the wicked, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.17. which implies more then a wicked Errour; which a holy Chriſtian through weakneſs or temptation, may be drawn into as <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> was, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.11, 12, 13, 14. <hi>verſ.</hi> ſuch are ſaid to <hi>erre from the Faith,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.10. which is more then to erre in the Faith; for thoſe Errours were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the graces of Righteouſneſs, Godlineſs, Faith, Love, Patience, Meekneſs &amp;c. which the Apoſtle in the next verſe exhorts <hi>Timothy</hi> to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low in his flight from the foreſaid Errours.</p>
            <p>Such are ſaid to <hi>erre</hi> from the <hi>truth, James</hi> 5. 19. <hi>viz.</hi> the Body and ſubſtance of ſaving truth; for he that converts ſuch a ſinner from the <hi>errour</hi> of his way, ſhall <hi>ſave a Soul</hi> from <hi>death,</hi> and ſhall hide a multitude of ſins, <hi>verſ.</hi> 20. which clearly implyes the erring from the truth in that peace is meant ſuch an erring as putts the Erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:115061:53"/>
perſon out of a ſaveable ſtate: they are ſaid to live in Error, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.18. which is more then to have Error live in them: In which Chapter he fully deſcribes what ſort of errone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous perſons he there means, from the tenth verſe to the end; <hi>John</hi> calls it the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Error,</hi> 1 <hi>John</hi> 4.6. by which he means more then an errring ſpirit. <hi>Jude</hi> calls ſuch <hi>ſenſual ſeparatiſts, Jude</hi> 19. ſuch as had no appearance of the grace of God in them, but were <hi>ungodly</hi> men, turning the grace of our God into <hi>laſciviouſneſs,</hi> and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying the onely Lord God, and our Lord Jeſus Chriſt: the whole Epiſtle is ſpent to deſcribe thoſe ſort of Separatiſts; now from ſuch ſort of Erroneous perſons as theſe are mentioned, and fully deſcribed, leaſt we ſhould miſtake, doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs the Church of God and Saints ought to <hi>ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate</hi> from, and <hi>reject.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. The fourth ſort of Erroneous perſons, which I judge holy Churches and Saints ought to ſeparate from, are ſuch as err in <hi>fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals,</hi> or foundation points of Religion, holding opinions, that lay the Ax to the Root of the Tree of Life.</p>
            <p>Now as theſe ſorts of <hi>Errors</hi> are moſt <hi>dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous</hi> to be permitted: ſo they are moſt <hi>difficult</hi> to ſingle out: for though it be a thing out of doubt, that there are foundation Doctrines, which the Church of God ought to prefer, in order to its <hi>Beeing,</hi> before its <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity;</hi>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:115061:54"/>
yet it remains very doubtfull, whether ſeveral of thoſe precious and ſubſtantial truths that are highly to be prized, and much contended for, and are by ſeveral godly and ſound Chriſtians eſteemed <hi>foundation</hi> points, be ſo or no: that is, ſo to be eſteemed <hi>foundations,</hi> as the perſons not beleeving them, or holding <hi>Error contrary</hi> to them, (and are otherwiſe in the main gratious) be thereby made incommunicable: But as in the former caſes, ſo in this, I ſhall decline coming to particulars, as a work above my capacity; and ſhal onely tender my thoughts in ſome few general Rules; and ſo leave it to them who are more able to add.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt, I judge that Errors againſt the <hi>foundation points</hi> of Religion, muſt be of ſuch a nature and tendency, as do ſtrike at the very root of <hi>Saving</hi>-Grace, and tend to <hi>unſtate</hi> the the perſon holding them from a poſſibility of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, he living and dying therein; for ſo <hi>Paul</hi> argues, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.14. concerning the reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the dead; <hi>If Chriſt be not riſen then is our preaching Vain, and our faith is alſo Vain.</hi> And alſo verſe 17.18. <hi>And if Chriſt be not raiſed, your Faith is Vain, ye are yet in your Sins. Then they alſo that are fallen aſleep in Chriſt, are periſhed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. I judge they muſt be Errors contrary to the general tendency and ſcope of Scripture, and to the <hi>Doctrines</hi> of <hi>Salvation, plainly</hi> and <hi>evidently</hi>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:115061:54"/>
therein expreſt, which all true Beleevers concur and agree in: And therefore ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>if our Goſpel be hid, it is hid to them that are loſt,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.3. and ſo chapter 11.3. <hi>But I fear leſt by any means, as the Serpent beguiled Eve through his ſubtilty, ſo your mindes ſhould be corrupted from the ſimplicity that is in Chriſt. For if he that cometh preacheth Another Jeſus, whom we have not preached, or if ye receive Another Spirit which ye have not received, or Another Goſpel which ye have not excepted,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ye might well bear with him.</hi> And ſo <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.6, 7, 8. <hi>I marvel that ye are ſo ſoon removed from him that hath called you into the grace of Chriſt, unto Another Goſpel: Which is not Another; but there be ſome which trouble you, and would pervert the Goſpel of Chriſt. But though we, or an Angel from Heaven preach another Goſpel unto you, then that which we have preached, let him be accurſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now it is evident that that bringing in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Goſpel was a joyning Circumciſion and the works of the Law with Faith in Chriſt in Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, contrary to the very Eſſence of Goſpel Faith, as they held it.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>Why, how did they hold it? did not you before number this among one of the Errors</hi> Paul <hi>permitted in the Church of</hi> Rome, &amp;c. <hi>and preſt the Church to union, without ſeparating from it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> They held it rigidly, impoſing it
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:115061:55"/>
upon others, as of neceſſity to Salvation, chap. 2.14. and 6.12. For where the ſame Error was held more moderately, as we obſerve before in the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Corinth, &amp;c.</hi> the Apoſtles deals milder with it; there he ſaith, <hi>Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion is nothing, nor uncircumciſion is nothing,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.19. <hi>Is any man called being circumciſed; let him not be uncircumciſed,</hi> verſe 8. But when they come to hold it <hi>impoſingly</hi> and <hi>poſitively,</hi> as in this verſe, he then changeth his voice: then <hi>O fooliſh</hi> Galatians, <hi>who hath bewitched you, that ye ſhould not obey the truth?</hi> &amp;c. Chap. 3.1, 2, 3, 4. then, <hi>Behold, I</hi> Paul <hi>ſay unto you, that if ye be cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed, Chriſt ſhall Profit you Nothing; For I teſtifie again to Every Man that is circumciſed, Chriſt is become of None Effect unto you,</hi> Chap. 5.2, 3, 4. So that the <hi>manner</hi> of holding an Error, alters the caſe of its <hi>fundamentalneſs</hi> much: It was <hi>Peters</hi> ſeparating from the Saints differing minded, and diſſimulation, rather then his Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, Chap. 2.11, 12, 13, 14. that made <hi>Paul</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand him to the face, verſe 11. But it is my opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, moſt other fundamental Errors are inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded under the three heads foregoing; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſhall not venture any further upon this difficult work of diſtinguiſhing fundamentals; but conclude my Anſwer to this Objection, with this one Argument.</p>
            <p>That if thoſe Errors and Hereſies the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture mentioneth, as dangerous and unſufferable
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:115061:55"/>
in the Church of God, which the Churches and Saints of God are onely exhorted to reject and withdraw from, was all either of a <hi>ſcandalous prophane</hi> nature, denying the power of godlineſs, on the one hand; or <hi>contrary to a godly life, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtent with true grace,</hi> or ſtriking at the <hi>foundation</hi> of <hi>Saving Faith</hi> on the other hand: Then the Churches and Saints of God, who deſire not to be wiſe above what is written at this day, ought onely to reject and withdraw from ſuch.</p>
            <p>But the Errors and Hereſies the Scripture men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions as dangerous and inſufferable in the Church of God, whom the Churches and Saints of God were exhorted to reject, and withdraw from, were only ſuch: <hi>Ergo,</hi> the Churches and Saints at this day ought only to reject, &amp; withdraw from ſuch.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>But there are ſeveral commands, or rules in Scripture to withdraw from, and note per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons for offences, that ſeem to be of a different na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture from theſe general Rules, propoſed by you, as for diſorderly walking,</hi> 2 Theſ. 3.6. Now we command you brethren in the name of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that ye withdraw your ſelves from every Brother that walketh diſorderly, <hi>&amp;c. and and ſo for diſobedience, verſe</hi> 14. If any man obey not the word, by this Epiſtle note that man, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I do admit all offences and diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, coming within the rules of Church <hi>cenſure,</hi> to be incommunicable after the Church <hi>cenſure</hi>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:115061:56"/>
is paſt, ſo far as ſuch cenſure extends to excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate; and conſequently, perſons living in ſuch diſorders, and not manifeſting repentance, and reſolution to reform, ought to be refuſed admiſſion into fellowſhip, if they ſhould tender themſelves, and none other: It being my opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, that whatſoever is ſufficient to unqualifie a perſon for a Church ſtate before admiſſion, would alſo be ſufficient to caſt him out, or with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw from him, if he were already in: But the caſes quoted, with all other of that nature, I judge, come clearly within the ſecond rule laid down, of opinions and practiſes contrary to the Doctrine which is according to <hi>godlineſs:</hi> For if you obſerve theſe two verſes, quoted with what the Apoſtle ſaith betwixt them, by way of explanation, we ſhall not need to ſearch further for his meaning, by theſe two rules, which are indeed but one, intending both the ſame perſons, and the ſame things; which was not Errors of judgment or opinion, but Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors of life and converſation; as ver. 11. <hi>For we hear that there are ſome which walk among you diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orderly, working not at all, but are buſie bodies; now ſuch we command, and exhort by the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that with quietneſs they work, and eat their own bread:</hi> By which we may diſcern, there were ſome members of this Church, that were idly diſpoſed, living in the neglect of their callings; and not onely ſo, but buſying them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:115061:56"/>
about matters they were not called unto; tending not onely to the burthen and charge of the Church, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.9. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.8. but to the diſturbance and diſquiet of it, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.11. And alſo to the ſcandal of the Goſpel to them that were without, verſe 12. which ſort of perſons are onely meant here by the Apoſtle; and of the like diſorder he further complains, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.13. <hi>And they withall learn to be idle, wandring about from houſe to houſe; and not onely idle, but tatlers alſo, and buſie-bodies, ſpeaking things which they ought not;</hi> and therefore this cannot concern any perſons who are of holy, blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs converſations, for their Error in judgement, not within the former rules propoſed.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>But is there not an Order, that God hath appointed his Churches to walk in, which ſuch as refuſe to obſerve, ought to be excluded and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawn from as Diſorderly perſons?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Yes, there is an <hi>Order</hi> God hath appointed, which ſuch as refuſe may be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawn from, as <hi>diſorderly</hi> perſons; yet all <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order</hi> doth not ariſe to that height of offence, as to be liable to that cenſure; and therefore we muſt conſider <hi>diſorderly</hi> walking amongſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, chiefly to conſiſt of offences againſt one of theſe two Rules.</p>
            <p>Firſt, either againſt the Rule of Goſpel con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, or,</p>
            <p>Secondly, Againſt the Rule of Goſpel viſible worſhip.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:115061:57"/>Againſt the firſt of theſe Rules did all thoſe offend, which we obſerve the Apoſtle to <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy writes</hi> againſt; and thoſe idle buſie-bodies, mentioned by <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> as in the former Objection; of ſuch <hi>Peter</hi> propheſied, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.2. <hi>By reaſon of whoſe pernitious wayes, the way of truth ſhall be evil ſpoken of;</hi> So <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Philippians,</hi> Chapter 3.18. <hi>For many walk, of whom I have told you often, and now tell you even weeping, that they are the enemies of the Croſs of Chriſt.</hi> Now theſe ſort of diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly perſons, I hope all that are gracious will agree to diſown.</p>
            <p>But the difficulty lieth in the ſecond head of <hi>diſorders</hi> againſt the rule of Gods viſible wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; the controverſie about which hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced more rents and diviſions among Gods people, then Doctrines of Faith, or inward qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lification of grace hath done; for ſuch as never were able to contend for the Faith once deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Saints, <hi>Jude</hi> verſe 3. nor to underſtand the myſtery hid from ages and generations, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.26. ſuch as never had acquaintance with the power of godlineſs in their own hearts, have been very able to plead for the form of it, from rational concluſions out of the Hiſtory of the Goſpel, with which they have filled their heads; and therefore it muſt be admitted, that not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly carnal Chriſtians, but even Jews, Turks, and Pagans, that are capable of reading the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:115061:57"/>
are capable of diſcovering, and obſerving the outward form of Gods worſhip; for what men are rationally capable to oppoſe, they are rationally capable to judge of and obſerve.</p>
            <p>But Atheiſts, Jews, and Turks, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onally capable to oppoſe: Therefore rationally capable to judge of, and obſerve the viſible writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten rule of Gods worſhip; and therefore though the viſible rule, and true form of Gods worſhip laid down in Scripture, ought to be highly valued by all ſincere Chriſtians, and by them all faithfully obſerved; yet when through the general Apoſtacy of Profeſſors of the true Religion, or the corrupt eſtate of the Church, the viſible form of Gods worſhip becomes cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted, and from thence controverſies ariſe, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Primitive patern, betwixt perſons equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly aiming at purity in it, there ought then to be much of tenderneſs, and caution in ſuch, about their ſtriving for the right form, leſt thereby they ſtifle and deſtroy the true power, which is the end and ſubſtance of the form, and ought to be proportionably preferred before it; and therefore we finde the Lord deſpiſing, and pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing contempt upon the true form, when it hath been ſo abuſed, as to ſet up it ſelf againſt or without the true power: <hi>To what purpoſe is the multitude of your ſacrifices unto me, ſaith the Lord; I am full of your burnt-offerings of Rams, and the fat of fed beaſts: I delight not in the
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:115061:58"/>
blood of Bullocks, nor of Lambs, or of he-goats: when you come to appear before me, who hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired this at your hands, to tread my Courts? Bring no more vain oblations; incenſe is abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion unto me; the new Moons and Sabbaths, and calling of Aſſemblies I cannot away with: It is iniquity, even the ſolemn meeting. Your new Moons, and appointed Feaſts my ſoul hateth; they are a trouble to me, I am weary to bear them;</hi> ſo <hi>Iſa:</hi> 29.13. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33.30. Yet all theſe particular performances were the required inſtituted Acts of Gods viſible worſhip, which he blames them for the neglect of, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 43, 21, 22, 23, 24. <hi>Mal.</hi> 1. 8. compared with the 13, 14. But when his people become carnal obſervers of his viſible worſhip, crying as thoſe carnal Jews did, the <hi>Temple of the Lord,</hi> the <hi>Temple of the Lord,</hi> Jer. 7.4. without manifeſting a due regard to the life and power of Religion, which all outward acts of worſhip are but the ſhadow and form of, <hi>Then behold, to obey is better then Sacrifice,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.12. <hi>He will have mercy then, and not Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, Hoſea</hi> 6.6. <hi>Mat.</hi> 9 13. <hi>Then to do Juſtice and Judgement, is more acceptable to the Lord, then Sacrifice, Pro.</hi> 21.32. as the Scribe replied to our Saviour, <hi>Mark</hi> 12.3. <hi>Well Maſter, thou haſt ſaid the truth; for there is one God, and none other but be, and to love him with al the heart, and with all the underſtanding, and with all the ſoul, and with all the ſtrength, and to love his neighbour as himſelf,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:115061:58"/>
is more then all whole burnt-offerings and ſacrifices:</hi> and when Jeſus ſaw <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat he anſwered diſcreet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, he ſaid unto him, Thou art not far from the Kingdom of God; in which reply, the Lord places a great deal of weight in perſons, eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>power</hi> of Religion much above the <hi>form</hi> of it; And from all theſe Scriptues I would in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, that in our ſtrivings about the true forms of worſhip, we ſhould have a tender regard to the preſerving, and propagating the true power be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it, if they come in competition, in regard the Lord hath ſo evidently in his word declared his well-pleaſedneſs in the power, when menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned diſtinct from the form; but never to the form, when mentioned diſtinct from the power.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>Do you think the power of Religion can conſiſt without the true form?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> If by true form is meant a ſincere deſire after the true form, and a conſciencious walking up thereto, ſo far as the ſoul is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced, or perſwaded of the truth thereof, I anſwer, no:</p>
            <p>For I do not judge the power of Religion can conſiſt in the wilfull and ſetled neglect of the leaſt of Gods Commandments, even in his viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble worſhip, when nothing comes in competition therewith of more immediate concernment to Gods Church and Glory.</p>
            <p>But if you mean by <hi>true form,</hi> the perfect un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erring
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:115061:59"/>
Obſervance of the outward Acts of Gods worſhip, without the miſtake of the Rule given in his word; Then I anſwer it may, in regard the moſt underſtanding and ſincere Chriſtian is fallible and ſubject to miſtake; for the proof of which, our own ſad experience ſpeaks loud; for I hope there is none ſo uncharitably rigid of any perſwaſion, retaining gracious qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, but wil admit, that amongſt ſuch as are god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly differing from them, there are ſome that are both able and ſincere, and that if they were convinced of their duty in the matter wherein they are judged to erre, would practice it, and in that caſe, I judge it is againſt all the rules of ſpiritual and natural Reaſon as wel as Scripture, to compel a conformity to a viſible Act of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, before the conſcience be convinced of its duty therein, or at leaſt unprincipled in Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Conſcience, againſt the Act required; which all that ſeparate from, or reject gracious perſons for not conforming to ſuch Acts of worſhip before conviction, do evidently do.</p>
            <p>For I judge, there can be no higher impulſion upon conſcience in a gracious perſon, their anon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtating of him from his viſible intereſt in, &amp; pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge with the viſible Church of Chriſt; which ſurely ſincere Chriſtians do value above their Liberty, or the greateſt outward good they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy; yet this they muſt loſe if they will not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme to Acts of worſhip againſt their judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:115061:59"/>
and Conſcience; and theſe violations of conſcience are oft practiſed by ſuch as moſt cries up Liberty of Conſcience; as if the impoſing of practiſes and principles upon gracious perſons, conſcientiouſly diſſenting from them, were no violation of Conſcience.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>But there are ſome differences of opinion betwixt ſuch as are Godly about the viſible worſhip of God, that are inconſiſtent to unity in Goſpel Order; for where ſome are poſſitively for, and others poſitively againſt the ſame thing, how can ſuch a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree together to walk in one fellowſhip.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Either thoſe poſitive contraries muſt be about things of that weight that one ſide muſt come within ſome of the Former Rules before minded, page 17. or otherwiſe of leſſe weight, for which there is no viſible rule in Scripture to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate and withdraw from: If the former, the ſound in Judgment hath there an evident rule to withdraw and ſeparate from; If the latter, then to walk tenderly and charitably towards each other; then the ſtrong ought to bear the infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the weak, &amp; not to pleaſe themſelves; then <hi>Pauls</hi> rule, <hi>Philip.</hi> 3.15, 16. comes in, <hi>Let us therefore as many as be perfect (or ſincere) be thus minded; and if in any thing ye be otherwiſe minded, God ſhall reveal even this unto you Nevertheleſſe, whereto we have already attainted, let us walk by the ſame rule; let us mind the ſame thing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Object. <hi>But you would do well to be more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:115061:60"/>
as to thoſe controverſies amongst the Godly, about the power of the Keyes, the extent of Chriſts death, Baptiſme, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Though I do judge as thoſe and the moſt of ſuch like controverſies are held by the generality of the Godly of each perſwaſion; the erring party whereſoever it is, is not incommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable; nor the differences about them of that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent as to be inconſiſtent to an Orderly and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable walking together in the fellowſhip of the Goſpel, and therein each enjoying both the purity and liberty of his conſcience, they walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing tenderly, and humbly towards each other therein; yet I ſhall decline a particular ſpeaking my thoughts at preſent, having reaſon to be ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of my own inſufficiency and diſability for that work, and being in hope the Lord may draw out the heart of ſome more able to engage in this controverſy againſt controverſyes, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by I ſhall avoid that diſadvantage to the truth pleaded for my weak handling of it may admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, and content my ſelf with ſome few more general Objections, and ſo conclude with ſome directions to ſuch whoſe hearts are groaning under the Diviſions of Saints.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>Though this comfortable State of the Churches unity in Goſpel-worſhip be a deſirable thing, yet it it not poſſible to be attained untill the glorious eſtate of the Church, the time of fulfiling thoſe promiſes of unity, quoted by you.</hi> pag. 56.57.
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:115061:60"/>
               <hi>and therefore to labour to attanie to impoſſibilities in an uncomfortable work.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The ſame objection might have been made in the Apoſtles time, and in the primitive State of the Church; and yet you find they preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and laboured after the Churches <hi>unitie,</hi> and ſo far prevailed as we never heard of more uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Churches Chriſt had on earth but one, though in that Church ſeveral different opinions about ſeveral weighty points, yet they preſerved an <hi>union</hi> in <hi>Church-state,</hi> and did not unchurch nor unſaint one another untill theſe latter days, wherein the Spirit of diviſion hath been in its raigne and ſtrength.</p>
            <p>And there is as much reaſon to object againſt all our endeavours after all other graces and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual attainments, becauſe the perfection and fulneſs of them is reſerved for that glorious day; for until then our <hi>knowledge</hi> will be but darkly as through a glaſſe, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.9.12. but then we ſhall <hi>know</hi> as we are <hi>known,</hi> we ſhall then <hi>ſee face</hi> to <hi>face</hi> verſ. 12. then ſhall knowledge cover the earth as waters do the Sea, <hi>Eſay</hi> 11.19. we ſhall all then <hi>know</hi> the Lord from the leaſt to the greateſt <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.34.</p>
            <p>And ſo <hi>holineſs</hi> and purity is now very imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect: <hi>We are now all the Sons of God, but it doth not yet appear what we ſhall be; but when he ſhall appear we ſhall be like him,</hi> 1 John 3.2. the way; of the Lord ſhal then be called <hi>the way of holineſs
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:115061:61"/>
the unclean ſhall not paſs over it, Iſa.</hi> 35.8. <hi>In that day there ſhall be upon the bells of the Horſes holineſs to the Lord, Zach.</hi> 14.20. <hi>then ſhall</hi> Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem <hi>be holy, there ſhall no ſtranger paſs through her any more, Joel</hi> 3.17. Yet I hope none will object from theſe Scriptures; knowledge and holineſs is reſerved for the glorious ſtate of the Church; and therefore, why do ye preſs to an encreaſe of it, until the fulfilling of thoſe glorious promiſes.</p>
            <p>Therefore though the perfection of the Saints union be reſerved for the laſt and glorious times of the Church, yet the labouring after the meaſure of the preſent day, is to not be omitted, but rather to be laboured for, as a mercy that muſt forerun many other precious mercies the Saints ſeem at this day to be in expectation of; that I may ſay in this caſe, as was ſaid of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.58. <hi>Mar.</hi> 6.5. he could not do ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny mighty works among them, becauſe of their unbelief; ſo the Lord cannot do many works amongſt us, becauſe of our diviſions; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we ſhould eſteem the unity of the Saints a mercy, that would make way for abundance of other mercies: for thoſe glorious promiſes, relating to the glorious eſtate of Chriſts Church, in the latter dayes, are to be fulfilled to <hi>all</hi> the Saints, whether of <hi>Paul, Apollo</hi> or <hi>Cephas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſtirs up <hi>all</hi> Gods people to gladneſs and rejoycing at that day, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66.
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:115061:61"/>
10. <hi>Rejoyce ye with</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>and be glad with her, All ye that love her: rejoyce with joy with her, all ye that mourn for her: That ye may ſuck, and be ſatisfied with the breſts of her conſolation; that ye may milk out, and be delighted with the abundance of her glory:</hi> And ſo <hi>Iſa.</hi> 4.5. <hi>The Lord ſhal create upon every dwelling place of mount</hi> Sion, <hi>and upon her aſſemblies, a cloud, and ſmoke by day, and the burning of a flaming fire by night; for upon all the glory ſhall be a defence.</hi> So <hi>Zach.</hi> 14.5. <hi>And the Lord my God ſhall come, and All the Saints with thee.</hi> And ſo the generality of thoſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious promiſes, relating to the laſt and glorious ſtate of the Church, doth hold forth an <hi>uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſality</hi> of <hi>peace, purity,</hi> and <hi>glory,</hi> to the <hi>whole Church,</hi> to <hi>all Saints,</hi> which the divided State of the Church is uncapable of receiving; and therefore ſuch whoſe ſouls long for the day of the Churches glory, ſhould take heed that therein they do not hurry the Saints beſides, or beyond the means of its preſent Unity: for the obſtructing the latter, is an eminent means to hinder the former, and ſuch as will defer the work of the Saints Unity, preſt for, untill that glorious day, ſhall never have an oppotuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of caſting their Mite into that Treaſury; for the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> of that day ſhall ſtand in no need of their help; <hi>The Lord alone ſhall be exhalted, as the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niter of his Church, in that day; there ſhall then be no night there; and they need no can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:115061:62"/>
neither light of the Sun, for the Lord God ſhall give them light, Reu.</hi> 22.5. It would be taken for a very ſtrange anſwer from a Phyſitian to a ſick perſon that deſired his help, that when he was well he would come &amp; cure him; ſince the whole needs no Phyſitian, but thoſe that are ſick; which Anſwer agrees much with this Objection.</p>
            <p>Which I have been the larger in anſwering, in regard I have often met with it, from the moſt moderate againſt this Goſpel union; who though they have ſeemed to be convinced of the duty, yet would quiet their conſciences in the neglect of their uttermoſt endeavour to obtain it, from the conſideration that it was not to be expected until the laſt and glorious times: That until there was an unity of knowledge and judgement, there could be no unity in Church-fellowſhip, alledging that Scripture; <hi>How can two walk together unleſs they be agreed?</hi> which Scripture, &amp; others of like tendency are evident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly miſtaken, when applied in this caſe; for ſuch an agreement, as to have no difference of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding among Saints, and that in conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable weighty points, was never yet on earth; yet Gods Church hath preſerved its unity.</p>
            <p>And therefore it is to be conſidered, that the union we are capable of attaining unto, and ought to preſs after in this day of our imperfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, is not to proceed from the <hi>perfection of our un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding</hi> in the ſame things; but from the <hi>exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:115061:62"/>
of grace one towards another;</hi> whiles thus dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering; to which purpoſe the Lord hath ſupplyed his people, with ſeveral <hi>ſpecial graces,</hi> which are chiefly applicable in this <hi>ſpecial duty;</hi> and there fore ye may obſerve, that generally exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to <hi>union,</hi> as the <hi>end,</hi> do provoke to the exerciſe of <hi>ſuch graces</hi> as are proper thereunto as the <hi>means;</hi> as for inſtance, <hi>Epheſ</hi> 4.1, 2, 3. <hi>That ye walk worthy of the vocation whereunto ye called, are with all lowlineſs, and meekneſs, with long ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, forbearing one another in love,</hi> verſe 2. <hi>And further let all bitterneſs, wrath, and anger, and cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour; and evil ſpeaking be put away from you, with all malice, and be ye kinde one to another, tender-hearted, forgiving one another, even as God for Chriſt ſake forgave you,</hi> verſe 31.32. <hi>here was the means then,</hi> verſe 3. <hi>endeavouring to keep the unity of the ſpirit in the bond of peace,</hi> here is the <hi>end:</hi> ſo the ſame Apoſtle to the <hi>Philippians,</hi> Chapter 2.2. <hi>that ye be like-minded, having the ſame Love, being of one accord, of one minde:</hi> here he expreſſeth the <hi>end,</hi> then, verſe 3. <hi>Let nothing be done through ſtrife, or vain janglings; but in lowlineſs of minde, let each eſteem other better then themſelves:</hi> ſo verſe 4. <hi>Look not every man on his own things, but every man alſo on the things of others:</hi> thus he directs the <hi>means;</hi> ſo that the <hi>great mercy</hi> of <hi>Goſpel union,</hi> is not to be expected, but in the exerciſe of the <hi>great means</hi> of <hi>ſuitable Goſpel Grace;</hi> and why Beleevers
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:115061:63"/>
ſhould be more diſcouraged in endeavouring the Churches <hi>unity,</hi> then its <hi>purity,</hi> I know no ground; for there is no difficulty, attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the one, but what attends the other; even the corruption of our hearts and principles, which <hi>Paul</hi> affirmed to be the cauſe of the diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.3.</p>
            <p>And therefore they that begin in the work of Saints, union to diſpute and reaſon them into the ſame underſtanding and practice, begin at the <hi>wrong end.</hi> The firſt ſtep to unity is <hi>humility,</hi> and therein the exerciſe of the graces of pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, meekneſs, charity, long-ſuffering, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearing one another in love, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The principal and main uſe of thoſe graces in their exerciſe would be little needed, if all the Saints had once attained to the ſame underſtanding in all things;</p>
            <p>And therefore if through the rigid froward contentious diſpoſition of ſome Chriſtians, unity of Church-ſtate in ſome places could not be obtained; but Chriſtians ſhould continue to walk in ſeveral diſtinct ſocieties, according to their ſeveral perſwaſions; yet therein they might, be through the exerciſe of the foregoing uniting graces, and <hi>unity</hi> of <hi>brotherhood,</hi> by gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the right hand of fellowſhip to each other, as Goſpel Churches, and exerciſing all Brother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and Chriſtian affection towards each other, and in extraordinary caſes, where the joynt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, or the aſſiſtance of the Elderſhip or Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:115061:63"/>
of the ſeveral ſocieties, may be required in things wherein they are all agreed, they might make uſe of, and ſubmit unto the help of each other therein, which would prepare the way for a more perfect union:</p>
            <p>For as nothing more tends to divide, then a frequent controverting of the caſes in contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie amongſt Saints; ſo nothing would tend more to unite, then a frequent partaking of each others gifts and graces, in thoſe things wherein they agree; for in the one, they onely come to diſcern the unſoundneſs of judgement, and weakneſſes of each other, by paſſionate un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing expreſſions, which the beſt of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans are ſubject unto in diſputes; whereas in the other they would come to obſerve the ſoundneſs of judgement, and ſtrength of grace in each other, which would exceedingly tend to endear and unite: for if godly perſons were better known to one another in their ſpiritual excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies and graces, and leſs in their defects and weakneſſes, their union would not be ſo difficult a thing, as at preſent it ſeems to be; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore what the Church ſaith, <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.5. concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning her afflictions, might be repeated by diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent-minded ſocieties of Chriſtians one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to the weakneſſes of their judgement, or ſuppoſed Errors on each hand; <hi>Look not upon me, becauſe I am black;</hi> for as a good man obſerved in a diſcourſe upon <hi>Hebr.</hi> 12.1. Chriſtians are the
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:115061:64"/>
exceeding apt to be poring upon the dark ſide of the cloud; prying into each others infirmities and weakneſſes; judging of one another accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the ſight of the eye, and the hearing of the ear, which he that ſhall judge righteous Judgement will not do, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 11.3. for it is the natural diſpoſition of the Churches enemies, to be ſo exerciſed; they ſay, <hi>Let her be defiled, and let our eye look upon</hi> Sion, <hi>Mich.</hi> 4.11. which ſin in Saints is neer kin to the ſin of <hi>Ham; Gen.</hi> 9.22. whoſe ſin did not lie in the ſeeing of his fathers nakedneſs, but in not covering it, and his publiſhing it to his brethren without; and therfore to expect union of Saints whiles we live in the exerciſe of all dividing practiſes, is to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect it by way of miracle; but to expect it as before in the exerciſe of uniting graces, is to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect it in a way of means, unto which the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of bleſſing is onely annexed.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>But although the union of Saints as before be a mercy of that worth, and a duty of that waight you preſs it, yet the preſent ſad divided State of Gods People in theſe Nations ſeemes to render it ſo difficult, that endeavours to unite may tend further to divide; there is ſuch a ſpirit of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice in Chriſtians againſt the opinions and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples they are contrary unto, that not only the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions of each other, but the very perſons holding them are ofttimes unacceptable, and burthenſome to each other for their opinions ſake.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:115061:64"/>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I would I could ſay there is no ground for this Objection, but doubtleſſe there is: The work is like to be attended with much difficulty and oppoſition, both from good and bad men, but eſpecially where this ſpirit of Diviſion is predominant, it will exceedingly rage, it will there like thoſe unclean ſpirits our Saviour caſt out, <hi>Mark</hi> 1.26. Chap. 5.2, 3, 4. teare thoſe it poſſeſſeth, and cry with a loud voice before it come forth; but be not diſcouraged; the ſpirit of power and love, and of a ſound mind, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.7. ſhall prevaile againſt this carnal ſpirit of contention, ſtrife and vain iangling, which thus begets and increaſeth Diviſions amongſt Gods People; but the better to enable thee to employ thy talent and opportunities in this good work, conſider the following directions.</p>
            <p>In general to all perſons of what degree or condition ſoever, labour to inform thy ſelf not only that the unitie of Gods Church is a mercy, and the endeavouring of it is a duty, but that it is a duty and mercy to be prefered before many others, nay moſt others when they come in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petition therewith; for the conſideration of the worth of a mercy, and the weight of a duty doth much enlarge the heart towards it, and carryes the heart in earneſt prayer for it, which is the firſt and chief duty I ſhall preſs thee unto, to pray for the peace of <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Being ſatisfied of the worth and weight of it,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:115061:65"/>
and therby ſeeking frequently the Lord with fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent prayer for it, labour to arm thy ſelf againſt all <hi>diſcouragements</hi> and difficulties that may ſeem to lie in the way of it, that though its likely thou mayeſt come to bear the reproach of a luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warm <hi>Laodicean,</hi> a perſon of no ſetledneſs in judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that is filled with notions of unpractiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able things, and much worſe then this; yet heed it not, but know, this ſpirit of diviſion is beſt diſcerned by its uncharitable cenſoriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and that's the air it breaths in; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you may obſerve, with what people ſoever this ſpirit is predominate, they eſteem not of any that own the ſame points with them, wherin they differ from others, unleſs they be ſticklers for them, they dare not lay more weight, or place more religion in a controverted truth, then their conſcience tells them the Scripture doth; they do little leſs then deny it in ſome mens opinions.</p>
            <p n="3">3. As thou muſt expect oppoſition and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragements; and oughteſt to be armed againſt them; ſo take heed thou doſt not imploy any of the <hi>carnal weapons</hi> of the ſpirit of diviſion in the ſpirit of unions cauſe: ſome men will oppoſe the ſpirit of diviſion by a <hi>dividing ſpirit,</hi> that is exerciſing the ſame carnal contention, and proud wrath with uncharitable cenſoriouſneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> againſt diviſions, as dividing ſpirits pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote them by; now this comes under <hi>Jobs</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proof, Chapter 13.7. <hi>Will ye ſpeak wickedly for
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:115061:65"/>
God, and talk deceitfully for him?</hi> if we had no better Phyſicians then theſe, we might tell the Church with <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> Chap. 30.13. <hi>thy bruiſe is incurable, and thy wound is grievous; thou haſt none to plead thy cauſe, that thou mayeſt be bound up; thou haſt no healing medicines;</hi> And therefore <hi>Paul</hi> being ſenſible how apt the beſt Church-healers are to apply the wrong plaiſter he gives to <hi>Timothy</hi> a ſpecial direction, 2 <hi>Tim</hi> 2.24. <hi>The ſervant of the Lord muſt not Strive, but be Gentle unto all men, apt to teach, patient; in meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs inſtructing thoſe thoſe that oppoſe themſelves, if God peradventure will give them Repentance, to the acknowledging of the truth;</hi> I muſt ſay the contrary ſpirit in healers hath added much infla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, and thereby corruption to our wound.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Labor to obtain a <hi>compaſſionate tender</hi> frame of ſpirrit, even towards thoſe whom thou art leaſt in love with, upon the account of their Errors in judgement. If Chriſtians would mourn and ſigh more in the ſenſe of Saints diviſions and deluſions, and fret and rage leſs, our heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing would not ſeem to be ſo far of, as it doth.</p>
            <p>There is a kinde of religious hard-heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs, and cruelty overſpread the hearts of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Chriſtians in theſe dayes; that we have cauſe to complain with the Church, <hi>Lam.</hi> 4.5. <hi>Even the Sea monſters draw out the breſt, they give ſuck to their young ones, the daughter of my people is become cruel, like the Oſtriges in the wilderneſs:</hi>
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:115061:66"/>
Chriſtians can as eaſily, and with as little re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luctancy hear or ſpeak evil of others that are gracious, if they be but judged erroneous by them, as carnal malicious perſons can do of one another; nay, ſome be ready and zealous to ſtir up the rude carnal multitude againſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; and even take contentment in each others afflections: Oh! where is the bowels of good <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> that lived in a day when he could ſay of his people, <hi>They be all Adulterers, an Aſſembly of treacherous men, they bend their tongue like a bowe for lies,</hi> Chap. 9.2, 3. and yet he cries out! <hi>Oh that my head were waters, and mine eyes a fountain of tears, that I might weep day and night for the ſlain of the daughter of my people:</hi> and ſo <hi>Iſaiah</hi> he mentions the Sins of Gods people to be very great, Chapter 22.8, 9, 10, 13. And yet when he conſiders their ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, verſe 4. he cries out, <hi>Look away from me, I will weep bitterly; labour not to comfort me, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the ſpoiling of the daughter of my people:</hi> But the like bowels and compaſſion in Gods people towards one another is not found, which until the Lord afford thee, thou wilt be very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit for healing work.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Labour to ſet thy affections on thoſe things or qualifications in Saints, which moſt lively and evidently demonſtrate the <hi>powerfull work of Grace</hi> in them, and the ſincerity of their <hi>Love</hi> to Chriſt: many Chriſtians will more eſteem of
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:115061:66"/>
their own image in their brethren then Chriſts; their cloſing with them in judgement, in ſome particular controverted opinion, will anſwer the defect of a great deal of more precious grace, when much grace in another will not anſwer the defect of their differing in that opinion; it is an eaſie matter to love them that love us; the worſt of men can do that, <hi>Luke</hi> 6.32. but <hi>Paul</hi> ſets us a pattern of another manner of Love, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.15. <hi>And I will very gladly ſpend, and be ſpent for you, though the more abundantly I love you, the leſs I am beloved;</hi> it was this love in <hi>Paul</hi> that enabled him to bear all thoſe hard meaſures from the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> &amp; to labor for their union and peace, whileſt they made war againſt him.</p>
            <p>Now without this Love, that will cover a multitude of infirmities, thou wilt never be able to receive this truth in the love of it, nor to bear with patience all thoſe diſcouragements thou wilt meet withall in this work.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Labour to abound in all other uniting graces, which the Apoſtle mentions, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.12. he having ſpoken of the union of Saints, verſe 11. he then comes to commend as a means to fit them for it, verſe 12. <hi>Put on therefore (as the Elect of God, holy and beloved) bowels of mercy, kindneſs, humbleneſs of minde, meekneſs, long-ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering, forbearing one another, forgiving one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, if any man hath a quarrel</hi> (or complaint) <hi>againſt any; even as Chriſt forgave you, ſo alſo
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:115061:67"/>
do ye; and above all things, put on Charity, which is the bond of perfectneſs; and let the peace of God rule in your hearts, unto which alſo ye are called in one body, and be ye thankfull; let the word of Chriſt dwell in you richly, in all wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</hi> &amp;c. It is the want of putting on and exerciſing of theſe graces that hinders Saints from Goſpel union, more then all their dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent underſtanding doth; for if all men were of one minde, in the things wherein they differ, the want of theſe uniting graces, and living in the exerciſe of the contrary dividing vices would doubtleſs diſunite, and divide the people of God from one another; for I am afraid there is little of that union among Saints at this day, even among thoſe of the ſame judgement, that) deſerves the name of <hi>Goſpel union,</hi> either from the <hi>nature, grounds</hi> or <hi>degree</hi> of it; but gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally a kinde of an outſide heartleſs formal uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that the very union of carnal people in carnal things, ſeems to be more ſtrongly found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, which proceeds clearly from the want of the enjoying, and exerciſing thoſe precious graces; for Chriſtians united upon the Account of opinions are onely united in the <hi>head;</hi> but Goſpel-union, upon the account of viſible grace, would be an uniting of <hi>hearts</hi> together; ſuch was the union the Saints enjoyed, <hi>Acts</hi> 4.32. <hi>And the multitude of them that beleeved were of one heart, ane of one ſoul.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:115061:67"/>7. Labour to preſerve a proportionable growth of grace in the ſoul; all grace in the exerciſe of it muſt preſerve an <hi>harmony;</hi> other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe it will ſound like an Inſtrument out of tune: ſome Chriſtians ſeem to be all <hi>affection,</hi> and no <hi>judgement;</hi> others all <hi>judgement,</hi> and no <hi>affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction:</hi> ſome have <hi>zeal,</hi> but want <hi>knowledge;</hi> others have <hi>knowledge,</hi> but want <hi>zeal;</hi> whereas light and heat goes together, if grace be of a true growth. Now this time of unevenneſs in thy graces will much diſinable thee for uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting work; for herein thou wilt be like the fool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh Phyſitian who hath but one ſort of medicines for all diſeaſes and conſtitutions, whereas that which cures ſome kills others: and therefore <hi>Job</hi>'s friends, though good men, applying the wrong plaiſter to his ſore, he eſteems them to be Phyſitians of no value, <hi>Job</hi> 13.4. <hi>How forcible are right words?</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>but what doth your Arguments reprove?</hi> that is, words <hi>rightly</hi> applied ſutable to the condition of the perſon or people unto whom they are ſpoke, and <hi>ſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable</hi> to the time, and place, occaſion; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſaith <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> Chap. 50.4. <hi>The Lord God hath given me the tongue of the learned, that I ſhould know how to ſpeak a word in ſeaſon,</hi> &amp;c. ſo the wiſe man, <hi>Prov.</hi> 25.11. <hi>A word fitly ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, is like apples of gold in pictures of ſilver, and as an earing of gold, an ornament of fine gold, ſo is a wiſe reprover upon an obedient ear.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:115061:68"/>Now until thou haſt a ſpiritual judgment, as well as ſpiritual affections, thou wilt not be ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of Underſtanding the ſeaſon of a duty, nor the right way of performing, and applying it.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Be moſt conſciencious, and diligent in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming that duty, in order to this good work, that is moſt <hi>properly</hi> thy own, unto which thou art moſt clearly call'd by that place, or condition Providence hath ſet thee in, either in Church or Commonwealth, and thy abilities and gifts in ſuch thy place do moſt fit thee for; the want of a due regard thereto amongſt Chriſtians, hath greatly encreaſed and promoted their Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions; for order of Place is neceſſary to union and harmony in all things, whether natural, Civil, or Spiritual; for what a confuſion in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture would it be, for the hands to be performing the work of the <hi>feet,</hi> or the <hi>feet</hi> the <hi>hands,</hi> or the <hi>eye</hi> to uſurp the office of the <hi>ear,</hi> or the <hi>ear</hi> of the <hi>eye?</hi> which Metaphor the Apoſtle makes uſe of in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. to teach the divided Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians, that order of Place was neceſſary to uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Saints, which he proves, firſt in regard all had not the ſame gifts; verſes 8, 9, 10, 11. 2 in regard all had not the ſame Place, or office verſe 28, 29. <hi>God hath ſet ſome in the Church, firſt Apoſtles, ſecondly Prophets, thirdly Teachers, after that miracles, then gifts of healing, helps of governments, diverſities of tongues; are all Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:115061:68"/>
are all Prophets, are all Teachers, are all workers of miracles? &amp;c.</hi> wherein he doth not only preſerve <hi>diſtinction,</hi> but alſo <hi>degree</hi> of place, which he doth not ſay <hi>himſelf</hi> ſet in the Church, though that might have been of ſufficient Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, but God hath ſet them in his Church, leaſt the Ringleaders of Diviſion in that Church, ſhould have broken the Order under pretence of the inſufficiency of the Authority it were ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by; and ſo the ſame Apoſtle obſerving the inclination of the ſame People to be expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing changes in their outward condition, after they profeſt the Chriſtian Religion, anſwers ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral particular Caſes, 1 Epiſtle Chap 7. And leaſt any others from the like temptation or miſtake, ſhould not think themſelves concerned in thoſe Anſwers, he layes down ſome general Rules or precepts to anſwer all Objections a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this truth, as verſe 20. <hi>Let every man a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide in the ſame calling, wherein he was called; and ſo verſe</hi> 24. <hi>Brethren let every man wherein he is called, therein abide with God:</hi> therefore of all duties labour to be performing thoſe dutyes, thy preſent place and calling requires at thy hands, in Order to the union of Saints; and when the Lord of the harveſt finds thee like a good and faithful Servant, faithfully improving thy few Talents, he will truſt thee with many Talents, <hi>Matt.</hi> 25.23. And therefore I ſhall ſpeak a word to the Miniſters of the Goſpel (by
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:115061:69"/>
whom I intend not thoſe carnal ſcandalous dumb dogs, who ſeldom open their mouths, unleſs it be to bark at the precious flock of Chriſt, for to expect better from them would be to expect grapes of Thorns, and figs of thiſtles, but I mean ſuch as are gracious holy men, ſolemnly ſet apart to ſerve the Lord in that work of what judgment or perſwaſion ſoever, as to the preſent contoverſies among the Godly;) who are not only to be fellow-Labourers, but Maſter-builders in this work of Saints union; And it is my opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on they have had the firſt, and chiefeſt hand in Saints Diviſions; ſo it is my earneſt prayers they might be owned and fitted by the Lord in the firſt and chief place in this work of Saints uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: Now that which I ſhall propoſe to them is;</p>
            <p>Firſt that you Labour to be ſenſible of the ſad effects of thoſe ſad Diviſions that have been amongſt your ſelves, and from thence thoſe unbrotherly, untender, and uncharitable car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages in your publick writings and ſpeakings one towards another; that I am aſſured many private Chriſtians of the ſame perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons with you have been grieved, and aſhamed to read and hear, though the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerality of Chriſtians are too apt to be pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed moſt with ſuch of their teachers as are moſt vehement againſt thoſe contrary minded to them; and from thence hath that general overflow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſpirit of diviſion and diſſentions which we
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:115061:69"/>
now complain of, received its life and nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: That the Lord hath cauſe to complain, as in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 4.12. <hi>O my people, they which lead thee cauſed thee to erre, and deſtroy the way of thy paths;</hi> if the leaders of the people go before them in a froward contentious uncharitable ſpirit towards one another in matters wherein they differ; no marvel if the generality of their followers tread on each others heels in that crooked path.</p>
            <p>Therefore if no other Argument be prevail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, let the conſideration of the ſad divided condition of Gods Church and people, produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by your example affect your hearts, that you cannot with that comfort and authority re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peat that exhortation to the Saints under your charge, that <hi>Paul</hi> gave to the Church of <hi>Philip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pi,</hi> Chap. 3, having in the 15, and 16. verſes ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted them to <hi>union,</hi> and directed them how to preſerve it, he exhorts in verſe 17, <hi>Brethren be ye followers together of me, and mark them which walk, ſo as ye have us for an enſample;</hi> ſo he exhorts <hi>Timothy,</hi> Chap. 4. after he had ſpent the former part of the Chapter in Inſtructions to him con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Errors and Diviſions that were in his Flock, he then exhorts him, verſe 12. <hi>But be thou an example of the Beleevers, in word, in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, in charity, in ſpirit, in faith, in purity;</hi> and ſo <hi>Peter</hi> in his firſt Epiſtle, Chap. 5.3. he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horts <hi>the elders that were among them, not to be as lords over Gods heritage, but to be examples to the
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:115061:70"/>
Flock:</hi> I am far from ſaying, that none of Gods Miniſters at this day have been examples to their Flocks in this great duty of a holy tender ſpirit, and humble brotherly carriage towards others differing from them; for I know my ſelf many that have ſo walked; but I fear, if there was a due ſearch, the moſt have not ſo done, but there have been more hands dividing and rend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, then have been binding up and healing, or elſe the diſeaſe would not have grown ſo Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demical, as it is this day, that the Lord hath juſt cauſe to take up the complaint againſt them he did againſt his Shepherds of old, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 34.4, 5.6. <hi>The diſeaſed have ye not ſtrengthened, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther have ye healed that which was ſick, neither have ye bound up that which was broken, neither have ye brought again that which was driven a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, neither have ye ſought that which was loſt; but with Force and with cruelty have ye ruled them: And they were ſcattered, becauſe there is no Shepherd; and they became meat to all the beaſts of the field, when they were ſcattered; my ſheep wandered through all the mountains, and upon every high hill; yea, my Flock was ſcattered upon all the face of the earth, and none did ſeek or ſearch after them:</hi> And therefore until the Lord ſet this great evil upon your hearts, that you have troden under your feet, and ſcattered abroad ſo much of Gods precious wheat, by your inordinate and unſeaſonable ſtriving to
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:115061:70"/>
be plucking up the tares, there is little hopes of your ſetting your ſelves to this work of labour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for the unity of Gods Church, with ſuch deſire and endeavour to accompliſh it, as may promiſe much ſucceſs.</p>
            <p n="2">2. You having once the ſad divided conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the people of God ſet upon you hearts, with a due ſenſe of what furtherance you have given thereto, as aforeſaid; then begin to ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy all holy wayes of furthering the work of union; then imitate the chief and good Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 34.11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16. <hi>For thus ſaith the Lord God, behold I, even I will both ſearch my ſheep, and ſeek them out. As a ſhepherd ſeeketh out his flock in the day that he is among his ſheep that are ſcattered: ſo will I ſeek out my ſheep, and will deliver them out of all places, where they have been ſcattered in the cloudy and dark day. And I will bring them out from the people, and ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther them from the countries, and will bring them to their own land, and feed them upon the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains of</hi> Iſrael <hi>by the rivers, and in all the inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited places of the country, I will feed them in a good paſture, and upon the high mountains of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael there ſhall their fold be; there ſhall they lie in a good fold, and in a fat paſture ſhall they feed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the mountains of</hi> Iſrael. <hi>I will feed my flock, and cauſe them to lie down, ſaith the Lord God. I will ſeek that which was loſt, and bring again that which was driven away, and I will binde up
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:115061:71"/>
that which was broken, and will ſtrengthen that which was ſick: but I will deſtroy the fat and the ſtrong, I will feed them with judgement.</hi> For un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til then you will not be able to bear the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction and oppoſition you muſt expect to meet withall in this work, not onely from bad, but from good men; till then the meekeſt <hi>Moſes</hi> will be in danger to lift up himſelf over his poor deluded murmuring brethren, <hi>Numb.</hi> 20.10. and ſmite the rock oftner then he ought to do in his anger, verſe 11. but if once the Lord bring your hearts under an holy ſenſe of equal guilt, there will then be a ſpirit of ſympathy with your poor weak brethren: then you will know how <hi>to feed your flocks like a ſhepherd, and to gather the lambs with your arms, and carry them in your boſom, and gently to lead thoſe that are with young.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. I would propoſe to you, to change your ſharp ſevere <hi>cenſurings and blamings,</hi> into affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionate <hi>beſeechings and intreatings;</hi> that was <hi>Paul</hi>'s way, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.1. <hi>If there be therefore any conſolation in Chriſt, if any comfort of love, if any fellowſhip of the Spirit, if any bowels of mercies; fulfill ye my joy, that ye be like minded, having the ſame love, being of one accord, of one minde.</hi> And ſo <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.1. <hi>I therefore the priſoner of the Lord, beſeech you, that ye walk worthy of the vocation whereto ye are called, with all lowlineſs and meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, with all long-ſuffering, forbearing one another in love: endeavouring to keep the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:115061:71"/>
of the Spirit in the bond of peace,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="4">4. In all your preachings or writings againſt Errors and Diviſions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> labour to diſtinguiſh betwixt the <hi>chaff</hi> and the <hi>wheat,</hi> the <hi>droſs</hi> and the <hi>ſilver;</hi> do not only <hi>condemn</hi> what is evil, but alſo <hi>commend</hi> what is good in the ſame people or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; that is, the method Chriſt obſerved to the ſeven Churches of <hi>Aſia, Rev.</hi> 2. and 3. Chap. as to <hi>Epheſus,</hi> Chapter 2.2. <hi>I know thy works, and thy labour, and thy patience, and how thou canſt not bear them that are evil, and thou haſt tried them which ſay they are Apoſtles, and are not, and haſt found them liers: and haſt born, and haſt patience, and for my Names ſake haſt la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured, and haſt not fainted.</hi> And then he tells them of their faults, verſe 4. <hi>Nevertheleſs, I have ſomwhat againſt thee,</hi> &amp;c. And ſo to <hi>Perga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi> verſe 13. <hi>I know thy works, and where thou dwelleſt, even where Satans ſeat is, and thou holdeſt faſt my name, and haſt not denied my faith, &amp;c.</hi> then in verſe 14. he tells them of their evils, <hi>but I have a few things againſt becauſe thou haſt them that hold the doctrine of Balaam,</hi> &amp;c. And ſo he proceeds to <hi>Thyatira, Sardis,</hi> and <hi>Phila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delphia, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if this method were obſerved by you in your preachings and acting againſt what you judge Error, it would tend much to <hi>unity,</hi> and alſo to the furtherance of the truth you contend for: for by the contrary practice you uſually
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:115061:72"/>
prejudice and incenſe the perſons holding the Errors you reprove againſt the reprover, by your ſo far extending the Error or Errors they hold, as to blemiſh, and render undiſcernable all the graces and precious truths retained and profeſt by them.</p>
            <p n="5">5. In your oppoſing of Errors, lay no more weight upon the Errors reproved, then the Scripture doth; the contrary extream of all hands, tending much to Diviſion: ſuch as are rigid againſt ſeparation, they have one ſort of general exclamations againſt all ſorts of perſons they judge Erroneous, ſeparating from them, jumbling them all together uſually in their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vectives, under the odious names of Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, Heriticks, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And ſuch as are rigid for ſeparation, anſwer them in the ſame extream on the other hand; they cry out againſt them as Idolaters, falſe worſhippers, ſuperſtitions For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maliſts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> by which unchriſtian and unreaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable deportments one towards another, not onely the godly on both hands are incenſed and prejudiced one againſt another, but even car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal wicked people, obſerving theſe paſſages, and hearing ſuch expreſſions, they are hardened in their unbelief, and impiety; they preſently ſtand up with the Phariſee in the Temple, and cry out, Thanks be to God, I am not as other men are, not as this falſe worſhipper, or Formaliſt, nor that Heretick, or Schiſmatick, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> then
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:115061:72"/>
they think they are religious enough; for a great deal of the Religion of this day diſſolves into <hi>negatives;</hi> men are better able to tell you what they are <hi>not</hi> then what they <hi>are</hi> in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</p>
            <p n="6">6. In your labouring againſt Errors, take heed of falſe accuſations, of charging perſons tainted with one or ſome Errors, with many others of a dangerous tendency, which they profeſs a deteſtation againſt; this evil practice hath much tended to Diviſion, and eſtabliſhing ſome perſons in their Errors they hold; for when they have heard that point wherein they are ſaid to be deluded, oppoſed, and ſpoke againſt by a ſlanderous tongue and uncharitable ſpirit, they have concluded it to be a truth from the Error and evil of the ſpirit oppoſing it, and have been ſo much moved to obſerve falſe witneſſes to riſe up againſt them, who laid to their charge things that they knew not, Errors that their ſouls abhor, that they never heeded the Arguments againſt the chief point in controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, but are hereby further prejudiced againſt the truth, preſt upon them by the falſehood and ſlanderouſneſs of the mouth pleading for it, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding, the ſame fountain cannot ſend forth both ſweet water and bitter; and hereby this erroneous way of oppoſing Error, doth ſerve ſome of the main deſigns of the father of Error and Lyes: for next to the corrupting of the
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:115061:73"/>
judgement, he endeavours in order to lock them up in Error, to incenſe their hearts, and preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice them in their affections againſt the truth, and the profeſſors of it: which this untruth-like ſpirit and carriage of the pretended friends of truth doth exceedingly promote.</p>
            <p n="7">7. In your oppoſing <hi>Errors controverſal,</hi> and of leſſer moment, take heed you thereby give not countenance and encouragement to <hi>Errors</hi> more weighty and <hi>fundamental,</hi> leaſt whiles you are pulling a mote out of the eyes of ſome, you do thereby put a beam into the eyes of others; ſome on the one hand ſo rigidly oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Error in thoſe of the ſeparation, that they harden and confirm others, erring againſt the main truths of the new birth and regenerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſetling poor carnal people upon the Lees of their formal profeſſion and outward priviledges, in the neglect of ſanctifying grace, and ſpiritual qualifications, whereby thouſands of poor ſouls are led blindfold to perdition, yet made beleeve they are the onely Orthodox true Chriſtians, becauſe they are free from ſome leſſer contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Errors, ſome holy perſons may be infect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with, when in the mean time they are igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of the main points of ſalvation, and void of the very power and life of godlineſs; yet by this ſinfull daubing of ſome Preachers with un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempered morter are perſwaded of themſelves <hi>Laodicean</hi> like, that they are rich, and have
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:115061:73"/>
need of nothing, and knows not that they are wretched and miſerable, poor, blinde, and naked, the blood of whoſe ſouls will be required at ſuch Preachers hands by the Lord, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33.8, 9. <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>Him that ſaith to the wicked, thou art righteous, him ſhall the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple curſe:</hi> and if ſo, then, ſurely, him will not the righteous God bleſs; he who would not have his <hi>childrens</hi> bread caſt to <hi>Dogs,</hi> would much leſs have <hi>Dogs</hi> accounted <hi>Children,</hi> whilſt his <hi>Children</hi> are accounted <hi>Dogs,</hi> which is a crying ſin at this day amongſt ſome ſuch as would be loth not to be accounted godly Miniſters, who ye ſhall obſerve carry them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves towards ſome poor Chriſtians in their Pariſhes, who differ from them, as towards the worſt of men, and in their Pulpits are more vehement and harſh againſt them, then againſt the moſt prophane impious perſons and practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; and in the mean while adminiſter the preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſealing Ordinances of the Goſpel to a mixt multitude, many, if not moſt of which being ignorant, ſcandalous and prophane perſons, common ſcoffers at Religion, common ſwearers, drunkards, Sabbath-breakers, &amp;c. yet all thoſe (ſaving ſome general admonitions againſt ſin, and general exhortations to duty) ſhall be ſpoke <hi>of</hi> and <hi>to,</hi> and walked <hi>towards</hi> as the Church of Chriſt, and people of God; and if there be ſome more ſober perſon or perſons who are free
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:115061:74"/>
from the fore-mentioned ſcandals, and have at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained to ſome Hiſtorical knowledge of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and cloſe but with them in the way of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip they are for, eſpecially if by their eſtate or intereſt they be able to ſerve their deſigns, why ſuch men muſt be eſteemed of, and cried up for eminent godly men; when as to any inward ſanctifying work of grace in their hearts, there is no more appearance of it, then there was of Goſpel in <hi>Paul</hi> when he was <hi>Saul</hi> the perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, or of the work of regeneration in <hi>Nicode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi> when he came to Chriſt by night: Now what is this leſs then <hi>juſtifying the wicked for a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and taking away the righteouſneſs of the righteous from him? Iſa.</hi> 5.23.</p>
            <p>And the ſame ſort of evil is to be diſcerned, though not in ſo great a meaſure in them that are rigidly for ſeparation, and particular opinions; many of them will be ready to have a huge good opinion, and ſhew a ſingular reſpect to perſons that favour them in their particular perſwaſions; though otherwiſe looſe notional frothy perſons, void of any ſavour or power of Godlineſs, and in the mean time have a ſlight eſteem of perſons both ſober and gratious, that differ from them, againſt whom they will be ready to take up an evil report, and joyn with carnal looſe people in reproaching them, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the mindes of ſuch carnal Incendiaries are ſetled in a looſe frothy notional frame, againſt
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:115061:74"/>
the gravity and purity of Religion; now theſe practiſes of all hands, though they may be vail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed under pretences of zeal for Truth againſt Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, or for purity of worſhip againſt the Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and cuſtoms of men; yet they are impious and evil in themſelves; beſides, exceeding pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judicial and deſtructive, both to the purity and unity of Gods people, and ought to be avoided and witneſſed againſt, as the worſt ſort of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godlineſs in godly perſons.</p>
            <p>But though I could not omit the giving theſe cautions to all that pretend a Love to <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi>'s <hi>Peace,</hi> yet little is my expectation, as to the furtherance of this bleſſed work, from ſuch as have engaged themſelves far in theſe carnal con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendings for ſpiritual things; for evils clothed with good and plauſible pretences, are not eaſily reclaimed: therefore I ſhall direct my ſelf chiefly in what I have further to ſay, to Goſpel Miniſters, to thoſe few names in <hi>Sardis,</hi> that have not defiled their garments with theſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentious dividing practices; for many there are I hope, that for the Diviſions of <hi>Reuben</hi> have great thoughts of heart, whoſe ſouls long for <hi>Sions</hi> Peace; who with <hi>Jeremiah</hi> could wiſh their heads were waters, and their eyes foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains of tears, that they might weep day and night for the ſlain of the daughter of their peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: Now to ſuch I have theſe following di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections to propoſe.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="116" facs="tcp:115061:75"/>Though you do not think it convenient to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage your ſelves in the controverſies of the times as they tend to eſtrange the hearts and alienate the affections of good People one from another, yet to engage your ſelves in a controverſy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt controverſies, managing of it with a ſpirit of love and tenderneſs, which may ſo much tend in the fruits of it to the endearing, and uniting of the hearts of Saints one to another, that may be worth your engaging in. If you ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve what is ſaid, page 32, 33, 34, 35, 36. you will there ſee how all the ſervants of God in all ages contended againſt the contentions in the Church, and laboured to preſerve union a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt Saints as the main duty.</p>
            <p>And therefore in the firſt place I would begg of you, to ſtir up your own hearts with all the Saints near you to be much in prayer for this mercy; ſet ſpecial times apart to meet together to wreſtle with the Lord about it: this is a difficult and a great work, and prayer hath done many ſuch; all thoſe late great mercies that God hath beſtowed upon his People in theſe Nations [which they are now ſo unable to agree about the dividing of] were all by many gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and eminent inſtruments received and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged to be the returns of Prayer: I ſhall cloſe this requeſt with <hi>Joels</hi> exhortation, Chap. 2.17. <hi>Let the Prieſts the Miniſters of the Lord weep between the Porch and the Altar, and let them ſay,
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:115061:75"/>
Spare thy People O Lord, and give not thy heritage to reproach, that the Heathen ſhould uſe a by-word againſt them; wherefore ſhould they ſay among the People, Where is their God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Give up your ſelves to ſtudy and propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate this truth; for among the multitude of books that this day hath produced, I have found few, though I have diligently enquired and ſought for them of this ſubject; And had I not been wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried with long delayed expectation, I ſhould not durſt to have made an Eſſay upon this work; but I hope if it be of no other uſe, it may ſerve to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke ſome of you to lay your hand to this plough, leaſt ſuch unskilful ones as my ſelf is, ſhould ſpoile a good cauſe by badly managing it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Set upon ſome beginnings in <hi>Goſpel-fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi> upon this <hi>Goſpel principle;</hi> I am perſwaded the Lord would proſper and bleſſe it, againſt this Spirit of diviſion, as the houſe of <hi>David</hi> againſt <hi>Sauls;</hi> it ſhal grow ſtronger and ſtronger, and the other weaker and weaker: the Lord ſeems to be withdrawing his good ſpirit of his quickening, ſanctifying, comforting grace from the People, with whom the ſpirit of diviſion is moſt predominate, even pouring upon the head of dividers what he threatned to back-ſliders, <hi>Prov.</hi> 14.14. even to fill them with their own wayes, that they are even wearied with the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of their diviſions and contentions; and ſuch as are ſincerely ſenſible thereof, are ready
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:115061:76"/>
to cry out with <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 120.6 <hi>My ſoul hath long dwelt with him that hateth peace;</hi> unto whom your feet will be beautiful, that bring good tydings; that publiſh peace, <hi>Eſay</hi> 52.7. when they ſhall obſerve by your Order and ſpirituall concord, <hi>how good and pleaſant a thing it is for brethren to dwell together in unity,</hi> as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 133.1.</p>
            <p>If you have already the charge of a particular Church, labour to inſtruct them in this precious truth, which when they have received, endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to manifeſt it and make it known to all the Godly round about, that you are in <hi>charity,</hi> and deſire to be in <hi>fellowſhip</hi> with them, and all the <hi>godly</hi> or <hi>viſible Beleevers</hi> in the World; But if you be not engaged to any particular Church at preſent, then make known your judgment to al that feares God near unto you, and preſs them to their dutys, to congregate themſelves together and to have fellowſhip one with another in all Ordinances ſo farr as the Lord hath enlightned them therein, which when obtained, proceed as before.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>But in caſe the Churches, or at leaſt a great part of them over whom the Lord hath ſet us, be ſo averſe to this truth that the promoting of it among them may hazard a breach betwixt us, or at leaſt a diviſion in the Churche, show ſhould we then walk in the proſecution of this duty?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Either ſuch an averſneſs muſt proceed
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:115061:76"/>
from a <hi>conſcientious godly fear,</hi> that ſome other truth of Chriſt they have received may be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judiced thereby.</p>
            <p>Otherwiſe from a <hi>contentious unruly frame of ſpirit,</hi> not being able to bear the ſincere and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vory advice and inſtruction of thoſe the Lord hath ſet over them; If from the former, a great deal of tenderneſs, and Chriſtian patience, ought to be exerciſed toward them, and endeavours uſed to ſatisfie them; that your main aim and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendment in promoting this duty is to take away the cauſe from whence all grievances of that hand come, and to provide that an equal pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion of Liberty and opportunity may be to all conſcientiouſly profeſſing or practiſing any controverted point without the leaſt diſcourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or reſtraint, which is as much as any ſober mind can deſire. If from the latter, leſſe weight is, to be put upon it ſaith <hi>Paul, if any man ſeem to be contentious, we have no ſuch cuſtom, neither the Churhes of God,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.16. And ſo to <hi>Titus, There are many unruly and vain talkers, whoſe mouths muſt be ſtopped, Titus</hi> 1.10, 11. <hi>Rebuke them ſharply that they may be ſound in the faith; verſ.</hi> 13. <hi>Theſe things ſpeak and exhort, and rebuke with all authority; let no man deſpiſe thee, Chapter</hi> 2.15. when Chriſtians contain not themſelves within the bounds of a ſober gracious ſpirit, whether the matter they ſtrive about be truth or error, their pride, paſſion, unrulineſs ought to be reproved.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="120" facs="tcp:115061:77"/>But if in caſe they all ſhould agree to diſſent in this matter, and will retain their former rule of ſeparation, yet if they be willing to allow that liberty to others that they deſire to enjoy them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, ſeparate not from them, but the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther abide with them as with a Church of Chriſt that moſt needs your help: For Chriſtians, much more miniſters ſhould not ſomuch conſider where they may walk to enjoy moſt comfort and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian liberty &amp;c. but rather where they may be moſt ſerviceable to the Lord, and the weak di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſed of his People; for the whole need not the Phyſitian.</p>
            <p>But though I do judge you ought to condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend to the weakneſs of your Brethren, and to walk with all Chriſtian and brotherly affection towards them, yet not herein with <hi>Peter, Gal.</hi> 2.12, 13. to diſſemble the truth, or to ſuffer any of the ſame ſociety to be impoſed on by them; but your ſelves withall like-minded to manifeſt your charity towards, and deſire of <hi>fellowſhip with all the Saints on earth,</hi> and as your occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons give you opportunity, to evidence your prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple by your practice.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>But in caſe the Church with whom wee walk ſhould be ſo offended as they ſhould proceed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us, and withdraw from us upon this Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Having as before walked with all ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs and unblamableneſs towards them, let
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:115061:77"/>
not that offend you; that is their Sin, ſo to abuſe an Ordinance of God; it is not yours; the fear of this puniſhment kept many a beleeving Jew from publiquely owning the Goſpel, <hi>John</hi> 12.42. <hi>Nevertheleſſe among the chief rulers alſo many be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeved on him, but bicauſe of the Phariſees durſt not confeſſe him; least they ſhould be put out of the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogue;</hi> ſo <hi>John.</hi> 9.22. <hi>Acts.</hi> 22.19.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>But would not this be a meanes to fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and encreaſe a great deal of contention and ſtrife in every particular Church? for where con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations do conſiſt of perſons ſo different-minded each enjoying an equall liberty of profeſſing and practiſing their different perſwaſions, this muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily tend to a frequent begetting diſputes and controverſies amongst them, whereby the mutual edification and comfort of the whole would be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dangered.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Without doubt the different perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Chriſtians walking together in the ſame fellowſhip, will be attended with many difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and hazards, which the mercy of unity of underſtanding would remove; but put them all in the ballance with the fore-mentioned evils which their dividing and ſeparating from one another as at preſent is attended with, and then judge which is the greateſt; for where a neceſſity of evill is upon us, one in competition with the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, it is our duty to admit the leaſt, that which leaſt diſhonors God, and tends leaſt to the
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:115061:78"/>
ruine and deſolation of his Church and people; and ſure I need not bring the evils attending each of theſe caſes in competition, to find out which is the greateſt; but when you find ſuch Errors or Erroneous perſons ſingled out; the admitting of whom into the Church of God, or giving the right hand of fellowſhip unto, would be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with equall evill, either as to Gods diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour, or to the damage of his Church, that our preſent Diviſions are attended with; then and not elſe, I judge you ought to aſſent there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to: But if once union of Saints had that weight upon our hearts which it ought to have, I do not judge differences of judgement amongſt Members of the ſame Church could be ſo incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent to its Peace and Edification: For,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Church muſt allow an <hi>equal liberty</hi> to all controverſal points, either in doctrine or practice, and withal muſt provide an <hi>equal rule</hi> to <hi>limit,</hi> and reſtrain the extreams of unſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, unſober, and troubleſom promotions of them, or oppoſitions to them of each hand, ſo that the mutual edification and comfortable walking of the whole, in the practice of thoſe main duties, wherein there is a mutual agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, may not be interrupted; for <hi>God is not the Author of confuſion,</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>but of Peace in all Churches of the Saints,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.33. And <hi>James</hi> doth not ſay, Where difference of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding is, <hi>but, where envying and ſtrife is,
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:115061:78"/>
there is confuſion &amp; every evil work;</hi> and therefore, do but make an <hi>equal</hi> proviſion againſt carnal contentions, and diſorderly promotions of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverted points, and then the holding them, or ſober preaching and practiſing of them, could not be inconſiſtent to union in the ſame Church.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>But would not this be a means to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice, and block up the way of ſome deſpiſed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverted truths, which much the leaſt part of the people of God have received, and the generality is very much prejudiced againſt? And this way would ſubject the Saints, profeſſing them, to the united Church power of ſuch</hi> as oppoſe <hi>them, and thereby bring ſuch truths of God, and the profeſſors of them, under great diſcouragements and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Whatſoever the rule of Chriſt directs us unto, in order to the promoting controverted deſpiſed truths, is the beſt way to promote them, howſoever to our reaſon it may not ſeem ſo to be; and when we lay our hands to any part of Gods work, we muſt be careful to keep our feet in the way of his pathes; and though con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies and differences of underſtanding have been in all ages in the Church; yet produce one Inſtance out of Gods Word to juſtifie Separati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereupon, before you plead for the practice of it; but this Union would not at all tend to the prejudice of any particular truth that may be at preſent under reproach amongſt the generality
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:115061:79"/>
of Chriſtians; for nothing more tends to the damage of an oppoſed deſpiſed truth then the reproach and diſhonour brought upon it by weak, ſelf-conceited ſticklers for it, whoſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſonable and unſober contending for it doth ſo much offend, and ſtumble the contrary mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that they take a prejudice againſt the truth for the promoters ſake, whereas were Saints uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in Church Order, there might be ſpecial times and places appointed for the moſt able and ſober of each different perſwaſion, to hold forth their grounds for their judgement either Doctrinally, by way of Preaching, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, by a ſober and Chriſtian conference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt ſuch as the brethren of each different perſwaſion ſhould make choice of, where all might have liberty to be preſent, and to make their ſober Objections againſt what ſhould be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered as they ſee cauſe; and this might be done without the leaſt diſturbance of the peace, and with mutual edification of the whole as a Church which would alſo exceedingly tend to remove thoſe diſcouragements on the one hand, which lye in the way of deſpiſed Truths, and thoſe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragements on the other hand, that are given by our diviſions to ſeveral applauded Errors: For when the Judgment of any perſon made him neither more nor leſſe eſteemed, nor advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taged; Chriſtians would then receive or reject controverted points ſingly to anſwer a good
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:115061:79"/>
Conſcience towards God in obedience to his will made known to them, whereby doubtleſs Truth would much prevail againſt Error; for a ſincere ſober Conſcience no ways byaſſed ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome miſcarries in its judgement.</p>
            <p>And ſo in our preſent divided confuſed ſtate, ſeveral controverted Truths may ſuffer much prejudice by the many Errors they are accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with in the Profeſſors of them: and oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſo inter-woven and intangled in their practice, that ſuch as may have a deſire to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe the Truth are diſcouraged, and kept off thereby; whereas this Union upon Goſpel prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples removes all that, and leaves every Truth ſingle and pure without any addition or detra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; thou mayeſt then take up ſuch a trampled on pearl, though it be found among Swine, and adde it to the Bracelet of thy former graces or duties, without wallowing with them in the mire to enjoy it or perform it.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>But there are many whom we judge god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, both Miniſters and private Chriſtians that will be oppoſite to us in this work upon the account of our ſeparation from the carnal multitude and viſible unbelievers, they admitting a bare profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Chriſtian Religion with ſome other additional qualifications, not evidencing converſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on nor viſible grace to be the rule of Church-mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berſhip,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>now how ſhould we walk towards them?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="126" facs="tcp:115061:80"/>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> As in the former Caſes, ſo in this there muſt be a great deal of regard had to the diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of mind and nature of the Principles from which ſuch perſons diſſent or oppoſe; for that may much aggravate, or extenuate their evill, and thereby much differ the Rule of your walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing towards them; for if ſuch oppoſition or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent proceed from that common Principle and Spirit of oppoſition and contempt which ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally the Popiſh and Prelatical people walk in againſt holy qualifications and purity of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip preſt after by the Godly, then to walk to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them as perſons holding only the form of Religion, but denying the power of it, but if ſuch diſſent, or oppoſition proceed from a conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious mind charitably diſpoſed towards the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, thus walking, only differing in judgment as to the Rules of Church-memberſhip, then ſuch a conſcientious diſſent and charitable mind on the one hand requires a ſuitable deportment on the other; then though you ought not to own them, nor joyne with them in an union of Church-ſtate, in regard their Principles and practices may waſt the viſible bounds of Chriſts Church (viz. Regeneration and Sanctifying faith) yet to walk towards them with all Chriſtian tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and charitable reſpect, owning what is good in them, as well as rejecting what is evill, that though you cannot own them in the ſtate in which they ſtand as true Goſpel Churches, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:115061:80"/>
the Principle by which they walk opens the door to all materiall pollution, and the body of the matter of which they are built are not living ſtones, yet you may own their perſons whiles in that State as Goſpel brethren, and perform towards them all dutyes of Goſpel brotherhood which they are capable as particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Chriſtians to receive, and are willing to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of at your hands; and ſuch of them as the Lord hath by his Providence, called &amp; by his gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces &amp; ſpiritual gifts qualified for the work of the miniſtry, they making it their maine buſineſs to convert Souls to Chriſt, and to preſs their hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers to ſanctification, and Godly life; they ought doubtles to <hi>be highly eſteemed for their works ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> and to be frequently prayed for, that God would give them utterance, <hi>that they may open their mouths boldly to make known the myſtery of the Goſpel,</hi> as in <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.19. and the ſucceſs of their labours to be as much prized; and thanks to be as duly returned to the Lord for it as for the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of thoſe in Goſpel Order; herein Chriſt ſet us an example, <hi>Mark</hi> 9.39. ſhewing this reaſon for it; <hi>he that is not againſt us is on our part, verſe</hi> 40. And ſo <hi>Paul,</hi> though ſome preached Chriſt of envy and contention, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.15.16. yet ſaith he, <hi>what then notwithſtanding every way whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in pretence or truth Chriſt is preached, and I do therein rejoyce, yea and will rejoyce therein, verſe</hi> 18. ſo that I do judge, though there cannot be
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:115061:81"/>
an union of Church State with ſuch, yet there ought to be a tender and charitable deportment towards ſuch as viſible Saints, and Goſpel Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>But there are many who will be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded amongſt the number of common profeſſors, that though there be nothing appearing in them that evidences a work of grace or true converſion, yet they are not prophane ſcandalous perſons, nor deſpiſers nor raylers at Godlineſs, but ſeem to be ſenſible of their own ignorance, and deſirous to be further informed in the power and mystery of the Goſpel. Now how ought we to walk towards ſuch? muſt we eſteem them as Idolaters or Heathens, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are not viſible Converts, and walk in a falſe way of worſhip?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> As I do judge the grace of Chriſt in Saints where it hath its kindly work, dos natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tend to humble &amp; lay low Saints in their own eyes, and makes them vile in their own ſight; ſo it doth as naturally tend to work in them a tend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er heart and charitable affections towards all others in whom the leaſt appearance of love to Chriſt is found, rather directing them to erre (in matters in the leaſt doubtfull) in <hi>charity, then</hi> in <hi>Severity;</hi> for that great Goſpel grace of Charity which the Scripture ſo much magnifies and gives the preheminence above all other graces unto, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. is only then uſefull when the caſe is doubtfull; for where certain evidences of things
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:115061:81"/>
are, there needs not Charity to Chancellorize; for then our underſtanding and judgment of themſelves are able to determine; which being defective, and ſubject to erre, in doubtful caſes the Lord hath provided Charity to be Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor in the Conſcience, whoſe buſineſs is when the <hi>ſeverity</hi> of a rule tends to oppreſs, to <hi>moderate</hi> and prefer mercy and equity before ſeverity and exactneſs of rule; therefore wherein the caſe may be in any meaſure doubtful, Charity muſt then ſupply the defect of viſible evidences, at leaſt to ſuſpend thy judgement on the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere hand:</p>
            <p>And therefore I anſwer, you ought not to eſteem them either Heathens or Idolaters, but Chriſtians, though their conditions were much more doubtfull then the qualification in your ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection ſtates them to be; for I do judge a ſenſe of ignorance with a ſincere deſire after further knowledge in the myſtery of the Goſpel, are (if not ſignes of the new birth) yet evident ſignes of ſpiritual pangs that prepare for it, and ought inſtead of being ſo vilified and ſlighted, to be taken into the Churches care, and watch, who is in that caſe to perform the part of a compaſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, tender, and ſpiritual midwife, by uſing all means to encourage, ſtrengthen and comfort ſuch ſoules, leſt there ſhall want ſtrength to bring forth; yet not adminiſter the Seals until there be Evidence of a new Creature for firſt
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:115061:82"/>
God muſt ſubſcribe the evidence, you muſt be able to read his hand in a viſible work of grace before you ought to apply his Seals, which are to be a viſible confirmation of the new Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, agreement between God and the soul.</p>
            <p>But doubtleſs not only in theſe caſes, but to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards all profeſſing Chriſtianity, Gods people ought to demeane themſelves with all tenderneſs, and reſpect; and avoid all provoking and harſh carriage, either in word or deed, that ſhall tend to the hardning and incenſing of them againſt the precious wayes of God; and <hi>to ſhew out of a good converſation their workes with meekneſs of wiſedome:</hi> Paul fearing the ſpirits of the Saints in this caſe, exhorts the Colloſſians <hi>to walke in wiſdome towards them that are without; and that their ſpeech ſhould be alwaies with grace, ſeaſoned with ſalt; that they might know how they ought to anſwer every man. Chap.</hi> 4, 5, 6. And ſo to the Theſſalonians, <hi>ſtuddy to be quiet, and to do your own buſineſs, &amp;c. that ye may walke honesty to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them that are without.</hi> &amp;c. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.11.12.</p>
            <p>But if Chriſtians were more exerciſed in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering the riches and freeneſs of Gods Grace to their poore ſouls, and of their own vileneſs and unworthineſs of the leaſt part thereof, if they would more look unto the Rock whence they are hewn; and the hole of the pitt whence
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:115061:82"/>
they are digged, they would be leſs in offenſive termes, and ſcornefull carriages towards poore carnal profeſſors; they would rather ſay as <hi>Paul</hi> argues, 1 Cor. 4.7. <hi>who maketh us to differ from others? what have we that we did not receive?</hi> Unto whom I ſhall conclude with <hi>Pauls</hi> reply, <hi>Now if you did receive it, why doe ye glory as if you had not received it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I might multiply many more Anſwers to Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections, that may lie in the way of this duty of making beginnings in this bleſſed worke; but I hope the proſperous ſucceſs of ſome, whoſe hearts the Lord ſhall engage in the practice hereof, will be more convincing arguments, to prove that gracious holy perſons of diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent judgments, may comfortably walke to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in Goſpel fellowſhip, edifying each other in their moſt holy faith, without being offenſive or grievous one to another in their different mindes, then I am able to adde; and therefore I ſhall conclude what I have to ſay to Goſpell Miniſters, as to their propagating this pretious truth with this one direction.</p>
            <p n="4">4. If providence hath placed your preſent reſidence amongſt a people ſo frowardly bent to dividing principles and practices, that the labouring to promote this Goſpel union, might be ſo ill reſented by them, as might render your preſent miniſtration unacceptable, and thereby unſuccesfull amongſt them that you have cauſe
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:115061:83"/>
to take up <hi>Davids</hi> complaint, Pſal. 120.7. <hi>I am for peace; but when I ſpeak they are for warre.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then it is my opinion, you ought to ſuſpend earneſt preſſing the practice of this Goſpel union; and ſay as the Lord did <hi>Iohn</hi> 16.12. <hi>I have yet many things to ſay, but you cannot beare them now.</hi> But yet not to cloſe with ſuch in their rigid dividing principles as <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Barna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bas</hi> did, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.12, 13. but to be daily labouring to remove them; for take but away the rubbiſh and droſs of Chriſtians principles and ſpirits, and then like hewn ſtones they will unite of themſelves.</p>
            <p n="1">1. By the rubbiſh and droſs of their ſpirits that hinders union, I meane thoſe ſinful diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers of ſpirit, that are contrary to the uniting graces before mentioned, as Pride and Paſſion, ſelfe conceit, Envy, Hatred, Emulations and the like; for if theſe were once removed, and the oppoſite graces ſtrengthned, inclinations to union would become as natural to them, as now inclinations to diviſion are; for remove but the cauſe and the effect ceaſeth; and if you ſhould convince them of the evill of their dividing principles, before their dividing ſpirits were ſubdued, they would be no more capable to practice this Goſpel union then a drunken man would be capable to goe without ſtaggering; and therefore if nothing elſe can be done to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards this worke, be preparing the ſpirits of
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:115061:83"/>
Gods people with uniting graces. 2. By the rubbiſh or dividingneſs of their principles, I meane ſuch notions and tenents as naturally tend to diviſion, which Chriſtians of moſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions have received by tradition from their fathers, as I may ſay, that becauſe former good men of the ſame opinion with them, and the people all along profeſſing the ſame way with them have ſo done, therefore they conceive they muſt do ſo too, of which ſort of dividing principles are,</p>
            <p n="1">1. A confining their Chriſtian relation, affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and duty within the limits of their own judgements, allowing God to have no viſible Church, nor judging themſelves to owe any ſpecial duty to Chriſtians as Brethren beyond their own rule of <hi>fellowſhip,</hi> which principle is uſually the nurſe, if not the mother of theſe following practices.</p>
            <p>From hence proceed all thoſe ſcruples which hinder Saints from a free participation of each others gifts and graces; on the one hand ſuch as are rigid againſt Separation, will neither hear nor joyn with any but ſuch as are of their own Principles; they will either have Objections againſt their Call and Ordination; or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe againſt their judgement and qualifications; and thereby oft deprive themſelves of a ſoul-ſearching powerful inſtruction, and ſtand pick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the bones of a dry, ſapleſs, Hiſtorica Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:115061:84"/>
ſet off with the trimming of ſome hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane excellency; that the other might want more minding what the diſh is the Lord pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents the Bread of life to them in, then the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and ſpiritualneſs of the Bread it ſelf, when the Lord doth uſually put this treaſure of his graces, and ſpiritual gifts into earthen veſſels, <hi>that the glory might be of God, and not of man,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.7. He oft times <hi>hides theſe things from the wiſe and prudent, when he reveals them to babes and ſucklings,</hi> Mat. 11.25. I having ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved ſome whom I judge godly, to rigid upon this hand, that they have rather choſe to hear where the Speaker hath been a viſible ungra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious perſon, or ſtay at home, then to attend a powerful heart-ſearching Godly Preacher contrary-minded in ſome things to them.</p>
            <p>And on the other hand many poor Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans do run into the like extream; for as the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer makes humane defects the Rule of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection, they go neer to make them the Rule of Election; and ſo by both the true Rule of gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious qualifications and ſpiritual gifts where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever found are declined, and ſet light by, and put in competition with every circumſtantial thing; whereas if Chriſtians would make that which tends moſt to anſwer the ends of hearing, (<hi>viz.</hi> the nouriſhment, edification and comfort of their ſouls the rule of hearing theſe things would not be; and nothing would more tend to further the Saints union, then the removal
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:115061:84"/>
of theſe hinderances in their providential Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion in things wherein they are agreed; for if gracious perſons different-minded, did but ſometimes meet to pour out their Souls to the Lord together in prayer, for their joynt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernments, and to taſte the preciouſneſs of each others experiences, and graces by a mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all communication of ſpiritual gifts, it would much tend to remove uncharitable jealouſies; and endear their hearts one to another: that was the Argument <hi>Peter</hi> uſed to convince the unbeleeving Jews, that the Gentiles were per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers with them of the ſame grace, <hi>Acts</hi> 11.17. <hi>Foraſmuch then as God gave them the like gifts as he did unto us, who believed on the Lord Jeſus Chriſt; what was I that I could withſtand God,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to which Reaſon they aſſented, <hi>v.</hi> 18. <hi>When they heard theſe things they held their peace, and glorified God, ſaying, Then hath God alſo to the Gentiles granted repentance unto life:</hi> From which Scripture you may clearly gather that it was both <hi>Peters</hi> and the believing Jews opinion, that ſuch ought to own and eſteem each other as fellow-brethren in the Goſpel of Chriſt, whom God had grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the ſame precious gifts and graces unto. And I may ſay, it is impoſſible for Chriſtians ever to come to an union in things wherein they differ, until they come to a Communion in things wherein they agree; for while Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans be at the utmoſt diſtance one from another
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:115061:85"/>
they can never come to acknowledge (of any thing that is obliging or uniting) for we may truly ſay of this ſpirit of Diviſion, as <hi>Ahab</hi> ſaid of <hi>Micaiah,</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 22.8. <hi>It doth never ſpeak good of me</hi> that is, of Chriſtians differing in judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to one another; It will not want its Spies at every Chriſtian meeting or Sermon to gather up all offenſive dividing expreſſions, and paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and carry them up and down as fuell to the fire of contention, that if ye obſerve it, there is not the leaſt ſecret miſ-carriage among Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans but ſhall be known, talked of, and ſtretched out to the utmoſt, by others contrary-minded to them.</p>
            <p>But Chriſt wants his Intelligencers to publiſh and tell of thoſe expreſſions and paſſages which would tend to unite and endear differing Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians one to another, and if any out of a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to beget love amongſt Saints ſhould take upon them that Office, they would find it a very unthankful one, where this ſpirit of Diviſion hath found entertainment, though there it is moſt needed; and therefore until ye open the door of a free participation of gifts and graces among Saints, expect no union.</p>
            <p>And as this principle of confining the Church, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> within our own limits, thus nouriſhes di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding practices, and hinders a free communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of gifts and graces; ſo it tends to beget and nouriſh the ſaddeſt of inward deluſions of heart
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:115061:85"/>
that Chriſtians can be poſſeſt with, tending to the Corruption of our beſt duties to God, and to make all our ſolemne ſacrifices have an ill ſavour before him; as</p>
            <p n="1">1. It confines our petitions and the deſires of our hearts in prayer to a few of Gods people, excluding the reſt; for no further then our prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples carry us to own Gods Church, and people to extend, can our petitions to the Lord for his Church and people intend; nay hereby ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times our prayers becomes oppoſite to Gods de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes of mercy to his people, when they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare before him at the throne of grace in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to one another; and juſtifying where he condemnes; and condemning where he juſtifies; it would make a conſiderate heart tremble to appeare before him that knows all hearts in Prayer; and there to repeat ſuch general peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions as theſe. <hi>Doe good in thy good pleaſure unto Sion, build thou the walls of Jeruſalem. Pſal.</hi> 51.18. and in their hearts exclude the generality of the Lords people, or to utter ſuch complaints as theſe: <hi>Let them all be confounded and turned backe that hate Sion, &amp;c.</hi> Pſal. 129.5. and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend hereby amongſt others, ſuch as are graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous perſons, differing-minded to them, only for oppoſing ſome controverted point of Doctrine or practice which they have received, and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine as carnally as the other oppoſeth it. I ſay, thus to do is to provoke the Lord againſt us all,
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:115061:86"/>
by engaging him as much as lyeth in us, in our carnal contentions and diviſions, that the Lord hath juſt cauſe to take up that complaint againſt us, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.20.21. <hi>Thou ſitteſt and ſpeakeſt againſt thy brother; thou ſlaundereſt thine own mothers ſonne; theſe things haſt thou done, and I kept ſilence; thou thoughteſt I was altogether ſuch an one as thy ſelfe; but I will reprove thee; and ſet them in Order before thine eyes.</hi> This is very neere kinne to the ſin of that evill Servant, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.31. whom when his Lord had forgiven him many Talents, to take his fellow ſervant by the throate for one.</p>
            <p>And as it thus miſguides the heart in prayer, ſo in prayſes; this contraction in our hearts of the extent of God Church, will tend to put us upon rejoycing and prayſing, when we ſhould weepe and mourne, and put us upon mourning when we ſhould rejoyce; how hath this ungrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full principle, robbed the Lord of the glory due unto his name, for all the great mercies he hath beſtowed upon us in theſe Nations of late years, which before this ſpirit of diviſion overſpread us, had weight upon our hearts; that the people of the Lord did then ſeem to ſay with the Church, <hi>Pſal</hi> 126.1. <hi>When the Lord turned againe the captivity of Sion, we were like them that dreame; then was our mouth filled with laughter, and our tongues with ſinging; then ſaid they among the heathen; the Lord hath done great things for
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:115061:86"/>
them; the Lord hath done great things for us, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of we are glad;</hi> but now we have cauſe to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine with the Church, <hi>Lam,</hi> 5.15. <hi>the joy of our heart is turned into mourning, the Crown is fallen from our head; woe unto us that we have ſinned;</hi> now little but murmuring and complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is heard in our ſtreets; what we yet want, ſeemes to make all wee poſſeſs not worth being thankfull for.</p>
            <p>As this confineing Principle byaſſes our hearts in prayer and praiſe, ſo it tends to put us upon a wreſtling and miſapplying the precious promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and precepts of Chriſt, in the Scripture, to miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guide our obedience to God, and duty towards our brethren; for all we exclude out of the pale of the Church, we therby exclude from an intereſt in the promiſes; they are thereby made as far as it is in our power Aliens from the Commonwealth of Iſrael, and ſtrangers to the Covenant, and promiſes, and alſo thereby we excuſe our ſelves of all thoſe ſpecial dutyes we owe to one another as Chriſtian Brethren, that ye ſhal receive it as an Ordinary anſwer from ſome Chriſtians, if ye preſs them to Chriſtian duty towards ſuch as are not of the ſame fellowſhip with them; what have we to do with them that are without? but I am well aſſured that will not be admitted for a good anſwer at the laſt day to the Lord.</p>
            <p>And thus I ſhall conclude what I have to ſay to Gods Miniſters as to their part in this work
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:115061:87"/>
of Saints union, hoping the Lord will ſtir up the hearts of ſome of them to ſet their ſhouldiers to it, that that precious promiſe of the Lord to his Church, <hi>Eſay</hi> 60.17, 18. may be fulfilled in them, <hi>I will make thine Officers peace &amp;c. violence ſhall no more be heard in thy Land, waſting and deſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion within thy borders, but thou ſhalt call thy walls ſalvation, and thy Gates praiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:115061:87"/>
            <head>Books Printed, and are to be ſold by <hi>Giles Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert,</hi> at the black-ſpread Eagle, at the Weſt-end of St. <hi>Pauls.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>REnodaeus</hi> his diſpenſatory, containing the whole body of Phyſick; diſcovering the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and Properties, and vertues of Vegetals, Minerals and Animals: in folio.</item>
               <item>The Hiſtory of <hi>Diodorus Siculus,</hi> containing all that which is moſt memorable and of greateſt Antiquity in the firſt ages of the World, until the war of <hi>Troy:</hi> in folio.</item>
               <item>Doctor <hi>Pordages Innocencie</hi> appearing through the Dark Miſts of pretended guilt: in folio.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cornelius Aggrippa;</hi> his occult Philoſophy in 3 Books in quarto.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Henry Laurence</hi> Lord Preſident his book En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled, Our Communion and War with Angels, in quarto.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chriſtopher Goad</hi> his Sermons Entituled, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhing Drops, and Scorching Vials, in quarto.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>William Dells</hi> works in quarto.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Samuel Gorton,</hi> his Expoſition on the fifth Chapter of <hi>James,</hi> in quarto.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Samuel Hartlibs</hi> of Bees and Silkworms, in quarto.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cotton,</hi> his Book called the Bloody Tenet of Perſecution for cauſe of conſcience, in quarto.</item>
               <item>Doctor <hi>Gells</hi> Sermon Entituled <hi>Noahs</hi> Flood returning, in quarto.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:115061:88"/>A Taſte of the Spirit of God and of this world, by <hi>Robert Bacon</hi> in quarto.</item>
               <item>Several Pieces of <hi>Chriſtopher Blackwood,</hi> now publick Teacher in <hi>Ireland,</hi> in quarto.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Jacob Behem,</hi> his <hi>Signatura Rerum,</hi> or Signa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of all things, in quarto.</item>
               <item>His Epiſtles explaining many things written in his other Books, in quarto.</item>
               <item>Of Election and Predeſtination in quarto.</item>
               <item>His Book Entituled <hi>Aurora,</hi> or the day-ſpring lately printed in quarto.</item>
               <item>Several Pieces of <hi>Jſaac Penington</hi> Junior, in quarto.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Biggs</hi> of the vanity of the Craft of Phyſick, or a new Diſpenſatory in quarto.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Averies</hi> Scriptures Propheſies, in quarto.</item>
               <item>An Apology or Plea for two Treatiſes againſt Infant Baptiſme by <hi>John Tombs,</hi> in quarto.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>William Sedgwicks</hi> his leaves of the tree of life for the healing of the Nation, in quarto.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Collier</hi> his Pulpit-guard routed, in quarto.</item>
               <item>His Font-guard routed, in quarto.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Simon Hendon</hi> his key of Scripture Propheſies in quarto.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Parker</hi> his Anſwer to the Aſſembly, in large octavo.</item>
               <item>Several pieces of <hi>Thomas Collier,</hi> in large octavo.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Tillom</hi> on the eleventh Chapter of the <hi>Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> in large octavo.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:115061:88"/>
                  <hi>Henry Laurence</hi> Lord Preſident his Book of Baptiſme, in large octavo.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cobs</hi> Sermons entituled the Straight-Gate, in large octavo.</item>
               <item>Several Peeces of <hi>H. N.</hi> in octavo, namely, Prophecy of the Spirit of Love. <hi>Revelatio dei,</hi> or the Revelation of God.</item>
               <item>Introduction to the Glaſs of Righteouſneſs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>Evangelium Regni,</hi> a joyfull meſſage of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, Spiritual Tabernacle. The firſt Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation. The Apology for the ſervice of Love, all in octavo.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Samuell Hartlibs</hi> Chymicall addreſſes in octavo.</item>
               <item>Several Peices of <hi>Joſhua Spriggs</hi> in octavo.</item>
               <item>Several Peices of <hi>Jerrad Winstanley</hi> in octavo.</item>
               <item>The Marrow of Moderne Divinity in octavo.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Thomas Butler,</hi> his little Bible of the Man, or the book of God opened in Man, in octavo.</item>
               <item>Crooked Paths made ſtreight, or, the ways of God made known in loſt ſinners, by <hi>A. Yeomans,</hi> in octavo.</item>
               <item>Simmons Saints like Chriſt, in octavo.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>William Sedgwick</hi> his Eleven ſermons Intitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led ſome Flaſhes of Lightnings of the Son of Man, in octavo.</item>
               <item>A Word of Peace from the Prince of Peace, by <hi>J. Hatch,</hi> in octavo.</item>
               <item>Myſteries unvailed, wherein the Doctrine of Redemption by Chriſt is handled, by <hi>Robert Gardner,</hi> in octavo.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:115061:89"/>
                  <hi>Edward Hide</hi> Junior, his book of the Myſtery of Chriſt in us, in octavo.</item>
               <item>Purnels Weaver Shuttle, in octavo.</item>
               <item>His good tidings for Sinners, great Joy for Saints, in octavo.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Biſcos</hi> Glorious Myſteries in octavo.</item>
               <item>The confeſſion and Fame of the Roſie Croſſe, by Engliſh <hi>Philalethes,</hi> in octavo.</item>
               <item>Several Peeces of <hi>Joſeph Salmon</hi> in octavo.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Peytons</hi> Hiſtory of the Riſe; Raign and Ruine of the houſe of <hi>Stuarts,</hi> in octavo.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Larkhams</hi> Sermons in octavo.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Bacons</hi> Catechiſme in twelves.</item>
               <item>Corporations vindicated in their fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall Liberties by <hi>Charles Hotham,</hi> in twelves.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Iohn Saltmarſh</hi> his book of Free Grace, in twelves.</item>
               <item>And his book Intituled Sparkles of Glory, or ſome beames of the morning Starr, in twelves.</item>
               <item>Dawnings of Light, in twelves.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
